<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: filters.xml 9429 2009-07-14 21:11:45Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='caldata'>
  <title>Calibration and uncertainties</title>
  <sect2 id='caldata-overview'>
    <title>
      Calibration data
    </title>
    <para>
      Calibration data can be used to provide correction of measured data
      or perform uncertainty calculations. Generally, calibration data can be
      of different type and different level of complexity. For most of the cases
      user acquires error in each axis, e. g. using a calibrated standard.
      This value can be used for data correction. Similarily, the value of uncertainty 
      is mosttly determined for each axis from calibrated standard certificate and 
      from measurement process uncertainty budget.
    </para>
    <para>
      In more complex case, calibration data can be determined locally.
      Scanner error cannot always be described by only three parameters (one for each axis)
      and its uncertainty is not necessarily the same in whole range.
      For precise measurements it is therefore practical to determine local
      errors and namely local uncertainties that can be used for further
      calculations. By mean "local" we mean here uncertainties that are related
      to certain location in the complete volume that can be reached scanner.
    </para>
    <para>
      To obtain local errors and uncertainties, one can use a calibration
      standard again or use a more complex instrument, like interferometer
      for scanning stange calibration. This is usually done in metrology institutes.
    </para>
    <para>
      In Gwyddion, there is a set of tools helping local uncertainty processing.
      Primary calibration data, related to a scanning stage, can be determined or loaded. 
      They can be assigned to a certain SPM measurement data creating a set of calibrations. 
      These are used automatically in tools and modules where uncertainty propagation calculation can be performed
      in order to provide measurement uncertainty.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='caldata-create'>
    <title>Calibration data acquisition</title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Calibration</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>3D calibration</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
    Calibration data can be acquired in the following ways:
     The module
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>3D calibration</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Create...</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      can be used for creating simplest primary calibration data - based only on
      knowledge of xyz errors and uncertainties and on scanner volume geometry.
      We also need to specify calibration name. Primary calibration data will be
      accesible under this name module for its data application to SPM measurements. 
      </para>
      <para>
      Using 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>3D calibration</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Get simple error map...</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      module, we can determine primary xyz calibration data from a set of calibration
      grating measurements. Here we need to provide several measurements
      of calibration grating for different z-levels of the scanner. This forms
      several cross-sections of the full scanner volume. Providing single grating detail,
      nominal grating pitch and assuming that the grating planarity and orthogonality
      is much higher than that of scanning stage we can determine primary calibration
      data on the basis of correlation. Note that this way of calibrating an microscope
      is only very approximate and its use for metrology purposes is very limited. 
      However, it can provide a lot of useful information about our scanner properties
      if we are unable to perform more complex analysis.
    </para>
    <para>
    Finally, using 
    <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>3D calibration</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Load from file...</guisubmenu>
    </menuchoice>
    we can load any primary 3D calibration data determined by an external device, like set of
    interferometers. Data should be a plain text file containing number of calibration sets
    and sets (x, y, z, x_err, y_err, z_err, x_unc, y_unc, z_unc).
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='caldata-apply'>
    <title>Calibration data application and further use</title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Calibration</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>3D calibration</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
    Primary calibration data obtained in previous steps are related to a scanning stage, not to
    concrete SPM measurements. We can use primary calibration data for different measurements.
    To use primary calibration data for our measured data processing, we need to apply them first.
    Using module 
          <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>3D calibration</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Apply to data...</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
    we can review and select calibration data applied on our height field measurements.
    After applying calibration data a set of calibration datafields is created and
    attached to selected data. A 'C' character appears in data browser as a sign of
    data with attached calibration. Note that the calibration attached to SPM measurement is no
    more related with primary calibration data (that were used for its creation).
    </para>
    <para>
    When there is calibration attached to data, data reading and statistical quantities
    evaluation modules and tools recognize it automatically. Measurement uncertainty
    is then added to the measurement results. Uncertainty is calculated using uncertainty
    propagation law.
    </para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
