<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='data-browser'>
  <title>Data Browser</title>
  <indexterm><primary>data browser</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    Data browser is a window that displays the structure of currently focused
    file.  It shows the content as represented in Gwyddion which may differ
    somewhat from the organization in the original software.
  </para>
  <para>
    Gwyddion supports an arbitrary number of two-dimensional data fields per
    file.  Depending on the context, they are also often called channels or
    height fields in this guide.  The dimensions of channels in one file may
    differ and also the physical dimensions and values can be arbitrary
    physical quantities.
  </para>
  <para>
    In addition, one-dimensional data, represented as graphs, and single-point
    spectra can be present in the same file.  The data browser is a tool for
    browsing and managing all the available data in the file.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-data-browser'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='data_browser.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Data browser displaying several channels.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <sect2 id='data-browser-operating'>
    <title>Controlling the Browser</title>
    <para>
      Since the data browser always displays the structure of currently
      focused file, its contents change as you switch between different
      windows, possibly showing data from different files.  There is no
      difference between native Gwyddion files (<filename>.gwy</filename>)
      and other files.  Once a file is loaded its structure is shown as if it
      was a Gwyddion file.
    </para>
    <para>
      The data browser has three tabs, one for each type of data that can
      be present in the file:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><guilabel>Channels</guilabel></listitem>
        <listitem><guilabel>Graphs</guilabel></listitem>
        <listitem><guilabel>Spectra</guilabel></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      Each list shows names of the data objects and some additional properties
      that depend on the specific data type.  The names can be edited after
      double-clicking on them.
    </para>
    <para>
      Individual channels, graphs or spectra can be deleted, duplicated or
      extracted to new Gwyddion native file using the buttons at the bottom
      of the browser. It is also possible to copy them to another file by
      dragging a data browser row to any window belonging to the target file.
    </para>
    <para>
      The close button in the top right corner of the data browser closes the
      current file, discarding all unsaved changes.  A file is also closed when
      all windows displaying data from this file are closed.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the data browser is closed it can be recalled using the
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Meta</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Show Data Browser</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      command.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='data-browser-channels'>
    <title>Channels</title>
    <para>
      The channel list shows channel thumbnails, check-boxes controlling
      whether the channel is visible (i.e. displayed in a window) and channel
      names.  Right to the name the presence of
      <link linkend='presentations-masks'>presentation, mask</link> or
      <link linkend='caldata'>calibration</link> is
      indicated by the following letters:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><guilabel>M</guilabel> – mask</listitem>
        <listitem><guilabel>P</guilabel> – presentation</listitem>
        <listitem><guilabel>C</guilabel> – calibration</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='data-browser-graphs'>
    <title>Graphs</title>
    <para>
      The graph list shows check-boxes controlling whether the graph is visible
      and graph names.  Right to the name the number of curves in the graph
      is displayed.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='data-browser-spectra'>
    <title>Spectra</title>
    <para>
      The spectrum list shows the spectra name and the number of points in the
      set.  Since single-point spectra are displayed and operated on only in
      connection with a two-dimensional data using the
      <link linkend='single-point-spectra'>spectroscopy tool</link>, there is
      no check-box controlling the visibility.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
