<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='data-windows'>
  <title>Data Window</title>
  <para>
    Two-dimensional data are presented in so called data windows. It is the
    main widget used for working with Gwyddion. The data are presented as a
    field of false colors corresponding to heights. Color axis that represents
    mapping of colors to real height values is on the right side of the data
    window.
  </para>
  <para>
    The False color palette used to represent height data can be changed by
    clicking on the color axis with right mouse button (i.e. invoking context
    menu) and selecting a palette from the list. Most frequently used palettes
    are available directly in the context menu; however you can reach much more
    of the possible palettes using the
    <menuchoice><guimenuitem>More</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu entry.
    Moreover, you can use the
    <link linkend='color-gradient-editor'>color gradient editor</link> to
    create your own palettes and select which palettes should be displayed
    in the short list.
  </para>
  <para>
    There is a context menu available also for the data area. This menu
    consists of basic data and presentation operations. To reach all the
    possible operations use
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Data process...</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>
    menu at the Gwyddion main window,
    or use some of the tools available at the <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> set
    of buttons at the Gwyddion main window.
  </para>
  <indexterm><primary>aspect ratio</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    The arrow in the upper left corner brings the aspect ratio switch menu.
    The data can be displayed either with pixels mapped with 1:1 aspect ratio
    to screen pixels (<guilabel>Pixelwise Square</guilabel>), or with
    physical dimensions mapped 1:1 onto the screen (<guilabel>Physically
      Square</guilabel>).  For instance a sample of size 1×1 μm scanned with
    reduced slow axis resolution and having therefore 512×128 pixels, can
    be displayed either in 512×128 or 512×512 window.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-data-window'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='data_window.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Data window with all three available context menus shown.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
