<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='editing-correction' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title id='editing-correction.title'>Data Edit and Correction</title>
  <indexterm><primary>defect correction</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    There are several modules that enable direct or indirect editing of the
    SPM data. In principal, most of the data processing modules change the data
    in one way or another. However, in this section we would like to describe
    the modules and tools that are specifically designed to correct local
    defects in an image. The functions below remove <quote>bad</quote> data
    from an image, and then fill it in using an interpolation algorithm.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='remove-spots'>
    <title>
      Remove Spots Tool
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_spot_remove-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <para>
      The <link linkend='remove-spots'>Remove Spots</link> tool can be used
      for removing very small parts of the image that are considered
      a scanning error, dust particle or anything else that should not be
      present in the data. Note that doing so can dramatically alter the
      resulting statistical parameters of the surface, so be sure not to
      remove things that are really present on the surface.
    </para>
    <para>
      While using this tool you can pick up position of the spot to magnify
      its neighbourhood in the tool window. Then, in the tool window, select
      a rectangle around the area that should be removed. You can then select
      one of several interpolation methods for creating data in place of the
      former <quote>spot</quote>:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        Hyperbolic flatten - uses information from selected area boundaries to
        interpolate the information inside area.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Pseudo-Laplace and Laplace solver - solves Laplace equation to
        calculate data inside area; the boundary is treated as virtual source.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Fractal correction - uses whole image to determine fractal dimension.
        Then tries to create randomly rough data that have the same fractal
        dimension and put them into the area.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Clicking <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> will execute the selected algorithm.
    </para>
    <para>
      <note>
      Spot removal will only work for regions of size 64 × 64 pixels or
      smaller. To remove larger regions, create a mask using the
      <link linkend='tool-mask-editor'>Mask Editor</link> tool, then use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><link linkend='remove-data-under-mask'>Remove Data Under Mask</link></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      </note>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='remove-grains'>
    <title>
      Remove Grains Tool
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_grains_remove-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <para>
      This simple tool removes manually selected connected parts of mask
      or interpolates the data under them, or possibly both.  The part of
      mask to remove is selected by clicking on it with left mouse button.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='remove-scars'>
    <title>
      Remove Scars
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_scars-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>scars correction</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>strokes correction</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Remove Scars</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Scars (or stripes, strokes) are parts of the image that are corrupted
      by a very common scanning error: local fault of the closed loop. Line
      defects are usually parallel to the fast scanning axis in the image.
      This function will automatically find and remove these scars, using
      neighbourhood lines to <quote>fill-in</quote> the gaps.  The method
      is run with the last settings used in <link linkend='mark-scars'>Mark
        Scars</link>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='mark-scars'>
    <title>Mark Scars</title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Mark Scars</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Similarly, the <classname>Mark Scars</classname> module can create a mask
      of the points treated as scars. Unlike
      <link linkend='remove-scars'>Remove Scars</link>
      which directly interpolates the located defects, this module lets you
      interactively set several parameters which can fine-tune the scar
      selection process:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        Maximum width – only scars that are as thin or thinner than this value
        (in pixels) will be marked.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Minimum length – only scars that are as long or longer than this value
        (in pixels) will be marked.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Hard threshold – the minimum difference of the value from the
        neighbouring upper and lower lines to be considered a defect.
        The units are relative to image RMS.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Soft threshold – values differing at least this much do not form
        defects themselves, but they are attached to defects obtained from
        the hard threshold if they touch one.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Positive, Negative, Both – the type of defects to remove.  Positive
        means defects with outlying values above the normal values (peaks),
        negative means defects with outlying values below the normal values
        (holes).
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      After clicking <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> the new scar mask will be applied
      to the image. Other modules or tools can then be run to edit this data.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-scars'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='remove-scars.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Scrars removal example</phrase>
        </textobject>
        <caption>
          Scars marking and removal example:
          (a) original data with defects,
          (b) data with marked deffects,
          (c) corrected data.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='remove-data-under-mask'>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>interpolation</primary>
      <secondary>of data under mask</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <title>
      Remove Data Under Mask
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_remove_under_mask-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Remove Data Under Mask</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      This function substitutes the data under the mask by the solution of
      solving the Laplacian equation. The data values around the masked areas
      define the boundary conditions.  The solution is calculated iteratively
      and it can take some time to converge.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='fractal-correction'>
    <title>Fractal Correction</title>
    <indexterm><primary>fractal interpolation</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fractal Correction</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      The Fractal Correction module, like the
      <link linkend='remove-data-under-mask'>Remove Data Under Mask</link>
      module, replaces data under the mask. However, it uses
      a different algorithm to come up with the new data: The fractal dimension
      of the whole image is first computed, and then the areas under the mask
      are substituted by a randomly rough surface having the same fractal
      dimension.
      The root mean square value of the height irregularities (roughness)
      is not changed by using this module.
    </para>
    <note>This calculation can take some time, so please be patient.</note>
    <warning>
      Running this module on data that do not have fractal properties can cause
      really unrealistic results and is strictly not recommended.
    </warning>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='mask-of-outliers'>
    <title>Mask of Outliers</title>
    <indexterm><primary>outliers correction</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Mask of Outliers</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      This module creates mask of areas in the data that not pass the
      <xi:include href="eqi-3sigma.xml"/> criterion. All the values above and
      below this confidence interval are marked in mask and can be edited or
      processed by other modules afterwards.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='line-correction'>
    <title>
      Line Correction
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_line_level-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>line correction</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Profiles taken in the fast scanning axis (usually
      <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/>-axis) can be mutually shifted by some
      amount or have slightly different slopes. The basic line correction
      functions deal with this type of discrepancy. Several functions can be
      used: The <link linkend='line-polynomial'>Polynomial</link> and
      <link linkend='path-level'>Path level</link> tools and then several
      procedures under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      menu.
    </para>
    <para id='line-polynomial'>
      The Polynomial tool fits each horizontal or vertical line by
      a polynomial up to the third order and then subtracts the fitted
      polynomial – a very frequently used function in basic processing of raw
      SPM data. It also permits to exclude or include selected area from the
      fit. The inclusion or exclusion only applies to the lines interseting
      the selected area.  Other lines are always fitted using all data
      values.
    </para>
    <para>
      Line correction functions in <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
      perform only horizontal line corrections, therefore one has to rotate
      the image to perform column-wise correction.  They include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <guimenuitem>Match Line Correction</guimenuitem>,
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <guimenuitem>Median Line Correction</guimenuitem>,
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <guimenuitem>Modus Line Correction</guimenuitem>, and
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <guimenuitem>Median Difference Line Correction</guimenuitem>,
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <guimenuitem>Step Line Correction</guimenuitem>.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The first three are very similar, they all align rows of the data field
      to minimize some quantity.  As the names indicate,
      <guimenuitem>Median Line Correction</guimenuitem> matches line medians
      while <guimenuitem>Modus Line Correction</guimenuitem> attempts to match
      line (pseudo)modus.
      <guimenuitem>Match Line Correction</guimenuitem> minimizes certain
      line difference function that gives more weight to flat areas and less
      weight to areas with large slopes.  The effect of all three functions
      is often very similar, although some can be more suitable for certain
      type of data than others.
    </para>
    <para>
      Function <guimenuitem>Median Difference Line Correction</guimenuitem>
      shifts the lines so that the median of differences (between vertical
      neighbour pixels) becomes zero, instead of the difference of medians.
      Therefore it better preserves large features while it is more sensitive
      to completely bogus lines.
    </para>
    <para>
      Function <guimenuitem>Step Line Correction</guimenuitem> differs from
      the others.  It attempts to identify misaligned segments within the rows
      and correct the height of each such segment individually.  Therefore it
      is often able to correct data with discontinuities in the middle of a
      row.  This function is rather experimental and the exact way it works can
      be subject of futher changes.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='path-level'>
    <title>
      Path Leveling Tool
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_path_level-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>path leveling</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>leveling</primary>
      <secondary>along paths</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Path Leveling</guilabel>
      tool can be used to correct the heights in an arbitrary subset of rows
      in complicated images.
    </para>
    <para>
      First, one selects a number of straight lines on the data.  The
      intersections of these lines with the rows then form a set of points
      in each row that is used for leveling.  The rows are moved up or down
      to minimize the difference between the heights of the points of
      adjacent rows.  Rows that are not intersected by any line are not
      moved (relatively to neighbouring rows).
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-path-level'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='path-level.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Path Level example:
          (a) uncorrected data with steps that the automated method may
          fail to correct, two suitable leveling lines are selected;
          (b) the result of Path Level application with line width 5.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <xi:include href='unrotate.xml'/>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
