<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='edit-extended'>
  <title>Extended Data Edit</title>
  <para>
     This section presents extended modules designed for editing (correcting)
     SPM data. Using simple data editing tools presented in chapter
     <link linkend='editing-correction' endterm='editing-correction.title'/>
     it is possible to correct many local scanning defects that
     can be found on SPM images. There are also many error sources within SPM
     methods that lead to global errors, like low frequencies modulated on
     the data or data drift in the slow scanning axis.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='drift-compensation'>
    <title>Drift Compensation</title>
    <indexterm><primary>drift compensation</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Compensate Drift</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Compensate Drift calculates and/or corrects drift in the fast scanning
      axis (horizontal).  This adverse effect can be caused by thermal
      effects or insufficient mechanical rigidity of the measuring device.
    </para>
    <para>
      The drift graph, which is one of possible outputs,
      represents the horizontal shift of individual rows compared to
      a reference row (which could be in principle chosen arbitrarily, in
      practice the zero shift is chosen to minimize the amount of data
      sticking out of the image after compensation), with the row
      <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/>-coordinate on the abscissa.
    </para>
    <para>
      The drift is determined in two steps:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          A mutual horizontal offset is estimated for each couple of rows not
          more distant than <guilabel>Search range</guilabel>.  It is
          estimated as the offset value giving the maximum mutual correlation
          of the two rows.  Thus a set of local row drift estimations is
          obtained (together with the maximum correlation scores providing
          an estimate of their actual similarity).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Global offsets are calculated from the local ones.  At present the
          method is very simple as it seems sufficient in most cases: local
          drift derivatives are fitted for each row onto the local drift
          estimations and the global drift is then obtained by intergration
          (i.e. summing the local drifts).
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Option <guilabel>Exclude linear skew</guilabel> subtracts the linear
      term from the calculated drift, it can be useful when the image is
      anisotropic and its features are supposed to be oriented in a direction
      not paralled to the image sides.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-drift-correction'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='drift-corrected-graph.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Drift correction example:
          (a) original data exhibiting strong drift in the fast scan axis,
          (b) corrected data,
          (c) calculated drift graph.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='fft-filter-1d'>
    <title>1D FFT Filter</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Fourier transform</primary>
      <secondary>1D filtering</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>1D FFT Filtering</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      One excellent way of removing frequency based of noise from an image is
      to use Fourier filtering.  First, the Fourier transform of the image is
      calculated.  Next, a filter is applied to this transform.  Finally, the
      inverse transform is applied to obtain a filtered image.  Gwyddion uses
      the Fast Fourier Transform (or FFT) to make this intensive calculation
      much faster.
    </para>
    <para>
      Within the 1D FFT filter the frequencies that should be removed from
      spectrum (suppress type: null) or supressed to value of neighbouring
      frequencies (suppress type: suppress) can be selected by marking
      appropriate areas in the power spectrum graph. The selection can be
      inverted easily using the Filter type choice. 1D FFT filter can be used
      both for horizontal and vertical direction.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='fft-filter-2d'>
    <title>2D FFT Filter</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Fourier transform</primary>
      <secondary>2D filtering</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>2D FFT Filtering</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
     2D FFT filter acts similarly as the 1D variant (see above) but using 2D
     FFT transform. Therefore, the spatial frequencies that should be
     filtered must be selected in 2D using mask editor. As the frequencies
     are related to center of the image (corresponding to zero frequency),
     the mask can snapped to the center (coordinate system origin) while
     being edited. There are also different display and output modes that are
     self-explanatory – image or FFT coefficients can be outputted by module
     (or both).
    </para>
    <para>
     Note that the filter usually resamples the data to size that fits to
     the available FFT algorithm (FFTW or Gwyddion FFT). As this may affect
     results, the resampled image size information is stated in the module
     window.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='polynomial-distort'>
    <title>Polynomial Distortion</title>
    <indexterm><primary>distortion in xy plane</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Polynomial Distortion</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      General distortion in the horizontal plane can be compensated, or
      created, with Polynomial distortion.  It performs transforms that
      can be expressed as
    </para>
    <xi:include href="eq-polynomial-distortion.xml"/>
    <para>
      where <xi:include href="eqi-P_x.xml"/> and
      <xi:include href="eqi-P_y.xml"/> are polynomials up to the third total
      order with user-defined coefficients.  Note the direction of the
      coordinate transform – the reverse direction would not guarantee an
      unambiguous mapping.
    </para>
    <para>
      The polynomial coefficients are entered as scale-free, i.e.
      as if the coordinate ranges were always [0, 1].  If
      <guilabel>Instant updates</guilabel> are enabled, pressing
      <keysym>Enter</keysym> in a coefficient entry (or just leaving moving
      keyboard focus elsewhere) updates the preview.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
