<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect2 id='facet-analysis'>
  <title>Facet Analysis</title>
  <indexterm><primary>facet analysis</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Statistics</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Facet Analysis</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
  </para>
  <para>
    Facet analysis enables to interactively study orientations of facets
    occuring in the data and mark facets of specific orientations on the
    image. The left view displays data with preview of marked facets. The
    right smaller view, called facet view below, displays two-dimensional
    slope distribution.
  </para>
  <para>
    The centre of facet view always correspond to zero inclination (horizontal
    facets), slope in <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/>-direction
    increases towards left and right border and slope in
    <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/>-direction increases towards top and bottom
    borders.  The exact coordinate system is a bit complex and it adapts to the
    range of slopes in the particular data displayed.
  </para>
  <para>
    <guilabel>Facet plane size</guilabel> controls the size (radius) of plane
    locally fitted in each point to determine the local inclination.  The
    special value 0 stands for no plane fitting, the local inclination is
    determined from symmetric <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/>
    and <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/> derivatives in each point.  The choice
    of neighbourhood size is crucial for meaningful results: it must be smaller
    than the features one is interested in to avoid their smoothing, on the
    other hand it has to be large enough to suppress noise present in the
    image.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-facet-analysis-sizes'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='facet-analysis-sizes.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Illustration of the influence of fitted plane size on the distribution
        of a scan of a delaminated DLC surface with considerable fine noise.
        One can see the distribution is completely obscured by the noise at
        small plane sizes.  The neighbourhood sizes are: (a) 0, (b) 2, (c) 4,
        (d) 7.  The angle and false color mappings are full-scale for each
        particular image, i.e. they vary among them.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    Both facet view and data view allow to select a point with mouse and read
    corresponding facet
    normal inclination value <xi:include href="eqi-theta.xml"/>
    and direction <xi:include href="eqi-phi.xml"/>
    under <guilabel>Normal</guilabel>.  When you select a point on data view,
    the facet view selection is updated to show inclination in this point.
  </para>
  <para>
    Button <guibutton>Find Maximum</guibutton> sets facet view selection
    to slope distribution maximum (the initial selection position).
  </para>
  <para>
    Button <guibutton>Mark</guibutton> updates the mask of areas with slope
    similar to the selected slope.  More precisely, of areas with slope
    within <guilabel>Tolerance</guilabel> from the selected slope.  The facet
    view then displays the set of slopes corresponding to marked points
    (note the set of selected slopes may not look circular on facet view,
    but this is only due to selected projection).  Average inclination
    of all points in selected range of slopes is displayed under
    <guilabel>Mean Normal</guilabel>.
  </para>
</sect2>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
