<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='grain-analysis' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title>Grain Analysis</title>
  <indexterm><primary>grain marking</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    There are several grain-related algorithms implemented in Gwyddion. First
    of all, simple thresholding algorithms can be used (height, slope or
    curvature thresholding). These procedures can be very efficient namely
    within particle analysis (to mark particles located on flat surface).
  </para>
  <para id='grain-threshold'>
    <indexterm><primary>threshold grain marking</primary></indexterm>
    Thresholding methods can be accessed within Gwyddion as
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Grains</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Mark by Threshold</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    Height, slope and curvature thresholding is implemented within this module.
    The results of each individual thresholding methods can be merged together
    using several operators.
  </para>
  <para id='grain-remove-thresholding'>
    Similarly, the grains can be removed from the mask using
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Grains</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Remove Grains</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> menu choice.
    Maximum height and/or size thresholding methods can be used to eliminate
    false grains occurred by noise or some dust particles, for example. You can
    use also interactive grain removal tool for doing this manually.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='grain-watershed'>
    <title>Watershed</title>
    <indexterm><primary>watershed grain marking</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      For more complicated data structures the effectiveness of thresholding
      algorithms can be very poor. For these data a <emphasis>watershed
        algorithm</emphasis> can be used more effectively for grain or particle
      marking.
    </para>
    <para>
      The watershed algorithm is usually employed for local minima
      determination and image segmentation in image processing. As the problem
      of determining the grain positions can be understood as the problem of
      finding local extremes on the surface this algorithm can be used also for
      purposes of grain segmentation or marking. For convenience in the
      following we will treat the data inverted in the
      <xi:include href="eqi-z.xml"/> direction while describing the algorithm
      (i.e. the grain tops are forming local minima in the following text). We
      applied two stages of the grain analysis
      (see [<link linkend='grain-analysis-ref-1'>1</link>]):
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        At each point of the inverted surface the virtual water drop was
        placed. In the case that the drop was not already in a local minimum it
        followed the steepest descent path to minimize its potential energy. As
        soon as the drop reached any local minimum it stopped here and rested
        on the surface. In this way it filled the local minimum partially by
        its volume (see figure below and its caption). This process was
        repeated several times. As the result a system of lakes of different
        sizes filling the inverted surface depressions was obtained. Then the
        area of each of the lakes was evaluated and the smallest lakes were
        removed under assumption that they were formed in the local minima
        originated by noise. The larger lakes were used to identify the
        positions of the grains. In this way the noise in the AFM data was
        eliminated.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        The grains found in the step 1 were marked (each one by a different
        number). The water drops continued in falling to the surface and
        filling the local minima. As the grains were already identified and
        marked after the first step, the next five situations could happen as
        soon as the drop reached a local minimum.
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            The drop reached the place previously marked as a concrete grain.
            In this case the drop was merged with the grain, i. e. it was
            marked as a part of the same grain.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            The drop reached the place where no grain was found but a concrete
            grain was found in the closest neighbourhood of the drop. In this
            case the drop was merged with the grain again.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            The drop reached the place where no grain was found and no grain
            was found even in the closest neighbourhood of the drop. In that
            case the drop was not marked at all.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            The drop reached the place where no grain was found but more than
            one concrete grain was found in the closest neighbourhood (e. g.
            two different grains were found in the neighbourhood). In this case
            the drop was marked as the grain boundary.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            The drop reached the place marked as grain boundary. In this case
            the drop was marked as the grain boundary too.
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      In this way we can identify the grain positions and then determine the
      volume occupied by each grain separately.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-grain-marking'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='allgrains.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Image of grain-like surface structure (a) and corresponding results
          of height thresholding (b), curvature thresholding (c), and
          watershed (d) algorithm.   Within watershed algorithm it is possible
          to segment image even further.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='grain-analysis-statistics'>
    <title>Statistics</title>
    <indexterm><primary>number of grains</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Grain properties can be studied using several functions. The simplest of
      them is Grain Statistics
    </para>
    <sect3 id='grain-statistics'>
      <title>Grain Statistics</title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Grains</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Statistics</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        This function calculates the total number of marked grains, their total
        (projected) area both as an absolute value and as a fraction of total
        data field area, and the mean area and equivalent square size of one
        grain.
      </para>
      <para>
        Overall characteristics of the marked area can be also obtained with
        Statistical Quantities tool when its <guilabel>Use mask</guilabel>
        option is switched on.  By inverting the mask the same information
        can be obtained also for the non-grain area.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='grain-distributions'>
      <title>
        Grain Distributions
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref='gwy_grains_graph-24.png' format='PNG'/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
      </title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Grains</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Distributions</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Grain Distributions is the most powerful and complex tool. It has two
        basic modes of operation: graph plotting and raw data export. In
        graph plotting mode selected characteristics of individual grains are
        calculated, gathered and summary graphs showing their distributions
        are plotted.
      </para>
      <para>
        Raw data export is useful for experts who need for example to
        correlate properties of individual grains.  In this mode selected
        grain characteristics are calculated and dumped to a text file table
        where each row corresponds to one grain and columns correspond to
        requested quantities.  The order of the colums is the same as the
        relative order of the quantities in the dialog; all values are
        written in base SI units, as is usual in
        <application>Gwyddion</application>.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='grain-correlation'>
      <title>
        Grain Property Correlation
      </title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Grains</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Correlate</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Grain correlation plots a graph of one selected graph quantity as
        the function of another grain quantity, visualizing correlations
        between them.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='grain-measure'>
      <title>
        Grain Measurement Tool
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref='gwy_grains_measure-24.png' format='PNG'/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
      </title>
      <para>
        The grain measurement tool is the interactive method to obtain the
        same information about individual grains as
        <link linkend='grain-distributions'>Grain Distributions</link> in raw
        mode.  After selecting a grain on the data window with mouse, all
        the available quantities are displayed in the tool window.
      </para>
      <para>
        Beside physical characteristics this tool also displays the grain
        number.  Grain numbers corresponds to row numbers (counting from 1)
        in files exported by
        <link linkend='grain-distributions'>Grain Distributions</link>.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='grain-properties'>
    <title>Grain Properties</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend='grain-distributions'>Grain Distributions</link>
      and <link linkend='grain-measure'>Grain measurement tool</link>
      can calculate the following grain properties:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Value-related properties</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <indexterm>
                <primary>minimum</primary>
                <secondary>of a grain</secondary>
              </indexterm>
              <guilabel>Minimum</guilabel>,
              the minimum value (height) occuring inside the grain.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <indexterm>
                <primary>maximum</primary>
                <secondary>of a grain</secondary>
              </indexterm>
              <guilabel>Maximum</guilabel>,
              the maximum value (height) occuring inside the grain.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <indexterm>
                <primary>mean</primary>
                <secondary>of a grain</secondary>
              </indexterm>
              <guilabel>Mean</guilabel>,
              the mean of all values occuring inside the grain, that is the
              mean grain height.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <indexterm>
                <primary>median</primary>
                <secondary>of a grain</secondary>
              </indexterm>
              <guilabel>Median</guilabel>
              the median of all values occuring inside the grain, that is the
              median grain height.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <indexterm>
                <primary>minimum</primary>
                <secondary>on a grain boundary</secondary>
              </indexterm>
              <guilabel>Minimum on boundary</guilabel>,
              the maximum value (height) occuring on the inner grain boundary.
              This means within the set of pixels that lie inside the grain
              but at least one of their neighbours lies outside.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <indexterm>
                <primary>maximum</primary>
                <secondary>on a grain boundary</secondary>
              </indexterm>
              <guilabel>Maximum on boundary</guilabel>,
              the maximum value (height) occuring on the inner grain boundary,
              defined similarly to the minimum.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Area-related properties</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Projected area</guilabel>,
              the projected (flat) area of the grain.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Equivalent square side</guilabel>,
              the side of the square with the same projected area as the
              grain.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Equivalent disc radius</guilabel>,
              the radius of the disc with the same projected area as the
              grain.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Surface area</guilabel>,
              the surface area of the grain, see
              <link linkend='surface-area-calculation'>statistical
                quantities</link> section for description of the surface area
              estimation method.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Boundary-related properties</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Projected boundary length</guilabel>,
              the length of the grain boundary projected to the horizontal
              plane (that is not taken on the real three-dimensional
              surface).  The method of boundary length estimation is
              described below.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Minimum bounding size</guilabel>,
              the minimum dimension of the grain in the horizontal plane.  It
              can be visualized as the minimum width of a gap in the
              horizontal plane the grain could pass through.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Minimum bounding direction</guilabel>,
              the direction of the gap from the previous item.  If the grain
              exhibits a symmetry that makes several directions to qualify,
              an arbitrary direction is chosen.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Maximum bounding size</guilabel>,
              the maximum dimension of the grain in the horizontal plane.  It
              can be visualized as the maximum width of a gap in the
              horizontal plane the grain could fill up.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Maximum bounding direction</guilabel>,
              the direction of the gap from the previous item.  If the grain
              exhibits a symmetry that makes several directions to qualify,
              an arbitrary direction is chosen.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Volume-related properties</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Zero basis</guilabel>,
              the volume between grain surface and the plane
              <xi:include href="eqi-z-is-0.xml"/>.
              Values below zero form negative volumes.  The zero level must be
              set to a reasonable value (often
              <link linkend='fix-zero'>Fix Zero</link> is sufficient) for
              the results to make sense, which is also the advantage of
              this method: one can use basis plane of his choice.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Grain minimum basis</guilabel>,
              the volume between grain surface and the plane
              <xi:include href="eqi-z-is-z_min.xml"/>, where
              <xi:include href="eqi-z_min.xml"/> is the minimum value (height)
              occuring in the grain.  This method accounts for grain
              surrounding but it typically underestimates the volume,
              especially for small grains.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Laplacian backround basis</guilabel>,
              the volume between grain surface and the basis surface formed
              by laplacian interpolation of surrounding values.  In other
              words, this is the volume that would disappear after using
              <link linkend='remove-data-under-mask'>Remove Data Under Mask</link>
              or
              <link linkend='tool-remove-grains'>Grain Remover</link> tool
              with Laplacian interpolation on the grain.  This is the most
              sophisticated method, on the other hand it is the hardest to
              develop intuition for.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Position-related properties</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Center x position</guilabel>,
              the horizontal coordinate of the grain centre.  Since the
              grain area is defined as the area covered by the
              corresponding mask pixels, the centre of a single-pixel grain
              has half-integer coordinates, not integer ones.  Data field
              origin offset (if any) is taken into account.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Center y position</guilabel>,
              the verical coordinate of the grain centre.  See above for
              the interpretation.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Slope-related properties</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Inclination θ</guilabel>,
              the deviation of the normal to the mean plane from the
              <xi:include href="eqi-z.xml"/>-axis,
              see <link linkend='inclinations-coordinates'>inclinations</link>
              for details.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Inclination φ</guilabel>,
              the azimuth of the slope, as defined in
              <link linkend='inclinations-coordinates'>inclinations</link>.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <informalfigure id='fig-grain-bounding-dims'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='grain-bounding-dims.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='grain-bounding-dims.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Maximum and minimum bounding dimensions and angles of a grain.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para id='boundary-length-calculation'>
      <indexterm><primary>boundary length calculation</primary></indexterm>
      The grain boundary length is estimated by summing estimated contributions
      of each four-pixel configuration on the boundary.  The contributions
      are displayed on the following figure for each type of configuration,
      where <xi:include href="eqi-h_x.xml"/> and
      <xi:include href="eqi-h_y.xml"/> are pixel dimension along corresponding
      axes and <xi:include href="eqi-h.xml"/> is the length of the pixel
      diagonal:
      <xi:include href="eq-grain-boundary-pixel-diagonal.xml"/>
      The contributions correspond one-to-one to lenghts of segments of the
      boundary of a polygon approximating the grain shape.  The construction of
      the equivalent polygonal shape can also be seen in the figure.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-boundary-length'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='boundary-length.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='boundary-length.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Contributions of pixel configurations to the estimated boundary
          length (top).  Grey squares represent pixels inside the grain, white
          squares represent outside pixels.  The estimated contribution of each
          configuration is:
          (a) <xi:include href="eqi-h-over-2.xml"/>,
          (b1), (b2) <xi:include href="eqi-h.xml"/>,
          (c) <xi:include href="eqi-h_y.xml"/>,
          (d) <xi:include href="eqi-h_x.xml"/>,
          (e) <xi:include href="eqi-h-over-2.xml"/>.
          Cases (b1) and (b2) differ only in the visualization of the
          polygonal shape segments, the estimated boundary lengths are
          identical.  The bottom part of the figure illustrates how the
          segments join to form the polygon.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para id='grain-volume-calculation'>
      <indexterm><primary>volume calculation</primary></indexterm>
      The grain volume is, after subtracting the basis, estimated as the
      volume of exactly the same body whose upper surface is used for
      <link linkend='fig-surface-area-vertices'>surface area calculation</link>.
      Note for the volume between vertices this is equivalent to the classic
      two-dimensional trapezoid integration method.  However, we calculate the
      volume under a mask centered on vertices, therefore their contribution
      to the integral is distributed differently as shown in the following
      figure.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-volume-pixel-weights'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='volume-pixel-weights.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='volume-pixel-weights.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Contributions of individual pixels to the volume of single pixel
          (grey).
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='grain-analysis-ref'>
    <title>References</title>
    <para id='grain-analysis-ref-1'>
      [1] <ulink url='http://klapetek.cz/download.html'>
        Petr Klapetek, Ivan Ohlídal, Daniel Franta, Alberto Montaigne-Ramil, Alberta Bonanni, David Stifter, Helmut Sitter:
        Acta Physica Slovaca, 3 (223-230), 2003
      </ulink>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <!--  Doesn't work well, needs serious formatting improvements.
  <bibliography>
    <biblioentry>
      <biblioset relation='article'>
        <authorgroup>
          <author><firstname>Petr</firstname><surname>Klapetek</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Ivan</firstname><surname>Ohlídal</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Daniel</firstname><surname>Franta</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Alberto</firstname><surname>Montaigne-Ramil</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Alberta</firstname><surname>Bonanni</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>David</firstname><surname>Stifter</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Helmut</firstname><surname>Stifter</surname></author>
        </authorgroup>
        <title>Atomic force microscopy characterization of ZnTe epitaxial films</title>
      </biblioset>
      <biblioset relation='journal'>
        <title>Acta Physica Slovaca</title>
        <volumenum>3</volumenum>
        <pagenums>223-230</pagenums>
        <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
      </biblioset>
    </biblioentry>
  </bibliography>
  -->
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
