<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='graph-processing'>
  <title>Graph Processing</title>
  <para>
    Many of the Gwyddion data processing modules produce graph as an output.
    Graphs can be exported into text files or further analyzed within
    Gwyddion by several graph processing modules. These modules can be found
    in the Graph menu in the Gwyddion main window. Note that the number of
    graph modules is quite limited now and consists of basic modules for
    doing things that are very frequent within SPM data analysis. For more
    analytical tools you can use your favorite graph processing program.
  </para>
  <para>
    In this section the graph modules present in Gwyddion are briefly
    presented.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='basic-graph-operations'>
    <title>Basic Operations</title>
    <para>
      First of all zooming and data reading functions are available directly
      in the graph window:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        Logarithmic axes – horizontal and vertical axes can be switched
        between linear and logarithmic using the logscale buttons.  Switching
        to logarithmic scale is possible only for positive values (either on
        abscissa or ordinate).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Zoom in and zoom out – after selecting zoom in simply draw the area
        that should be zoomed by mouse. Zoom out restores the state where all
        data can be seen.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Measure distances – enables user to select several points within
        the graph and displays their distances and angles between them.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-level'>
    <title>Graph Level</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend='graph-level'>Graph level</link> is a very simple module
      that currently performs linear fit of each graph curve and subtracts
      the fitted linear functions from them.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-fit'>
    <title>Function Fitting</title>
    <indexterm><primary>function fitting</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      The curve fitting is designed namely for fitting of statistical
      functions used in roughness parameters evaluation.  Therefore most of
      the available functions are currently various statistical functions of
      surfaces with Gaussian or exponential autocorrelation functions.
      Nevertheless it also offers a handful of common general-purpose
      functions.
    </para>
    <para>
      Within the fitting module you can select the area that should be fitted
      (with mouse or numerically), try some initial parameters, or let the
      module to guess them, and then fit the data using Marquardt-Levenberg
      algorithm.
    </para>
    <para>
      As the result you obtain the fitted curve and the set of its parameters.
      The fit report can be saved into a file using
      <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button.  Pressing
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button adds the fitted curve to the graph, if
      this is not desirable, quit the dialog with
      <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-graph-fit-screenshot'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='graph_fit.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Curve fitting module dialog
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='fd-curve-fitting'>
    <title>Force-Distance Curve Fitting</title>
    <para>
      The module for fitting of force-distance curves is very similar to
      the general curve fitting module, it is just specialized for
      force-distance curves.  Currently, the module serves for fitting jump-in
      part of force-distance curve (representing attractive forces) using
      different models:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between semisphere and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between pyramide and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between truncated pyramide and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between sphere and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between two spheres
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between cone and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between cylinder and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between paraboloid and half-space
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Note that the curve being fitted must be a real force-distance curve, not
      a displacement-distance or sensor-distance curve. Recalculation of
      cantilever deflection into force should be done before calling this
      module.
    </para>
    <para>
      Also note that for small cantilever spring constants the amount of usable
      data in attractive region is limited by effect of jumping into contact.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-critical-dimension'>
    <title>Critical Dimension</title>
    <indexterm><primary>critical dimension</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Critical dimension module can be used to fit some
      <quote>typical</quote> objects that are often found while analyzing
      profiles extracted from microchips and related surfaces. These objects
      are located in the graph and their properties are evaluated.
    </para>
    <para>
      The user interface of this module is practically the same as of the
      graph fit module.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-graph-cd-screenshot'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='graph_cd.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Critical dimension module dialog.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-dos-spectrum'>
    <title>DOS spectrum</title>
    <indexterm><primary>DOS spectrum</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
        DOS spectrum module intended to obtain Density-of-States spectra
        from I-V STM spectroscopy. It calculates
        <xi:include href="eq-graph-dos.xml"/> and plots it as graph.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
