<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='image-export'>
  <title>Image Export</title>
  <para>
    Microscopy data often need to rendered into image formats, usually for
    presentation purposes, occasionally to open them in programs that do
    not support any SPM data formats.  Both is achieved the same way in
    <application>Gwyddion</application>: by selecting
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Save As</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    and choosing a file name corresponding to an image format, e.g.
    <filename>channel.png</filename> or <filename>channel.tiff</filename>.
    The reference section <link linkend='pixmap-image-keys'>High-Depth Image
    Formats</link> describes the export of data as high-depth greyscale images
    that should be still usable as quantiative data.  For supported formats
    you can enabled it using the <guilabel>Export as 16 bit
    grayscale</guilabel> check-box at the top of the image export dialog. The
    rest of this section discusses the creation of nice images for publications
    and presentations.
  </para>
  <para>
    <application>Gwyddion</application> can render images into a number of
    formats, including for instance PNG, PDF, SVG, EPS, TIFF, BMP, PPM, TARGA
    and JPEG.  Depending on the intent, some may be more suitable more than
    others.  Generally, the following choices can be recommended:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <ulink url='https://www.adobe.com/devnet/pdf/pdf_reference_archive.html'>PDF (Portable Document Format)</ulink>
      for high-quality rendering suitable for printing, with all text and lines
      perfectly sharp and clean at any scale.  Gwyddion also suports output to
      EPS (Encapsulated PostScript) for the same purpose, however, some
      features currently seem to work better in the PDF output.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <ulink url='http://libpng.org/pub/png/'>PNG (Portable Network Graphics)</ulink>
      for web pages, low-resolution previews, thumbnails and icons, and also if
      you have to use a raster image format because it is the only option.
      PNG is a modern and widely supported raster image format with good
      loseless compression and a number of nifty features.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <ulink url='http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/'>SVG (Scalable Vector Graphics)</ulink>
      for subsequent editing and processing.  SVG is a modern vector graphics
      format.  You can open in a vector image editor such as
      <ulink url='http://inkscape.org/'>Inkscape</ulink> and modify it or
      combine with other images – keeping all text and lines perfectly sharp
      and clean.
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-screenshot'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='imgexport-screenshot.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Image export dialog screenshot showing the <guilabel>Basic</guilabel>
        options page.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    The image export options are divided into several groups, as seen in the
    above screenshot.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='image-export-basic'>
    <title>Basic</title>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> options specify various overall sizes and
      scales.  The <guilabel>Physical Dimensions</guilabel> part differs for
      raster and vector images.  For raster images the physical dimensions are
      specified as follows:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Zoom</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Scaling of data pixels to image pixels.  The default zoom 1 means
            data pixels correspond exactly to image pixels.  Upscaling is
            possible with zoom larger than 1, and downscaling with zoom
            smaller than 1.  For data with non-square pixels displayed with
            <link linkend='physical-aspect-ratio'>physical aspect ratio</link>,
            the zoom is applied to the shorted side of the pixel, whichever it
            is.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Width</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Width of the rectangle corresponding to data in the exported image
            (not width of the entire image), in pixels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Height</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Height of the rectangle corresponding to data in the exported image
            (not height of the entire image), in pixels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Vector images do not have finite pixel resolution, therefore, the
      physical dimensions can be instead given as follows:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Pixel size</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Size of one data pixel in millimetres.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Pixels per inch</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Number of data pixels per one inch.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Width</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Width of the rectangle corresponding to data in the exported image
            (not width of the entire image), in millimetres.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Height</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Height of the rectangle corresponding to data in the exported image
            (not height of the entire image), in millimetres.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-dimensions'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-dimensions.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-dimensions.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Illustration of the basic size parameters.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      The remaining size and scale parameters, denoted
      <guilabel>Parameters</guilabel>, are common to both image types.
      However, for raster images they are in pixels while for vector images
      they are in typographical points.  More precisely, this is true if they
      are given as absolute, i.e. the option
      <guilabel>Tie sizes to data pixels</guilabel> is not selected.  If this
      option is selected all sizes are relative to data pixels, i.e. they
      scale together with the image data when the physical dimensions change.
      The parameters, illustrated in the figure above, include:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Font</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The font used to draw all labels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Font size</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Font size, in pixels or typographical points as described above.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Line thickness</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Thickness of lines: borders, ticks, inset scale bar and selections.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Outline thickness</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Thickness of outlines that can be drawn around the inset scale bar
            and selections.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Border width</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Width of empty border around the entire image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Tick length</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Length of ruler and false colour map ticks.  This setting also
            controls the inset scale bar ticks and crosses drawn for the
            point-like selection.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-export-lateral'>
    <title>Lateral Scale</title>
    <para>
      Settings in the <guilabel>Lateral Scale</guilabel> page control how the
      lateral dimensions are visualised.  There are two basic choices displayed
      in the figure below, rulers and an inset scale bar, and the lateral
      scale information can be also disabled entirely.  The inset scale bar
      has the following settings:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Length</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The length can be set manually to an arbitrary value which does not
            result in too short or too long bar.  Press
            <keycode>Enter</keycode> to update the preview when you edit the
            length.  Button <guibutton>Auto</guibutton> selects a suitable
            length automaticaly (this is also done when the manually entered
            length is not found reasonable).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Placement</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The bar can be placed along the upper or lower edge and aligned
            to either side or centered.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Horizontal gap</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Horizontal gap between the bar and the closer vertical edge of the
            data area (meaningful only if the bar is not centered).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Vertical gap</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Horizontal gap between the bar and the closer horizontal edge of
            the data area.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Color</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Color with which the bar is drawn.  Buttons
            <guibutton>Black</guibutton> and <guibutton>White</guibutton>
            allow choosing quickly the basic colors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Outline color</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Color of the outlines.  Note if the outline width is zero (the
            default), no outlines are drawn, hence changing the color has no
            effect.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Opacity</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Opacity with which the inset scale bar is drawn.  This settings
            permits drawing the bar as semi-transparent.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Draw ticks</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If enabled, the bar has vertical ticks at its ends.  When disabled,
            the bar is just a line.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Draw label</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If enabled, the bar length is displayed under the bar.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-lateral'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-lateral.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-lateral.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Lateral scale visualisation types.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-export-value'>
    <title>Value</title>
    <para>
      Settings in the <guilabel>Value</guilabel> page control the rendering
      of values and false colour mapping.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-gaps'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-gaps.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-gaps.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Illustration of the various gap settings (for channel title, in the
          position at the top).
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-fmscales'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-fmscales.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-fmscales.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Rendering of the false color map scale depending on the mapping type.
          For the standard linear mapping, whether full or fixed range, ticks
          with values are drawn.  For an adaptive mapping the color gradient
          is drawn the same, but tick positions correspond to the adaptive
          mapping and interior ticks are drawn without labels (to avoid
          overlapping labels).  If a presentation is shown, the values are
          considered scaled arbitrarily thus no values and interior ticks are
          displayed.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-export-selection'>
    <title>Selection</title>
    <para>
      TODO
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-export-presets'>
    <title>Presets</title>
    <para>
      TODO
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
