<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='image-export'>
  <title>Image Export</title>
  <para>
    Microscopy data often need to be rendered into image formats, usually for
    presentation purposes, occasionally to open them in programs that do
    not support any SPM data format.  Both is achieved the same way in
    <application>Gwyddion</application>: by selecting
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Save As</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    and choosing a file name corresponding to an image format, e.g.
    <filename>channel.png</filename> or <filename>channel.tiff</filename>.
    The reference section <link linkend='pixmap-image-keys'>High-Depth Image
    Formats</link> describes the export of data as high-depth greyscale images
    that should be still usable as quantiative data.  For supported formats
    you can enable it using the <guilabel>Export as 16 bit
    grayscale</guilabel> check-box at the top of the image export dialog. The
    rest of this section discusses the creation of nice images for publications
    and presentations.
  </para>
  <para>
    <application>Gwyddion</application> can render images into a number of
    formats, including for instance PNG, PDF, SVG, EPS, TIFF, BMP, PPM, TARGA
    and JPEG.  Depending on the intent, some may be more suitable than
    others.  Generally, the following choices can be recommended:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <ulink url='https://www.adobe.com/devnet/pdf/pdf_reference_archive.html'>PDF (Portable Document Format)</ulink>
      for high-quality rendering suitable for printing, with all text and lines
      perfectly sharp and clean at any scale.  Gwyddion also suports output to
      EPS (Encapsulated PostScript) for the same purpose, however, some
      features currently seem to work better in the PDF output.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <ulink url='http://libpng.org/pub/png/'>PNG (Portable Network Graphics)</ulink>
      for web pages, low-resolution previews, thumbnails and icons, and also if
      you have to use a raster image format because it is the only option.
      PNG is a modern and widely supported raster image format with good
      loseless compression and a number of nifty features.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <ulink url='http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/'>SVG (Scalable Vector Graphics)</ulink>
      for subsequent editing and processing.  SVG is a modern vector graphics
      format.  You can open in a vector image editor such as
      <ulink url='http://inkscape.org/'>Inkscape</ulink> and modify it or
      combine with other images – keeping all text and lines perfectly sharp
      and clean.
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-screenshot'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='imgexport-screenshot.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Image export dialog screenshot showing the <guilabel>Basic</guilabel>
        options page.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    The image export options are divided into several groups, as seen in the
    above screenshot.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='image-export-basic'>
    <title>Basic</title>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> options specify various overall sizes and
      scales.  The <guilabel>Physical Dimensions</guilabel> part differs for
      raster and vector images.  For raster images the physical dimensions are
      specified as follows:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Zoom</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Scaling of data pixels to image pixels.  The default zoom of 1
            means data pixels correspond exactly to image pixels.  Upscaling is
            possible with zoom larger than 1, and downscaling with zoom
            smaller than 1.  For data with non-square pixels displayed with
            <link linkend='physical-aspect-ratio'>physical aspect ratio</link>,
            the zoom is applied to the shorter side of the pixel, whichever it
            is.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Width</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Width of the rectangle corresponding to data in the exported image
            (not width of the entire image), in pixels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Height</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Height of the rectangle corresponding to data in the exported image
            (not height of the entire image), in pixels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Vector images do not have finite pixel resolution, therefore, the
      physical dimensions can be instead given as follows:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Pixel size</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Size of one data pixel in millimetres.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Pixels per inch</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Number of data pixels per one inch.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Width</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Width of the rectangle corresponding to data in the exported image
            (not width of the entire image), in millimetres.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Height</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Height of the rectangle corresponding to data in the exported image
            (not height of the entire image), in millimetres.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-dimensions'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-dimensions.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-dimensions.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Illustration of the basic size parameters.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      The remaining size and scale parameters, denoted
      <guilabel>Parameters</guilabel>, are common to both image types.
      However, for raster images the values are in pixels while for vector
      images they are in typographical points.  More precisely, this is true if
      they are given as absolute, i.e. the option
      <guilabel>Tie sizes to data pixels</guilabel> is not selected.  If this
      option is selected all sizes are relative to data pixels, i.e. they scale
      together with the image data when the physical dimensions change.  The
      parameters, illustrated in the figure above, include:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Font</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The font used to draw all labels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Font size</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Font size, in pixels or typographical points as described above.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Line thickness</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Thickness of lines: borders, ticks, inset scale bar and selections.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Outline thickness</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Thickness of outlines that can be drawn around the inset scale bar
            and selections.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Border width</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Width of empty border around the entire image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Tick length</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Length of ruler and false color map ticks.  This setting also
            controls the inset scale bar ticks and crosses drawn for the
            point-like selection.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-export-lateral'>
    <title>Lateral Scale</title>
    <para>
      Settings in the <guilabel>Lateral Scale</guilabel> page control how the
      lateral dimensions are visualised.  There are two basic choices displayed
      in the figure below, rulers and an inset scale bar.  The lateral scale
      can be also disabled entirely.  The inset scale bar has the following
      settings:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Length</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The bar length can be set manually to an arbitrary value which does
            not result in a too short or too long bar.  Press
            <keycode>Enter</keycode> to update the preview when you modify the
            length.  Button <guibutton>Auto</guibutton> selects a suitable
            length automaticaly (this is also done when the manually entered
            length is not found reasonable).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Placement</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The bar can be placed along the upper or lower edge and aligned
            to either side or centered.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Horizontal gap</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Horizontal gap between the bar and the closer vertical edge of the
            data area (meaningful only if the bar is not centered).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Vertical gap</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Horizontal gap between the bar and the closer horizontal edge of
            the data area.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Color</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Color with which the bar is drawn.  Buttons
            <guibutton>Black</guibutton> and <guibutton>White</guibutton>
            allow choosing quickly the basic colors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Outline color</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Color of the outlines.  Note if the outline width is zero (the
            default), no outlines are drawn, hence changing the color has no
            effect.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Opacity</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Opacity with which the inset scale bar is drawn.  This setting
            permits drawing the bar as semi-transparent.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Draw ticks</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If enabled, the bar has vertical ticks at its ends.  When disabled,
            the bar is just a line.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Draw label</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If enabled, the bar length is displayed under the bar.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-lateral'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-lateral.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-lateral.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Lateral scale visualisation types.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-export-value'>
    <title>Value</title>
    <para>
      Settings in the <guilabel>Value</guilabel> page control the rendering
      of values and false color mapping.  Two basic settings control the
      rendering of field data:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The interpolation type can be noticeable particularly for
            large zooms.  In the case of vector image formats, the final
            rendering is done when then the image is viewed or printed.  Hence
            the available interpolations are limited to two types. Round, in
            which each data pixel is drawn as a sharp rectangle, and Linear,
            in which values in the rendered image are linearly interpolated
            between original data pixels.  In the case of raster images, you
            can choose from the full set of
            <link linkend='interpolation'>interpolations</link> supported by
            Gwyddion because the interpolation is done during the export.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Draw mask</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If enabled, the <link linkend='masks-introduction'>mask</link> is
            drawn on top the data using the same color as in the data window.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The value scale can be rendered as a false color ruler or disabled.
      The ruler is drawn somewhat differently depending on the
      <link linkend='color-map'>false color mapping</link> type,
      as illustrated in the following figure.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-fmscales'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-fmscales.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-fmscales.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Rendering of the false color map scale depending on the mapping type.
          For the standard linear mapping, whether full or fixed range, ticks
          with values are drawn.  For an adaptive mapping the color gradient
          is drawn the same, but tick positions correspond to the adaptive
          mapping and interior ticks are drawn without labels (to avoid
          overlapping labels).  If a
          <link linkend='presentations-introduction'>presentation</link>
          is shown, the values are considered arbitrarily scaled thus no
          values and interior ticks are displayed.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      The channel title can be optionally added to the top of the image
      or along the false color ruler.  Using the check-box
      <guilabel>Put units to title</guilabel>, the placement of value units
      can be chosen between the title and false color ruler.  Note if the
      no title is drawn then placing units to the title disables them
      entirely.
    </para>
    <para>
      Settings <guilabel>Horizontal gap</guilabel> for the false color ruler
      and <guilabel>Gap</guilabel> for the title control the gaps between
      them and the corresponding image edges as shown in the following figure.
      If the channel title is drawn along the false color ruler the gap can
      be negative, moving the title a bit inside the ruler.  For titles along
      the top edge, negative gap values are ignored.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-imgexport-gaps'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-gaps.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='imgexport-gaps.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Illustration of the various gap settings (for channel title, in the
          position at the top).
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-export-selection'>
    <title>Selection</title>
    <para>
      Any kind of <link linkend='selections'>selection</link> stored with the
      data can be also shown in the image.  If the check-box
      <guilabel>Draw selection</guilabel> is enabled you can choose the
      selection to draw from the list below.  The colors are specified in
      the same manner as for the inset scale bar:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Color</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Color with which the selection is drawn.  Buttons
            <guibutton>Black</guibutton> and <guibutton>White</guibutton>
            allow choosing quickly the basic colors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Outline color</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Color of the outlines.  Note if the outline width is zero (the
            default), no outlines are drawn, hence changing the color has no
            effect.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Opacity</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Opacity with which the selection is drawn.  This setting permits
            drawing the selection as semi-transparent.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Beside the colors, some selection types have further options, for
      instance whether individual shapes are numbered.  If you are using a
      <link linkend='tools'>tool</link> that has some shapes selected on the
      data, the kind of the selection to draw and the specific options are
      preset to match the current tool.  This is usually the most convenient
      way to get the selection drawn as you intend.  However, any existing
      selection can be drawn and the options adjusted manually if you wish.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-export-presets'>
    <title>Presets</title>
    <para>
      Different sets of image rendering options are useful on different
      occasions.  A set of options can be saved as a preset and recalled
      later.  The list in the <guilabel>Presets</guilabel> page shows all
      saved presets that can be managed using the buttons below:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton>Load</guibutton></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Loads the currently selected preset, i.e. sets the image rendering
            options according to the preset.  The inset scale bar length can be
            set to the automatic value if the stored length is not found
            reasonable.  Also the selection type and its options are kept
            intact, only the colors are set according to the preset.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton>Store</guibutton></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Stores the current options under the name given as
            <guilabel>Preset name</guilabel>.  The name also serves as a file
            name so it is advisable to avoid odd characters in the preset
            name.  If a preset of the same name already exists, it is
            overwritten.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton>Rename</guibutton></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Renames the currently selected preset to the name given as
            <guilabel>Preset name</guilabel>.  The preset does not have to be
            loaded for renaming.  It is not possible to overwrite an existing
            preset by renaming.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton>Delete</guibutton></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Deletes the currently selected preset.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
