<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<chapter id='introduction'>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    This guide was last updated to version 2.19 of Gwyddion.
  </para>
  <para>
    The latest version of this guide is available on-line at
    <ulink url='http://gwyddion.net/documentation/user-guide-en/'>http://gwyddion.net/documentation/user-guide-en/</ulink>.
    This guide is available in several languages, namely English, French and
    Russian.
    All language versions are listed on-line at
    <ulink url='http://gwyddion.net/documentation/'>http://gwyddion.net/documentation/</ulink>.
  </para>
  <sect1 id='motivation'>
    <title>Motivation</title>
    <para>
      <ulink url='http://gwyddion.net/'><application>Gwyddion</application></ulink>
      is a modular program for SPM data analysis. Primarily it is
      supposed to be used for analysis of height fields obtained by means of
      scanning probe microscopy techniques (AFM, MFM, STM, NSOM), but
      generally it can be used for any other height field analysis or image
      analysis.
      Gwyddion is Free Software (and Open Source Software), covered by
      <ulink url='http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html'>GNU General Public License</ulink>
      (GNU GPL).
    </para>
    <para>
      The main idea behind Gwyddion developement is to provide modular
      program for 2D data analysis that could be easily extended by modules
      and plug-ins with no need of core recompilation. Moreover, the status of
      free software enables to provide source codes to developers and users,
      which makes the further program improvement easier.
    </para>
    <para>
      Gwyddion can be currently used with Linux/Unix (including Mac OS X) and
      Microsoft Windows operating systems. Both families of systems can be
      used also for developement. For graphical interface,
      <ulink url='http://www.gtk.org/'>Gtk+</ulink> widget toolkit is used,
      therefore it can be basically ported on any system
      that is supported by Gtk+.
    </para>
    <para>
      Gwyddion core developement is currently funded by
      <ulink url='http://www.cmi.cz/?lang=2'>Czech Metrology Institute</ulink>.
      The project started as a part of the Nanomet initiative (covered by
      Euromet) in August, 2004. It is supposed that more persons and
      institutions will participate on developement. Project is open for
      anyone. Welcome…
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id='licensing'>
    <title>Licensing</title>
    <para>
      Gwyddion is covered by
      <link linkend='gpl'>GNU General Public License</link>
      (GNU GPL).  The full license text is also included as file
      <filename>COPYING</filename> in the source distribution (MS Windows
      installers contain it as file <filename>COPYING.wri</filename>).
      In brief, this license means that:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can freely use the program.  You can freely make copies,
            modify and distribute them.  You can download the program and its
            source code from Gwyddion web pages and modify it as you want.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you decide to distribute it, the modified code is still covered
            by the same license.  In particular, you have to offer the source
            code too.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The same holds for extensions, e.g. if you write an import module
            for a new file type or a new data analysis function it has to be
            licensed under GNU GPL (if you distribute it).
          </para>
          <para>
            However, it is also possible to execute third-party programs from
            Gwyddion and these do not necessarily have to be distributed under
            the same license – if they are not derived works of Gwyddion
            (which, admittely, is not always easy to determine).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      The main reasons, why the program is covered by this kind of license
      are here: first of all, this licensing policy enables us to make
      modular program that can be easily developed my many persons from
      different institutions. Second, this license protects the rights of
      developers that their code, here given to public, cannot be copied and
      used for closed proprietary products.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
