<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='logging'>
  <title>Logging</title>
  <para>
    Gwyddion records data modification operations for each channel or volume
    data in so-called log.  When data are saved to a <filename>.gwy</filename>
    file, the log is saved along with them.  The log can be displayed by
    selecting the
    <guimenuitem>View Log</guimenuitem>
    command in the right-click context menu of the channel or volume data
    window.  This is useful for recalling later what corrections you applied,
    how a mask or presentation was created, etc.  It should be noted that
    the logs are informational; they are not intended nor suitable for
    auditing purposes.
  </para>
  <para>
    The log view is live: if you keep it open you can see individual data
    processing operations appearing there as you perform them.
  </para>
  <para>
    A simple log example is shown in the following figure.  For each operation,
    the type, name, parameters and time are recorded.  The type can be for
    instance file import, data processing function or tool application.
    The function names correspond to those show in the module browser
    (<menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Meta</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Module Browser</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>),
    where they are listed in <guilabel>Registered functions</guilabel> for
    each module; or in the
    <ulink url='http://gwyddion.net/module-list.php'>on-line module
    browser</ulink>.  The parameter list represents the settings of the
    function at the time it was used.  Since the log is only informative,
    the parameters may or may not allow a precise reconstruction of the
    operation.  For typical simple operations, they should be sufficient.
    In the case of complex or interactive operations involving multiple
    channels, the log entry may not be detailed enough.  The time is recorded
    in the local time zone when the operation is performed; it is not
    recalculated when you send the files around the world and display
    elsewhere.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-log-viewer'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='log-viewer.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Log viewer showing a simple data processing operation log for a
        channel, starting with file import from an SPM vendor format and
        continuing with the application of data processing functions, tools
        and undo.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    The entire log can be exported to a text file using the
    <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button.  It not possible to modify the log
    entries as that would defeat the purpose of logging somehow, but you
    can clear the entire log with <guibutton>Clear</guibutton>.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='logging-disabling'>
    <title>Disabling logging</title>
    <para>
      In some circumstances, you may wish to store or publish
      <filename>.gwy</filename> files without logs.  Therefore, logging is
      controllable on several levels:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            It can be enabled and disabled globally using
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Logging Enabled</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            When logging is disabled no new log entries are added.  Existing
            logs are not removed though and you can still view them.  They are
            also still saved to <filename>.gwy</filename> files.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The log for a specific channel or volume data can be cleared with
            button <guibutton>Clear</guibutton> in the viewer.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            All logs in the current file can be removed using
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Remove All Logs</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            Of course, if logging is enabled and you start modifying the data,
            new logs will be created and the new data operations recorded in
            them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
