<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='presentations' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title>Presentations</title>
  <para>
    <link linkend='presentations-masks'>Presentation</link> modules do not
    modify the data, instead, they output their results into a separate layer
    displayed on top of the original data. The other data processing
    modules and tools will still operate on the underlying data. To remove a
    presentation, right-click on the data window, and select
    <guimenuitem>Remove Presentation</guimenuitem>.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='presentationops'>
    <title>Basic Operations</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>presentation</primary>
      <primary>basic operations</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Presentation</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      menu contains a few basic presentation operations:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry id='presentation-attach'>
        <term><guimenuitem>Attach Presentation</guimenuitem></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Attaches another data field as a presentation to the current data.
            Note that this useful option can be particularly confusing while
            evaluating anything from the data as all the computed values are
            evaluated from the underlying data (not from the presentation, even
            if it looks like the data).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='presentation-remove'>
        <term><guimenuitem>Remove Presentation</guimenuitem></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Removes presentation from the current data window.  This is
            an alternative to the right-click data window menu.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='presentation-extract'>
        <term><guimenuitem>Extract Presentation</guimenuitem></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Extracts presentation from the current data window to a a new
            channel in the same file.  In this way one can get presentation
            data for further processing.  Note, however, the extracted data
            have no absolute scale information as
            presentation often help to visualize certain features, but the
            produced values are hard or impossible to assign any physical
            meaning to.  Hence the value range of the new channel is always
            <xi:include href="eqi-interval-0-1.xml"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <informalfigure id='fig-presentation-examples'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='presentations.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Illustration of selected presentation filters</phrase>
        </textobject>
        <caption>
          Presentation examples:
          (a) original data,
          (b) shading,
          (c) vertical Prewitt gradient,
          (d) Canny edge detection,
          (e) local non-linearity edge detection,
          (f) local contrast improvement.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='shade'>
    <title>Shading Presentation</title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Presentation</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Shading</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <indexterm><primary>shading</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Simple and very useful way of seeing data as illuminated from some
      direction. The direction can be set by user.  It is also possible to mix
      the shaded and original images for presentational purposes.  Of course,
      the resulting image is meaningless from the physical point of view.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='gradient'>
    <title>Gradient Detection Presentations</title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Presentation</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Gradient</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <indexterm><primary>gradient filters</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Sobel filter</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Prewitt filter</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Sobel horizontal and vertical gradient filter and Prewitt horizontal
      and vertical gradient filter create similar images as shading, however,
      they output data as a result of convolution of data with relatively
      standardized kernel. Thus, they can be used for further presentation
      processing for example.  The kernels for horizontal filters are listed
      below, vertical kernels differ only by reflection about
      main diagonal.
      <xi:include href="eq-filters-sobel-prewitt.xml"/>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='edge'>
    <title>Edge Detection Presentations</title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Presentation</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Edge Detection</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <indexterm><primary>edge detection</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>step detection</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      One is often interested in the visualization of the discontinuities
      present in the image, particularly in discontinuities in the value
      (zeroth order) and discontinuities in the derivative (first order).
      Although the methods of location of both are commonly referred to as
      <quote>edge detection</quote> methods, these are actually quite
      different, therefore we will refer to the former as to step detection
      and to the latter as to edge detection.  Methods for the detection of
      more specific features, e.g. corners, are commonly used too, these
      methods usually are of order zero.
    </para>
    <para>
      The order of a discontinuity detection method can be easily seen on its
      output as edge detection methods produce typical double edge lines at
      value discontinuities as is illustrated in the following figure. While
      the positions of the upper and lower edge in an ideal step coincide,
      real-world data tend to actually contain two distinct edges as is
      illustrated in the picture.  In addition, finding two edges on a value
      step, even an ideally sharp one, is often an inherent feature of edge
      detection methods.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-step-vs-edge'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='step-edge.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='step-edge.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>One-dimensional step and edge schematic image</phrase>
        </textobject>
        <caption>
          Step versus edge in one dimension.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      The following step and edge detection functions are available in
      Gwyddion (the later ones are somewhat experimental, on they other
      hand they usually give better results than the well-known algorithms):
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry id='edge-canny'>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Canny</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Canny</primary>
            <secondary>edge detection</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Canny edge detector is a well-known step detector can be used to
            extract the image of sharp value discontinuities in the data as
            thin single-pixel lines.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='edge-log'>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Laplacian of Gaussians</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Laplacian of Gaussians</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Laplacian presents a simple convolution with
            the following kernel (that is the limit of discrete Laplacian of
            Gaussians filter for <xi:include href="eqi-sigma-to-0.xml"/>):
            <xi:include href="eq-filters-laplacian.xml"/>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='edge-zero-crossing'>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Zero Crossing</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>zero crossing edge detection</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Zero crossing step detection marks lines where the result of
            Laplacian of Gaussians filter changes sign, i.e. crosses zero.
            The FWHM (full width half maximum) of the Gaussians determines
            the level of details covered.  Threshold enables to exclude sign
            changes with too small absolute value of the neighbour pixels,
            filtering out fine noise.  Note, however, that for non-zero
            threshold the edge lines may become discontinuous.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='edge-step'>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>step detection</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Step</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A step detection algorithm providing a good resolution, i.e. sharp
            discontinuity lines, and a good dynamic range while being
            relatively insensitive to noise.  The principle is quite simple:
            it visualizes the square root of the difference between the 2/3
            and 1/3 quantiles of the data values in a circular neighbourhood
            of radius 2.5 pixels centered around the sample.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='edge-rms'>
        <term>
          <guilabel>RMS</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>rms</primary>
            <secondary>edge detection</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            This step detector visualizes areas with high local value
            variation.  The root mean square of deviations from the mean
            value of a circular neighbourhood of radius 2.5 pixels centered
            around each sample is calculated and displayed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='edge-rms-edge'>
        <term>
          <guilabel>RMS Edge</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm><primary>rms edge edge detection</primary></indexterm>
          <para>
            This function essentially postprocesses RMS output with a filter
            similar to Laplacian to emphasize boundaries of areas with high
            local value variation.  Despite the name it is still a step
            detector.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='edge-local-nonlinearity'>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Local Non-Linearity</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm><primary>local nonlinearity edge detection</primary></indexterm>
          <para>
            An edge detector which visualizes areas that are locally very
            non-planar. It fits a plane through a circular neighbourhood of
            radius 2.5 pixels centered around each sample and then it
            calculates residual sum of squares of this fit reduced to plane
            slope, i.e. divided by
            <xi:include href="eqi-1-plus-b_x-to-2-plus-b_y-to-2.xml"/>
            where <xi:include href="eqi-b_x.xml"/>
            and <xi:include href="eqi-b_y.xml"/>
            are the plane coefficients in <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> and
            <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/> directions, respectively.
            The square root is then displayed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='edge-inclination'>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>inclination</primary>
          <secondary>edge detection filter</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Inclination</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Visualizes the angle <xi:include href="eqi-theta.xml"/> of local
            plane inclination.  Technically this function belongs among step
            detectors, however, the accentuation of steps in its output is not
            very strong and it is more intended for easy visual comparison of
            different slopes present in the image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <informalfigure id='fig-edge-method-comparison'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='edge-method-comparison.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>
            Comparison of step and edge detection methods on several images
          </phrase>
        </textobject>
        <caption>
          Comparison of step and edge detection methods on several interesting,
          or typical example data.  Canny and Zero crossing are step detectors
          that produce one pixel wide edge lines, Step and Inclination are step
          detectors with continous output, Local nonlinearity is an edge
          detector – the edge detection can be easily observed on the second
          and third row. Note zero crossing is tunable, it parameters were
          chosen to produce reasonable output in each example.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='local-contrast'>
    <title>Local Contrast</title>
    <indexterm><primary>local contrast improvement</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Presentation</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Local contrast</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      A method to visualize features in areas with low and high value
      variation at the same time.  This is achieved by calculation of local
      value range, or variation, around each data sample and stretching it to
      equalize this variation over all data.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='logscale'>
  <title>Logscale</title>
    <indexterm><primary>logarithmic scale</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Presentation</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Logscale</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Logarithmic scale is used for false colors data presentation.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
