<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='raw-file-import' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title>Raw Data File Import</title>
  <para>
    Both raw ASCII and binary data files and files in unsupported formats
    can be imported with rawfile module – with some effort.
    Raw data import can be explicitly invoked by selecting
    <guilabel>Raw data files</guilabel> type in the file open dialog.
    It can be also set to appear automatically when you try to open a file
    in an unknown format.  This is controlled in the raw file dialog by
    option <guilabel>Automatically offer raw data import of unknown
      files</guilabel>.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='raw-file-import-information'>
    <title>Information</title>
    <para>
      Its first tab, <guilabel>Information</guilabel>, allows to set basic
      file information:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Horizontal size</guilabel></term>
          <term><guilabel>Vertical size</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Horizontal and vertical data resolution (number of samples).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Square sample</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Fixes horizontal and vertical resolution to the same value.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Width</guilabel></term>
          <term><guilabel>Height</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Physical sample dimensions.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Identical measure</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Keeps the ratio between physical dimension and number of
              samples equal for horizontal and vertical direction, that is
              the data has square pixels.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Z-scale (per sample unit)</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The factor to multiply raw data with to get physical values.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='raw-file-import-data-format'>
    <title>Data Format</title>
    <para>
      On the second tab, <guilabel>Data Format</guilabel>, particular data
      format can be chosen. There are two independent possibilities:
      <guilabel>Text data</guilabel> and <guilabel>Binary data</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Text files are assumed to be organized by lines, each line containing
      a one data row, data being represented by integers or floating point
      numbers in standard notation.  Following options are available:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Start from line</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The line data starts at, that is the number of lines to ignore
              from file start.  All types of end-of-line markers (Unix,
              MS-DOS, Macintosh) are recognized.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Each row skip</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The number of fields to ignore at the begining of each line.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Field delimiter</guilabel></term>
          <term><guilabel>Other delimiter</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If delimiter is <guimenuitem>Any whitespace</guimenuitem>, then
              any nonzero number of whitespace characters counts as field
              delimiter.  If a whitespace character is selected, the
              delimiter must be this character.  Otherwise field are
              separated by specified character or string and all whitespace
              around delimiters is ignored.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Decimal separator is comma</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              By default, floating point numbers are assumed to use decimal
              point.  This option changes it to comma.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Following options are available for binary files:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Binary data</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can either select one of predefined standard data formats,
              or <guimenuitem>User defined</guimenuitem> to specify
              a format with odd number of bits per sample or other
              peculiarities.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Byte swap pattern</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              How bytes in samples are swapped.  This option is only
              available for predefined formats larger than one byte.
              Its bits correspond to groups of bytes to swap: if the
              <xi:include href="eqi-j.xml"/>-th bit is set, adjacent groups of
              <xi:include href="eqi-2-to-j.xml"/> bits are swapped.
            </para>
            <para>
              For example, value 3 means sample will be divided into couples
              (bit 1) of bytes and adjacent couples of bytes swapped,
              and then divided into single bytes (bit 0) and adjacent bytes
              swapped.  The net effect is reversal of byte order in groups
              of four bytes.  More generally, if you want to reverse byte
              order in groups of size <xi:include href="eqi-2-to-j.xml"/>,
              which is the common case, use byte swap pattern
              <xi:include href="eqi-j-minus-1.xml"/>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Start at offset</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Offset in file, in bytes, the data starts at.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Sample size</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Size of one sample in bits for user defined formats.  E.g.,
              if you have a file with only 4 bits per sample, type 4 here.
              For predefined formats, their sample size is displayed, but
              it is not modifiable.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>After each sample skip</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The number of bits to skip after each sample.
            </para>
            <para>
              Usually, samples are adjacent to each other in the file.  But
              sometimes there are unused bits or bytes between them, that
              can be specified with this option.  Note for predefined
              types the value must be a multiple of 8 (i.e., only whole
              bytes can be skipped).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>After each row skip</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The number of bits to skip after each sample in addition
              to bits skipped after each sample.
            </para>
            <para>
              Usually, rows are adjacent to each other in the file.  But
              sometimes there are unused bits or bytes between them, that
              can be specified with this option.  Note for predefined
              types the value must be a multiple of 8 (i.e., only whole
              bytes can be skipped).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Reverse bits in bytes</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Whether the order of bits in each byte should be reversed.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Reverse bits in samples</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Whether the order bits in each sample should be reversed for
              user defined samples.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Samples are signed</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Whether samples are to be interpreted as signed numbers
              (as opposed to unsigned).
              For predefined formats, their signedness is displayed, but
              it is not modifiable.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='raw-file-import-presets'>
    <title>Presets</title>
    <para>
      Import settings can be saved as presets that allow to easily import
      the same file – or the same file type –
      later.
    </para>
    <para>
      Button <guibutton>Store</guibutton> saves current import settings
      under the name in <guilabel>Preset name</guilabel> field.
      <guibutton>Rename</guibutton> renames currently selected preset to
      specified name, <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> deletes selected preset,
      and <guibutton>Load</guibutton> replaced current import setting with
      selected preset.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
