<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='selections'>
  <title>Selections</title>
  <para>
    All interactive <link linkend='tools'>tools</link> and some other
    processing methods allow to select geometrical shapes on data with mouse:
    points, lines, rectangles, circles/ellipses.  Existing selections can be
    similarly modified by dragging corners, endpoints, or complete
    selections.  When mouse cursor is moved near to an editable point of
    a selection, is changes its shape to indicate the possibility to edit
    this point.
  </para>
  <para>
    Each tool typically uses only one type of selection and when it is
    activated on a data window, it sets the selection mode to this type.
    Selections of other types than currently displayed are remembered and
    they are recalled when a tool which uses them is activated again.  E.g.
    when you select several lines with Profile extraction tool, then switch
    to Statistical quantities (the lines disappear) and select a rectangular
    area to calculate its statistical characteristics, and then switch back to
    Profile extraction, the rectangle disappears and the lines appear again.
  </para>
  <para id='selection-sharing'>
    Tools that use the same type of selection – e.g. both Statistical
    functions and Statistical quantities use rectangular selection – share
    it.  To calculate height distribution of the same rectangle you have
    selected for statistical quantities, it is sufficient to switch the tool.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-selections'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='selections-vlsi.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Data window with three selected lines, two horizontal and one vertical.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    If you save data in Gwyddion native file format
    (<filename>.gwy</filename>), all selections are saved together with data
    and recalled the next time the file is opened and appropriate tool
    chosen.
  </para>
  <para>
    Pressing Shift during selection restricts the degrees of freedom of the
    shape, making it easier to draw shapes from a specific subset.
    Specifically, pressing Shift restricts
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        rectangular selections to perfect squares,
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        elliptical selections to perfect circles,
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        directions of line selections to multiples of 15°.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <sect2 id='selection-manager'>
    <title>Selection Manager</title>
    <para>
      The selection manager is a special <link linkend='tools'>tool</link>
      that displays the list of all selections in a channel and enables to
      copy them to other channels.
    </para>
    <para>
      For each selection, the tool shows the name, which is how the
      selection is identified in the <filename>.gwy</filename> file; the
      selection type and the number of objects (points, lines, rectangles, …)
      selected.  Usually, there is at most one selection of any type because
      they are shared among the tools as
      <link linkend='selection-sharing'>described above</link>.  Neverthesless,
      sometimes there are special or private selections present as shown on the
      following figure displaying two point-wise selections.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-selection-manager'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='selection-manager.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Selection Manager showing several selections present in the data.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      It is possible to delete individual selections by choosing them in the
      list and pressing <keycode>Delete</keycode> – this is equivalent to
      clearing the selection in the corresponding tool.  The
      <guibutton>Clear</guibutton> button removes all selections.
    </para>
    <para>
      However, the most interesting function of Selection Manager is selection
      copying.  There are two ways to copy a selection to another channel:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        Dragging a row from the selection list onto a data window copies
        the selection to this data window.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Clicking the <guibutton>Distribute</guibutton> button copies the
        selection to all other channels in the file.  Or, if
        <guilabel>to all files</guilabel> is enabled, to all channels in
        all open files.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Selections are copied only to channels with compatible lateral units.
      This means that a selection in a normal channel with meters as the
      lateral units will not be distributed to a two-dimensional PSDF channel
      or a two-dimensional slope distribution.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the physical dimensions of the target data are not sufficient to
      contain all the objects of the copied selection then only those objects
      that fit are copied (this can also mean nothing is copied).
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
