<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='statistical-analysis' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
  <para>
    While analyzing randomly rough surfaces we often need a statistical approach
    to determine some set of representative quantities. Within Gwyddion, there
    are several ways of doing this. In this section we will explain the various
    statistical tools and modules offered in Gwyddion, and also present the
    basic equations which were used to develop the algorithms they utilize.
  </para>
  <para>
    Scanning probe microscopy data are usually represented as a two-dimensional
    data field of size <xi:include href="eqi-NxM.xml"/>, where
    <xi:include href="eqi-N.xml"/> and <xi:include href="eqi-M.xml"/>
    are the number of rows and columns of the data field, respectively.
    The real area of the field is denoted as
    <xi:include href="eqi-L_x-times-L_y.xml"/>
    where <xi:include href="eqi-L_x.xml"/> and <xi:include href="eqi-L_y.xml"/>
    are the dimensions along the respective axes. The sampling interval
    (distance between two adjacent points within the scan) is denoted
    <xi:include href="eqi-Delta.xml"/>. We assume that the sampling interval is
    the same in both the <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> and
    <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/> direction and that the surface height at a
    given point <xi:include href="eqi-coords-x-y.xml"/> can be described by a
    random function <xi:include href="eqi-xi-x-y.xml"/> that has given
    statistical properties.
  </para>
  <para>
    Note that the AFM data are usually collected as line scans along the
    <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> axis that are concatenated together to form
    the two-dimensional image. Therefore, the scanning speed in the
    <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> direction is considerably higher than the
    scanning speed in the <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/> direction. As a
    result, the statistical properties of AFM data are usually collected along
    the <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> profiles as these are less affected by
    low frequency noise and thermal drift of the sample.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='stat-quantities'>
    <title>
      Statistical Quantities Tool
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_stat_quantities-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>Statistical Quantities tool</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Statistical quantities include basic properties of the height values
      distribution, including its variance, skewness and kurtosis. The
      quantities accessible within Gwyddion by means of the
      <guilabel>Statistical Quantities</guilabel>
      tool are as follows:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>mean</primary>
          <secondary>of a data area</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>median</primary>
          <secondary>of a data area</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>minimum</primary>
          <secondary>of a data area</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>maximum</primary>
          <secondary>of a data area</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        Mean value, minimum, maximum and median.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>rms</primary>
          <secondary>of a data area</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        RMS value of the height irregularities: this quantity is computed from
        data variance.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <xi:include href="eqi-R_a.xml"/> value of the height irregularities:
        this quantity is similar to RMS value with the only difference in
        exponent (power) within the data variance sum. As for the RMS this
        exponent is <xi:include href="eqi-q-is-2.xml"/>, the
        <xi:include href="eqi-R_a.xml"/> value is computed with exponent
        <xi:include href="eqi-q-is-1.xml"/> and absolute values of the data
        (zero mean).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Height distribution skewness: computed from 3rd central moment of data
        values.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Height distribution kurtosis: computed from 4th central moment of data
        values.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Projected surface area and surface area: computed by simple
        triangulation.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Mean inclination of facets in area: computed by averaging normalized
        facet direction vectors.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <tip>
      By default, the Statistical Quantities tool will display figures based
      on the entire image. If you would like to analyze a certain region within
      the image, simply click and drag a rectangle around it. The tool window
      will update with new numbers based on this new region. If you want you see
      the stats for the entire image again, just click once within the data
      window and the tool will reset.
    </tip>
    <para>
      More precisely, RMS (<xi:include href="eqi-sigma.xml"/>), skewness
      (<xi:include href="eqi-gamma_1.xml"/>), and kurtosis
      (<xi:include href="eqi-gamma_2.xml"/>) are computed from central moments
      of <xi:include href="eqi-i.xml"/>-th order
      <xi:include href="eqi-mu_i.xml"/> according to the following formulas:
      <xi:include href="eq-statistical-quantities.xml"/>
    </para>
    <para id='surface-area-calculation'>
      <indexterm><primary>surface area calculation</primary></indexterm>
      The surface area is estimated by the following method.
      Let <xi:include href="eqi-z_i.xml"/> for
      <xi:include href="eqi-i-is-1-to-4.xml"/> denote values in four neighbour
      points (pixel centres), and <xi:include href="eqi-h_x.xml"/> and
      <xi:include href="eqi-h_y.xml"/> pixel dimensions along corresponding
      axes.  If an additional point is placed in the centre of the rectangle
      which corresponds to the common corner of the four pixels (using the mean
      value of the pixels), four triangles are formed and the surface area can
      be approximated by summing their areas. This leads to the following
      formulas for the area of one triangle (top) and the surface area of one
      pixel (bottom):
      <xi:include href="eq-area-calculation.xml"/>
    </para>
    <para>
      The method is now well-defined for inner pixels of the region.  Each
      value participates on eight triangles, two with each of the four
      neighbour values.  Half of each of these triangles lies in one pixel, the
      other half in the other pixel.  By counting in the area that lies inside
      each pixel, the total area is defined also for grains and masked areas.
      It remains to define it for boundary pixels of the whole data field. We
      do this by virtually extending the data field with a copy of the border
      row of pixels on each side for the purpose of surface area calculation,
      thus making all pixels of interest inner.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-surface-area-vertices'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='surface-area-vertices.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='surface-area-vertices.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Surface area calculation triangulation scheme (left).  Application
          of the triangulation scheme to a three-pixel masked area (right),
          e.g. a grain.  The small circles represent pixel-center vertices
          <xi:include href="eqi-z_i.xml"/>, thin dashed lines stand for pixel
          boundaries while thick lines symbolize the triangulation.  The
          surface area estimate equals to the area covered by the mask (grey)
          in this scheme.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='sfunctions'>
    <title>
      Statistical Functions Tool
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_graph_halfgauss-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>Statistical Functions tool</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      One-dimensional statistical functions can be accessed by using the
      <guilabel>Statistical Functions</guilabel> tool.
      Within the tool window, you can select which function to evaluate using
      the selection box on the left labeled <guilabel>Output Type</guilabel>.
      The graph preview will update automatically. You can select in which
      direction to evaluate (horizontal or vertical), but as stated above, we
      recommend using the fast scanning axis direction. You can also select
      which
      <link linkend='interpolation'>interpolation</link> method to use.
      When you are finished, click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to close the
      tool window and output a new graph window containing the statistical data.
    </para>
    <tip>
      Similar to the
      <link linkend='stat-quantities'>Statistical Quantities</link>
      tool, this tool evaluates for the entire image by default, but you can
      select a sub-region to analyze if you wish.
    </tip>
    <sect3 id='height-angle-distribution'>
      <title>Height and Angle Distribution Functions</title>
      <indexterm><primary>height distribution</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>angle distribution</primary>
        <secondary>1D</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The simplest statistical functions are the height and slope
        distribution functions. These can be computed as non-cumulative (i.e.
        densities) or cumulative. These functions are computed as normalized
        histograms of the height or slope (obtained as dreivatives in the
        selected direction – horizontal or vertical) values. In other words,
        the quantity on the abscissa in <quote>angle distribution</quote> is
        the tangent of the angle, not the angle itself.
      </para>
      <para>
        The normalization of the densities <xi:include href="eqi-rho-of-p.xml"/>
        (where <xi:include href="eqi-p.xml"/> is the corresponding quantity,
        height or slope) is such that
        <xi:include href="eq-distribution-density-normalization.xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        Evidently, the scale of the values is then independent on the number
        of data points and the number of histogram buckets.  The cumulative
        distributions are integrals of the densities and they have values
        from interval <xi:include href="eqi-interval-0-1.xml"/>.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='first-order-vs-second-order-quantities'>
      <title>First-Order vs. Second-Order Quantities</title>
      <para>
        The height and slope distribution quantities belong to the first-order
        statistical quantities, describing only the statistical properties of
        the individual points. However, for the complete description of the
        surface properties it is necessary to study higher order functions.
        Usually, second-order statistical quantities observing mutual
        relationship of two points on the surface are employed. These functions
        are namely the autocorrelation function, the height-height correlation
        function, and the power spectral density function.
        A description of each of these follows:
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='autocorrelation-1d'>
      <title>Autocorrelation Function</title>
      <indexterm><primary>autocorrelation function (1D)</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>autocorrelation function (2D)</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        The autocorrelation function is given by
        <xi:include href="eq-autocorrelation-definition.xml"/>
        where <xi:include href="eqi-z_1.xml"/> and
        <xi:include href="eqi-z_2.xml"/> are the values of heights at points
        <xi:include href="eqi-coords-x_1-y_1.xml"/>,
        <xi:include href="eqi-coords-x_2-y_2.xml"/>; furthermore,
        <xi:include href="eqi-tau_x-is-x_1-minus-x_2.xml"/> and
        <xi:include href="eqi-tau_y-is-y_1-minus-y_2.xml"/>.
        The function <xi:include href="eqi-w-z_1-z_2-tau_x-tau_y.xml"/>
        denotes the two-dimensional probability density of the random function
        <xi:include href="eqi-xi-x-y.xml"/> corresponding to points
        <xi:include href="eqi-coords-x_1-y_1.xml"/>,
        <xi:include href="eqi-coords-x_2-y_2.xml"/>, and the distance between
        these points <xi:include href="eqi-tau.xml"/>.
      </para>
      <para id='autocorrelation-2d'>
        From the discrete AFM data one can evaluate this function as
        <xi:include href="eq-autocorrelation-discrete-2d.xml"/>
        where <xi:include href="eqi-m-is-tau_x-over-Delta-x.xml"/>,
        <xi:include href="eqi-n-is-tau_y-over-Delta-y.xml"/>.
        The function can thus be evaluated in a discrete set of values of
        <xi:include href="eqi-tau_x.xml"/> and
        <xi:include href="eqi-tau_y.xml"/> separated by the sampling intervals
        <xi:include href="eqi-Delta-x.xml"/> and
        <xi:include href="eqi-Delta-y.xml"/>, respectively.
        The two-dimensional autocorrelation function can be calculated with
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Statistics</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>2D Autocorrelation</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para>
        For AFM measurements, we usually evaluate the one-dimensional
        autocorrelation function based only on profiles along the fast
        scanning axis. It can therefore be evaluated from the discrete AFM data
        values as
        <xi:include href="eq-autocorrelation-discrete-1d.xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        The one-dimensional autocorrelation function is often assumed to have
        the form of a Gaussian, i.e. it can be given by the following relation
        <xi:include href="eqi-autocorrelation-gaussian.xml"/>
        where <xi:include href="eqi-sigma.xml"/> denotes the root mean square
        deviation of the heights and <xi:include href="eqi-T.xml"/>
        denotes the autocorrelation length.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the exponential autocorrelation function we have the following
        relation
        <xi:include href="eqi-autocorrelation-exponential.xml"/>
      </para>
      <informalfigure id='fig-gaussian-acf'>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gaussian-acf.pdf' format='PDF'/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gaussian-acf.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            Autocorrelation function obtained for simulated Gaussian randomly
            rough surface (i.e. with a Gaussian autocorrelation function)
            with <xi:include href="eqi-sigma-approx-20-nm.xml"/> and
            <xi:include href="eqi-T-approx-300-nm.xml"/>.
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <note>
        For optical measurements (e. g. spectroscopic reflectometry,
        ellipsometry) the Gaussian autocorrelation function is usually expected
        to be in good agreement with the surface properties. However, some
        articles related with surface growth and oxidation
        usually assume that the exponential form is closer to the reality.
      </note>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='height-height-correlation-1d'>
      <title>Height-Height Correlation Function</title>
      <indexterm><primary>height-height correlation function</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        The difference between the height-height correlation function and the
        autocorrelation function is very small. As with the autocorrelation
        function, we sum the multiplication of two different values. For the
        autocorrelation function, these values represented the different
        distances between points. For the height-height correlation function,
        we instead use the power of difference between the points.
      </para>
      <para>
        For AFM measurements, we usually evaluate the one-dimensional
        height-height correlation function based only on profiles along the fast
        scanning axis. It can therefore be evaluated from the discrete AFM data
        values as
        <xi:include href="eqi-height-height-correlation-discrete.xml"/>
        where <xi:include href="eqi-m-is-tau_x-over-Delta-x.xml"/>.
        The function thus can be evaluated in a discrete set of values of
        <xi:include href="eqi-tau_x.xml"/> separated by the sampling interval
        <xi:include href="eqi-Delta-x.xml"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The one-dimensional height-height correlation function is often
        assumed to be Gaussian, i.e. given by the following relation
        <xi:include href="eq-height-height-correlation-gaussian.xml"/>
        where <xi:include href="eqi-sigma.xml"/> denotes the root mean square
        deviation of the heights and <xi:include href="eqi-T.xml"/> denotes the
        autocorrelation length.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the exponential height-height correlation function we have the
        following relation
        <xi:include href="eq-height-height-correlation-exponential.xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        In the following figure the height-height correlation function obtained
        for a simulated Gaussian surface is plotted. It is fitted using the
        formula shown above. The resulting values of
        <xi:include href="eqi-sigma.xml"/> and <xi:include href="eqi-T.xml"/>
        obtained by fitting the HHCF are practically the same as for the ACF.
      </para>
      <informalfigure id='fig-gaussian-hhcf'>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gaussian-hhcf.pdf' format='PDF'/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gaussian-hhcf.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            Height-height correlation function obtained for simulated Gaussian
            randomly rough surface with
            <xi:include href="eqi-sigma-approx-20-nm.xml"/> and
            <xi:include href="eqi-T-approx-300-nm.xml"/>.
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='power-spectral-density-1d'>
      <title>Power Spectral Density Function</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>power spectral density function</primary>
        <secondary>one-dimensional</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The two-dimensional power spectral density function can be written in
        terms of the Fourier transform of the autocorrelation function
        <xi:include href="eq-power-spectral-density-fft.xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        Similarly to the autocorrelation function, we also usually evaluate
        the one-dimensional power spectral density function which is given by
        the equation
        <xi:include href="eq-power-spectral-density-1d.xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        This function can be evaluated by means of the Fast Fourier Transform
        as follows:
        <xi:include href="eq-power-spectral-density-1d-fft.xml"/>
        where <xi:include href="eqi-P_j-of-K_x.xml"/> is the Fourier
        coefficient of the <xi:include href="eqi-j.xml"/>-th row, i.e.
        <xi:include href="eq-power-spectral-density-Pj.xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        If we choose the Gaussian ACF, the corresponding Gaussian
        relation for the PSDF is
      </para>
      <para>
        For the surface with exponential ACF we have
        <xi:include href="eq-power-spectral-density-1d-exponential.xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        In the following figure the resulting PSDF and its fit for the same
        surface as used in the
        <link linkend='fig-gaussian-acf'>ACF</link> and
        <link linkend='fig-gaussian-hhcf'>HHCF</link> fitting are
        plotted. We can see that the function can be again fitted by Gaussian
        PSDF. The resulting values of <xi:include href="eqi-sigma.xml"/> and
        <xi:include href="eqi-T.xml"/> were practically same as those from the
        HHCF and ACF fit.
      </para>
      <informalfigure id='fig-gaussian-psdf'>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gaussian-psdf.pdf' format='PDF'/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gaussian-psdf.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            PSDF obtained for data simulated with Gaussian autocorrelation
            function.
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para id='psdf-radial'>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>power spectral density function</primary>
          <secondary>radial</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        We can also introduce the radial PSDF
        <xi:include href="eqi-W_r-of-K.xml"/> which of course contains the same
        information as the one-dimensional PSDF for isotropic rough surfaces:
        <xi:include href="eq-power-spectral-density-radial.xml"/>
      <para>
        For a surface with Gaussian ACF this function is expressed as
        <xi:include href="eq-power-spectral-density-radial-gaussian.xml"/>
        while for exponential-ACF surface as
        <xi:include href="eq-power-spectral-density-radial-exponential.xml"/>
      </para>
      <tip>
        Within Gwyddion you can fit all statistical functions presented here
        by their Gaussian and exponential forms. To do this, fist click
        <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> within the
        <link linkend='sfunctions'>Statistical Functions</link> tool window.
        This will create a new graph window. With this new window selected,
        click on
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Graph</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><link linkend='graph-fit'>Fit Graph</link></guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </tip>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='minkowski-functionals'>
      <title>Minkowski Functionals</title>
      <indexterm><primary>Minkowski functionals</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        The Minkowski functionals are used to describe global geometric
        characteristics of structures.  Two-dimensional discrete variants of
        volume <xi:include href="eqi-V.xml"/>, surface
        <xi:include href="eqi-S.xml"/> and connectivity (Euler-Poincaré
        Characteristic) <xi:include href="eqi-chi.xml"/> are calculated
        according to the following formulas:
        <xi:include href="eq-minkowski-functionals.xml"/>
        Here <xi:include href="eqi-N.xml"/> denotes the total number of pixels,
        <xi:include href="eqi-N_white.xml"/> denotes the number of
        <quote>white</quote> pixels, that is pixels above the threshold. Pixels
        below the threshold are referred to as <quote>black</quote>.  Symbol
        <xi:include href="eqi-N_bound.xml"/> denotes the number of white-black
        pixel boundaries. Finally, <xi:include href="eqi-C_white.xml"/> and
        <xi:include href="eqi-C_black.xml"/> denote the number of continuous
        sets of white and black pixels respectively.
      </para>
      <para>
        For an image with continuous set of values the functionals are
        parametrized by the height threshold value
        <xi:include href="eqi-theta.xml"/> that divides white pixels from
        black, that is they can be viewed as functions of this parameter. And
        these functions <xi:include href="eqi-V-of-theta.xml"/>,
        <xi:include href="eqi-S-of-theta.xml"/> and
        <xi:include href="eqi-chi-of-theta.xml"/> are plotted.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='line-stats'>
    <title>
      Row/Column Statistics Tool
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_graph_vertical-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>Row/Column Statistics tool</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      This tool calculates numeric characteristics of each row or column
      and plots them as a function of its position.  This makes it kind of
      complementary to
      <link linkend='sfunctions'>Statistical Functions</link> tool.
      Available quantities include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>mean</primary>
          <secondary>of a row/column</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>median</primary>
          <secondary>of a row/column</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>minimum</primary>
          <secondary>of a row/column</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>maximum</primary>
          <secondary>of a row/column</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        Mean value, minimum, maximum and median.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>rms</primary>
          <secondary>of a row/column</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        RMS value of the height irregularities computed from data variance
        <xi:include href="eqi-R_q.xml"/>.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Skewness and kurtosis of the height distribution.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Surface line length.  It is estimated as the total length of the
        straight segments joining data values in the row (column).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Overall slope, i.e. the tangent of the mean line fitted through the
        row (column).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Tangent of <xi:include href="eqi-beta_0.xml"/>. This is a
        characteristics of the steepnes of local slopes, closely related to the
        behaviour of autocorrelation and height-height correlation functions at
        zero.  For discrete values it is calculated as follows:
        <xi:include href="eq-tan-beta0.xml"/>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Standard roughness parameters
        <!-- FIXME: Formulas break inside links in dblatex. -->
        <link linkend='iso-Ra'>Ra</link>,
        <link linkend='iso-Rz'>Rz</link>,
        <link linkend='iso-Rt'>Rt</link>.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      In addition to the graph displaying the values for individual
      rows/columns, the mean value and standard deviation of the selected
      quantity is calculated from the set of individual row/column values.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='slope-distribution'>
    <title>Two-Dimensional Slope Statistics</title>
    <indexterm><primary>slope distribution (2D)</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>angle distribution</primary>
      <secondary>2D</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      Several functions in
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Statistics</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      operate on two-dimensional slope (derviative) statistics.
    </para>
    <para>
      <guimenuitem>Slope Distribution</guimenuitem> calculates a plain
      two-dimensional distribution of derivatives, that is the horizontal and
      vertical coordinate on the resulting data field is the horizontal and
      vertical derivative, respectively.  The slopes can be calculated
      as central derivatives (one-side on the borders of the image) or,
      if <guilabel>Use local plane fitting</guilabel> is enabled, by fitting
      a local plane through the neighbourhood of each point and using its
      gradient.  <guimenuitem>Slope Distribution</guimenuitem> has also
      another mode operation called <guilabel>Per-angle graph</guilabel>.
      in which it plots the distribution of <xi:include href="eqi-r-to-2.xml"/>
      over <xi:include href="eqi-phi.xml"/> where we introduced polar
      coordinates <xi:include href="eqi-coords-r-phi.xml"/> in the plane of
      derivatives. The relation between the derivative Cartesian coordinates of
      the two-dimensional slope distribution and the
      <link linkend='inclinations-coordinates'>facet inclination angles</link>
      are given by the following formula:
      <xi:include href="eq-facet-theta-phi.xml"/>
    </para>
    <para id='angle-distribution'>
      <guimenuitem>Angle Distribution</guimenuitem> function is
      a visualization tool that does not calculate a distribution in the
      strict sense.  For each derivative <xi:include href="eqi-v.xml"/> the
      circle of points satisfying
      <xi:include href="eq-angle-distribution.xml"/>
      is drawn.  The number of points on the circle is given by
      <guilabel>Number of steps</guilabel>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <xi:include href='facet-analysis.xml'/>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
