<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='tip-convolution-artefacts'>
  <title>Tip Convolution Artefacts</title>
  <para>
    Tip convolution artefact is one of the most important error sources in
    SPM. As the SPM tip is never ideal (like delta function) we often observe
    a certain degree of image distortion due to this effect. We can even see
    some SPM tips imaged on the surface scan while sharp features are present
    on the surface.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-tip-alltips-scans'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='alltips.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Images of ZnSe surface measured with four different SPM tips
        (more or less broken ones).
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    We can fortunately simulate and/or correct the tip effects using
    algorithms of dilation and/or erosion, respectively. These algorithms
    were published by Villarubia
    (see [<link linkend='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref-1'>1</link>]).
  </para>
  <sect2 id='tip-obtaining-geometry'>
    <title>Obtaining the Tip Geometry</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>tip</primary>
      <secondary>modelling</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      For studying the tip influence on the data we need to know tip geometry
      first. In general, the geometry of the SPM tip can be determined in
      these ways:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        use manufacturer's specifications (tip geometry, apex radius and
        angle)
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        use scanning electron microscope of other independent technique to
        determine tip properties
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        use known tip characterizer sample (with steep edges)
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        use blind tip estimation algorithm together with tip characterizers
        or other suitable samples
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para id='tip-model'>
      Within Gwyddion, we can use the first and the last approach of the
      mentioned ones. Using tip modelling
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Model Tip</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>)
      most of the tips with simple geometries can be simulated. This way of
      tip geometry specification can be very efficient namely when we need to
      check only certainty map of perform tip convolution simulation.
    </para>
    <para id='tip-blind-estimate'>
      To obtain more detailed (and more realistic) tip structure blind tip
      estimation algorithm can be used
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Blind Estimation</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>).
    </para>
    <para>
      Blind tip estimation algorithm is an extension of the well-known fact
      that on some surface data we can see images of certain parts of tip
      directly. The algorithm iterates over all the surface data and at each
      point tries to refine each tip point according to steepest slope in the
      direction between concrete tip point and tip apex.
    </para>
    <para>
      We can use two modification of this algorithm within Gwyddion:
      <emphasis>partial</emphasis> tip estimation that uses only limited
      number of highest points on the image and <emphasis>full</emphasis> tip
      estimation that uses full image (and is much slower therefore). Within
      Gwyddion tip estimation module we can use also partial tip estimation
      results as starting point for full estimation. This should improve the
      full tip estimation algorithm speed.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-tip-alltips'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='alltips2.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          SPM tips obtained from data of
          <link linkend='fig-tip-alltips-scans'>previous figure</link>
          using blind estimation algorithm.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='tip-operations'>
    <title>Tip Convolution and Surface Reconstruction</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>tip</primary>
      <secondary>convolution</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para id='tip-convolution'>
      When we know tip geometry, we can use tip convolution (dilation)
      algorithm to simulate data acquisition process. For doing this use
      Dilation module
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Dilation</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>).
      This can be in particular useful when working with data being result of
      some numerical modelling
      (see e.g. [<link linkend='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref-2'>2</link>]).
    </para>
    <para>
      Note this algorithm (as well as the following two) requires compatible
      scan and tip data, i.e. the physical dimensions of a scan pixel and
      of a tip image pixels have to be equal.  This relation is automatically
      guaranteed for tips obtained by blind estimate when used on the same
      data (or data with an identical measure).  If you obtained the tip
      image by other means, you may need to resample it.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-tip-simulated-convolution'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='fractaltips.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Simulated fractal surface before (left) and after (right) tip
          convolution.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para id='tip-surface-reconstruction'>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>tip</primary>
        <secondary>deconvolution</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      The opposite of the tip convolution is surface reconstruction (erosion)
      that can be used to correct partially the tip influence on image data.
      For doing this, use Surface Reconstruction function
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Surface Reconstruction</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>).
      Of course, the data corresponding to points in image not touched by tip
      (e. g. pores) cannot be reconstructed as there is no information about
      these points.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-tip-reconstruction'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='reconstruction.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Original and reconstructed image of ZnSe imaged by broken SPM tip.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para id='tip-certainty-map'>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>tip</primary>
        <secondary>certainty map</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      As it can be seen, the most problematic parts of SPM image are data
      points where tip did not touch the surface in a single point, but in
      multiple points. There is a loss of information in these points.
      Certainty map algorithm can mark points where surface was probably
      touched in a single point.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-tip-certainty-map'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='certainty-map.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Certainty map obtained from standard grating. Note that the modelled
          tip parameters were taken from datasheet here for illustration
          purposes. (left) – sample, (right) – sample with marked
          certainty map.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      Certainty map algorithm can be therefore used to mark data in the SPM
      image that are corrupted by tip convolution in an irreversible way. For
      SPM data analysis on surfaces with large slopes it is important to
      check always presence of these points. Within Gwyddion you can use
      Certainty Map function for creating these maps
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Certainty Map</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>).
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref'>
    <title>References</title>
    <para id='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref-1'>
      [1] J. S. Villarubia, J. Res. Natl. Inst. Stand. Technol. 102 (1997) 425.
    </para>
    <para id='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref-2'>
      [2] <ulink url='http://klapetek.cz/download.html'>P. Klapetek, I. Ohlídal, Ultramicroscopy, 94 (19-29), 2003</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
