<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='volume-data'>
  <title>Volume Data</title>
  <indexterm><primary>volume data</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    Volume data are three-dimensional data representing, for instance,
    grid spectroscopy (spectra in each image point) or time evolution of the
    image.  So, depending on the point of view, they can be imagined as
    either a stack of identically-sized images or as a set of curves forming
    a regular grid (image).
  </para>
  <para>
    <application>Gwyddion</application> currently offers some basic
    visualization and extraction tools in the <guimenu>Volume</guimenu> menu.
    Volume data windows, as shown in the following figure, provide the most
    basic visualisation of volume data: an <quote>preview</quote> image,
    representing one plane of the volume data or other associated
    two-dimensional data.  The <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> and
    <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> coordinates of the image correspond to the
    <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> and <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/>
    coordinates of the volume data; the <xi:include href="eqi-z.xml"/>
    coordinates can be imagined as orthogonal to the screen.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-volume-data-window'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='volume-data-window.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        A volume data window displaying the associated two-dimensional preview
        data.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    Button <guibutton>Change Preview</guibutton> near the top of the window
    can be used to change the preview image.  The preview can either be
    calculated as a summary quantity characterising data along the invisible
    <xi:include href="eqi-z.xml"/> direction (minimum, maximum, mean, …),
    chosen as a section of the volume data, alternatively just any
    two-dimensional data of the same dimensions can be shown as the preview.
  </para>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
