<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-basic">
  <title>Basic Operations</title>
  <para>
  Basic geometrical operations are the core of any data processing programme. Also Gwyddion
  has a wide set of modules and functions for data scaling, rotation, resampling or profile extraction.
  In this section the main algorithms behind these functions will be described and the list of
  avalilable modules will be presented.
  </para>
  <section>
     <title>Interpolation</title>
     <para>
     A large number of the morphological operations in Gwyddion are dependent on
     data interpolation. As the SPM data are relatively coarsely sampled 
     compared to measured details (full images are typically only a few hundred
     pixels in width and height), the interpolation method used can
     become critical for proper quantitative analysis of data properties.
     There are several interpolation methods in 1D and 2D implemented in 
     Gwyddion and the user can choose which method to use for most of the 
     modules using interpolation.
     </para>
     <para>
     Here, we describe 1D interpolation method principles. Nearly all interpolation methods in 2D are simply composed of these
     methods currently. The interpolation methods that can be applied on data are as follows
     </para>
     <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
	Round interpolation (within API accessed as GWY_INTERPOLATION_ROUND) is the simplest method
	- it just takes round value of the expected position and finds therefore the closest "integer" data value.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	Bilinear interpolation (within API accessed as GWY_INTERPOLATION_BILINEAR) is a linear interpolation
	between the two closest data values.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	Key interpolation (within API accessed as GWY_INTERPOLATION_KEY) is funny.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	Bspline interpolation (within API accessed as GWY_INTERPOLATION_BSPLINE) is funny.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	Omoms interpolation (within API accessed as GWY_INTERPOLATION_OMOMS) is funny.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	Nearest neighbour approximation (within API accessed as GWY_INTERPOLATION_NNA) is a weighted
	average of the closest four data values.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	None interpolation is a special choice within API for doing no interpolation at all as it is expected
	that data (e. g. after resample) will be anyway set by some other function to different values.
	</listitem>
     </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Basic 2D data operation modules</title>
     <para>
     Within basic modules it is possible to perform the following operations with 2D data field:
     </para>
     <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
           Scale data using chosen result dimension and chosen interpolation method by
           <menuchoice>
             <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Basic operations</guisubmenu>
             <guimenuitem>Scale</guimenuitem>
           </menuchoice>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
           Crop data using the Crop tool (at the Tools menu bar).
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
           Rotate data by 90 degrees or by user-specified amount using some of the rotate
	   modules:
           <menuchoice>
             <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Basic operations</guisubmenu>
             <guimenuitem>Rotate clockwise</guimenuitem>
           </menuchoice>, or
            <menuchoice>
             <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Basic operations</guisubmenu>
             <guimenuitem>Rotate anticlockwise</guimenuitem>
           </menuchoice>, or
            <menuchoice>
             <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Basic operations</guisubmenu>
             <guimenuitem>Rotate</guimenuitem>
           </menuchoice>.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           Invert data around X, Y or Z axis using the Invert module:
	   <menuchoice>
             <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Basic operations</guisubmenu>
             <guimenuitem>Invert</guimenuitem>
           </menuchoice>.
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
     <para>
     Moreover, calibration module can be used for changing the information about image physical dimensions and changing
     the data values calibration:
     <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Basic operations</guisubmenu>
       <guimenuitem>Calibrate</guimenuitem>
     </menuchoice>.

     </para>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Profile extraction</title>
     <para>
     Profile extraction tool can be accessed from the tools menu bar. You can use mouse to drag several
     profiles in the image (up to 4) that can be further moved and adjusted. Profile graph preview can be seen in
     the profile tool dialog. Profiles can be of different "thickness" which means that more neigbour data perpendicular
     to profile direction are used for evaluation of one profile point for thicker profiles. This can be very useful
     for noise suppression while emasuring some regular objects.
     </para>
     <para>
     After profiles are chosen, they can be extracted to graphs (separate of merged) that can be further analysed
     using Graph modules.
     </para>
  </section>
</section>

