<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="data-browser">
  <title>Data browser</title>
  <para>
    Data browser is a window that displays the actually focused Gwyddion native file (*.gwy) structure.
    As the Gwyddion native file format supports more channels for height (or other physical parameters) data
    and more graphs to be present in one file, data browser is a tool for browsing and managing all the available channels
    and graphs.
  </para>
  <para>
    As data browser displays all the time the structure of actually focused file, its content is switching
    if the user switches between different windows (belonging to different files).  If user loads new file (any type),
    it is automatically treated as a new Gwyddion file too.
  </para>
  <para>
    The check left of the channel or graph name controls whether it is displayed in a window.  When all windows belonging
    to a file (i.e., showing items of this file) are closed the file is closed too.  The browser displays some auxiliary
    information right to the name, it is specific to each item type.  For channels it indicates the presence of masks
    (M) and presentations (P), the graph list shows the number of curves in the graph.
  </para>
  <para>
    Individual channels of graphs can be deleted, duplicated or extracted to new Gwyddion native file using data browser buttons.
    It is also possible to copy a graph or channel to another file by dragging a data browser row to any window belonging to the
    target file.
  </para>
  <para>
    Data browser can be closed by user and afterwards recalled back using the
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Meta</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Data Browser</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command.
  </para>
  <para>
  </para>
  <figure float="0">
    <title>
      Data browser displaying several open channels.
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="data_browser.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</section>
