<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-filters">
  <title>Filters and presentations</title>
  <section>
     <title>Filters</title>
     <para>
     Filters are often used for data denoising. Of course, this way of altering
     real mesured data has to be done very carefully. These are several simple
     filters implemented in Gwyddion, filter tool.
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
       Mean filter - takes the mean value of neigbourhood of the
       filtered value as the value.
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
       Median filter - takes the median value of neigbourhood of the
       filtered value as the value.
       </listitem>
        <listitem>
       Conservative denoise filter - checks whether the value is not extreme
       within the neigbourhood. If yes, filter substitutes the value by
       of the next highest (lowest) value.
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     <para>
     Note that within the filter tool you can select the region in which filter will be applied.
     This can be usefull for corecting some badly measured area within good image.
     </para>
     <figure>
        <title>Filtering screenshot</title>
	<mediaobject>
	   <imageobject>
	      <imagedata width="700" fileref="filter.png" format="PNG"/>
	   </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
     </figure>
     <para>
     Moreover, there are more denoising fucntions in Gwyddion, for example DWT denoising.
     For details see setion Integral Transforms.
     </para>
     <para>
     If you need to only supress some values at the SPM data that are obviously wrong,
     you can try also the "Mask of outliers" module and some "remove data under mask"
     module. This way should mark only the outliers, e. g. values more far than 3 times
     the squared variance of the data.
     </para>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Presentations</title>
     <para>
     Presentations are special filters that output the result field into
     Gwyddion data container as "/0/view" instead of directly changing
     the field data. Therefore, data window widget can plot the created presentation
     to help user seeing some details on his/her data
     but the data processing modules and tools can use the original data.
     </para>
     <para>
     Currently, the following presentation filters are implemented in Gwyddion:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
       Shading - simple and very useful way of seeing data as illuminated from some
       direction. The direction can be set by user.
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
       Gradient detection - Sobel X and Y gradient filter and Prewitt X and Y gradient
       filter create similar images as shading, however, they output data as a result
       of convolution of data with relatively standardized kernel. Thus, they can be
       used for further presentation processing for example.
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
       Edge detection - Canny edge detector can be used to extract image of sharp edges
       on the data.
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <figure>
        <title>Presentation examples (left to right): shading, Canny edge detection, Sobel vertical gradient filter</title>
	<mediaobject>
	   <imageobject>
	      <imagedata width="1000" fileref="presentations.png" format="PNG"/>
	   </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
     </figure>
  </section>
</section>

