<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<chapter id="getting-started" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Getting started</title>
  <section id="main-window">
    <title>Main window</title>
    <para>
      The main window is the only Gwyddion part that appears after start with no parameters. It consist of set of
      Gwyddion menus: <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu></menuchoice>, <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu></menuchoice>,
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Data Process</guimenu></menuchoice>, <menuchoice><guimenu>Graph</guimenu></menuchoice>
      and <menuchoice><guimenu>Meta</guimenu></menuchoice>, and from several rows of buttons connected with tools
      and modules (accessible also by menus).
    </para>
    <para>
      <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu></menuchoice> menu associates commands that are used for file input and output.
      Global commands (e. g. Exit) are located here too. Submenu command names are self-explanatory (Load, Save, etc.).
    </para>
    <para>
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu></menuchoice> menu constist of commands that are applicable on more data windows
      (e. g. Data arithmetic) and commands that change status of data window presentation or selection. Masks and presentations
      options can be also set here.
    </para>
    <para>
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Data process</guimenu></menuchoice> menu is build automatically from all the modules available
      at the Gwyddion modules directory (depending on operating system). Modules are responsible for all the data processing,
      so this menu item associates most of the commands you will need at analyzing your SPM data.
    </para>
    <para>
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Graph</guimenu></menuchoice> menu consist of commands that are applicable on graphs. Graph processing
      includes reading values of graphs, measuring profile distances etc.
    </para>
    <para>
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Meta</guimenu></menuchoice> are commands that provide information about height field metadata
      (e. g. scanning speed, tip voltage, etc.) and information about the Gwyddion (About).
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, you can find some rows of buttons in the main window. These buttons represent tools and some of the modules.
    </para>
    <figure float="0">
      <title>
        Main window with data view showing microchip surface (Gwyddion sample file).
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="564" fileref="main_window.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  <xi:include href="managing-files.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="raw-file-import.xml"/>
  <section id="data-windows">
    <title>Data windows</title>
    <para>
      Data window is used for 2D data presentation to user. It is the main widget used for working with Gwyddion.
      The data are presented to user as a field of false colors correponding to heights. Color axis that represents mapping
      the colors to real height values is also part of the data window. Color palette used to represent height data can be
      changed by clicking on the color axis with right mouse button and selecting appropriate palette from the list of
      palettes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Graph window is used for 1D data processing. You can get it only by using appropriate tools or modules that
      extract some graphs from height field data. Currently, it is not possible to load graphs into application as the main
      intent of Gwyddion is to provide tools for analyzing height fields, not graphs.
    </para>
    <figure float="0">
      <title>
        Data window (left) with palette chooser and Graph window (right).
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="1000" fileref="colors.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  <section id="modules-tools">
    <title>Modules and tools</title>
    <para>
      Modules are responsible for most of the Gwyddion features. They mostly include data processing fucntions
      as leveling, rotations, integral transforms, etc. See Data process menu for list of available modules.
    </para>
    <para>
      Tools are a special kind of modules that can work with selections. Tools are used for interactive selecting areas
      or lines of the data and processing them. Tools can be lounched only from tools button rows located in the main window.
      Currently, Gwyddion includes at least these tools:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem id="tool-read-value">
        <para>
          Read value under cursor – reads x,y,z values at the position of mouse click. You can average more points around the point
          where you clicked.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-crop">
        <para>
          Crop – cuts part of the data and puts it to new window.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-level3">
        <para>
          Three-point leveling – levels data by plane obtained by clicking on three points wihin data window.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-stats">
        <para>
          Statistical quantities – computes basic statistical quantities (RMS, Ra, etc.) from selection of full data
          field.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-sfunctions">
        <para>
          Statistical functions – computes basic statistical functions (distribution of heights, autocorrelation
          function, etc.) from selection of full data field.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-profile">
        <para>
          Profile extraction – extracts profiles of the data field and puts them to separate graphs. These graphs can
          be further processed with commands from the Graph menu.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-distance">
        <para>
          Measure distances – similarly to Read value tool enables user to read distance and angle between points in
          the data field.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-polynom">
        <para>
          Fit X/Y profiles by polynom – very frequently used tool for basic processing of raw SPM data. Profiles
          taken in the fast scanning axis (usually X-axis) can be mutually shifted by some amount or having slightly
          different slope. Fit X/Y profiles tool can fix this discrepancy.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-filters">
        <para>
          Basic filters – mean, median, conservative denoise and similar simple filters to reduce noise in the data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-remove-grains">
        <para>
          Manually remove grains – remove continuous parts of the mask by clicking on mask point.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-remove-spots">
        <para>
          Manually remove spots – draw rectangle around defect in AFM data image and remove the defect using chosen
          interpolation method.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="tool-color-range">
        <para>
          Stretch color range – enables user to change the false color representation range (by default from data
          minimum to data maximum).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="selections">
    <title>Working with selections</title>
    <para>
      All interactive <link linkend="modules-tools">tools</link> and some other processing methods allow to select
      geometrical shapes on data with mouse: points, lines, rectangles, circles/ellipses.  Existing selections can
      be similarly modified by dragging corners, endpoints, or complete selections.  When mouse cursor is moved
      near to an editable point of a selection, is changes its shape to indicate the possibility to edit this point.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each tool generally uses only one type of selection and when it is activated on a data window, it sets the
      selection mode to this type.  Selections of other types than currently displayed are remembered and they
      are recalled when a tool which uses them is activated again.  E.g., when you select several lines with Profile
      extraction tool, then switch to Statistical quantities (the lines disappear) and select a rectangular area to
      calculate statistical characteristics of, and then switch back to Profile extraction, the rectangle disappears
      and the lines appear again.
    </para>
    <para>
      Tools that use the same type of selection – e.g., both Statistical functions and Statistical quantities use
      rectangular selection – share it.  To calculate height distribution of the same rectangle you have
      selected for statistical quantities, it is sufficient to switch the tool.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you save data in Gwyddion native file format (.gwy), all selections are saved together with data and
      recalled the next time the file is opened and appropriate tool chosen.
    </para>
    <para>
      <!-- FIXME: This is actually true only in 2.0 -->
      Pressing Shift during selection restricts the degrees of freedom of the shape, making it easier to draw shapes
      form a specific subset.  E.g., pressing Shift restricts rectanglular selections to perfect squares, or it
      restricts line directions to multiples of 15 ° in line selections.
    </para>
    <figure float="0">
      <title>
        Data window with three selected lines, two horizontal and one vertical.
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="369" fileref="selections-vlsi.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  <section id="presentations-masks">
    <title>Presentations and masks</title>
    <para>
      Presentations can be used to show the height field in other way than as false colors map of heights. Several
      presentation methods are implemented, including shading, gradient filters and edge detectors. When you use data
      with superposed presentation within data processing modules or tools the results will be computed from original
      data – presentation is thus only visualization mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      Masks are used for displaying special areal selections (e. g. grains). Masks can have any shape and within data
      window can be expressed by any chosen color. Masks can be created by different modules or directly by user
      using Mask selection tool.  It it possible to invert, grow, and shrink masks, or extract them to a separate
      data window using module functions in
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Mask</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menu.
    </para>
    <figure float="0">
      <title>
        Data in default false color representation (left), with superposed mask (centre) and with shading presentation (right).
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="858" fileref="mask.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  <section id="plugins">
    <title>Plugins</title>
    <para>
      Plug-ins are external programs that can be executed by Gwyddion to either perform some operation on the data or to read
      or write data in a third-party file format. In general, plug-ins are programe that can register itself within Gwyddion
      (for example printing something on standard output) to enable Gwyddion to create plugin menu choice and can be used
      for data processing (or IO operation).
    </para>
    <para>
      Generally it is preferable to extend Gwyddion functionality by modules, because modules are dynamic libraries linked
      directly to Gwyddion at run-time allowing much more versatile interaction with the application, and they are also faster
      (for the same reason). For example, plug-ins generally cannot make use of existing Gwyddion data processing functions
      and cannot modify data in-place, a new window is always created for the result. Programming of modules is also no
      harder than programming of plug-ins, maybe it is even easier (assuming you know C).
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
