<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-graph">
  <title>Graph processing</title>
  <para>
  Many of the Gwyddion data processing modules produce graph as a output.
  Graphs can be exported into ASCII files or further analyzed within Gwyddion by
  several graph processing modules. These modules can be found in the Graph
  menu in the Gwyddion main window. Note that the number of graph modules is
  really limited now and consists of basic modules for doing things that
  are very frequent within SPM data analysis. For more analytical tools
  you can use your favorite graph processing program.
  </para>  
  <para>
  In this section the graph modules present in Gwyddion are shortly presented
  </para>
  <section>
     <title>Basic operations</title>
     <para>
     First of all there are zooming and data reading modules in Graph menu. 
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
	Zoom in and zoom out - simply draw are that should be zoomed by mouse
	and zoom. Zoom out restores state whne all data can be seen.
	</listitem>
        <listitem>
	Read value - prints X and Y value under cursor
	</listitem>
        <listitem>
	Measure distances - enables user to select several points within graph and
	prints out their distances and angles between them.
	</listitem>		
     </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Fit graph</title>
     <para>
     This module is designed namely for fitting the statistical function by means of
     functions mostly used in roughness parameters evaluation. This influences
     the possible functions to be fitted that are currently namely various statistical
     functions for surface having Gaussian or exponential autocorrelation function.
     </para>
     <para>
     Within fit module you can select area that should be fitted (by mouse or by entries),
     try some initial parameters (or let the module to guess them) and fit the data
     using Marquardt-Levenberg algorithm.
     </para>
     <para>
     As a result you obtain fit and set of its parameters. These can be saved into a file.
     </para>
     <figure>
       <title>Fit graph module screenshot</title>
       <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
	   <imagedata fileref="graph_fit.png" format="PNG"/>
	 </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </figure>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Critical dimension</title>
     <para>
     Critical dimension module can be used to fit some "typical" objects that
     can be often found while analyzing microchips and related surfaces. These
     objects are found in the graph and their properties are evaluated.
     </para>
     <para>
     User interface of this module is practically same as for the graph fit module.
     </para>
     <figure>
       <title>Critical dimension module screenshot</title>
       <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
	   <imagedata fileref="graph_cd.png" format="PNG"/>
	 </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </figure>
  </section>
</section>

