<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>

  <!-- TODO: This needs to go somewhere.
  <section>
    <title>FFT Filters</title>
    <para>
      Sometimes it is useful to be able to filter an image in the frequency
      domain rather than in the spatial domain. To accomplish this, Gwyddion
      takes the Fast Fourier Transform (FFT) of the image, applies the user's
      filter, and then performs the inverse FFT.      
      <emphasis>TODO: Talk more about why this happens, give examples. </emphasis>
      Gwyddion has two modules
      
      One excellent way of removing this type of noise from an image is to
      use Fourier filtering. First, the Fourier transform of the image is
      calculated. Next, a filter is applied to this transform. Finally, the
      inverse transform is applied to obtain a filtered image. Gwyddion uses
      the Fast Fourier Transform (or FFT) to make this intensive calculation
      much faster. There are two FFT filtering modules, the
      <classname>1D FFT Filter</classname> and the
      <classname>2D FFT Filter</classname>.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>1D FFT Filter</title>
      <para>
        <emphasis>TODO: Info about 1D FFT Filter goes here</emphasis>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>2D FFT Filter</title>
      <para>
        <emphasis>TODO: Info about 2D FFT Filter goes here (chris will do)</emphasis>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section> -->

<section id="features-inttrans">
  <title>Integral transforms</title>
  <para>
    Currently, two different integral transforms can be used within Gwyddion
    for 2D data processing.
  </para>
  <para>
    Integral transforms and related modules can be accessed from menu as
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Integral Transforms</guisubmenu>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Fourier transform</title>
    <para>
      Fourier transform can be accessed within FFT module which implements Fast Fourier transform.
      Fourier transform decomposes signal into its harmonic compoments, it is therefore useful while studying
      spectral frequencies present in the SPM data.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that the Fourier transform treats data as being infinite, thus implying some cyclic boundary conditions.
      As the real data do not have these properties, it is necessary to use some windowing function to suppress
      the data at the edgest of the image. If you don't do this, FFT treats data as being windowed by rectangular
      windowing function which has really bad  Fourier image thus leading to corruption of the Fourier spectrum.
    </para>
    <para>
      Winhin Gwyddion several windowing functions are implemented. Most of them are formed by some sine and cosine
      functions that damp data correctly at the edges. Windowing function can be set within the Fourier Transform module.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Wavelet transform</title>
    <para>
      The wavelet transform is a transform similar to the Fourier transform (or much more to the windowed Fourier transform)
      with a completely different merit function. The main difference is this: Fourier transform decomposes the signal into
      sines and cosines - e. g. the functions localized in Fourier space; in contrary the wavelet transform uses functions
      that are localized in both the real and Fourier space. Generally, the wavelet transform can be expressed by the following
      equation:
    </para>
    <informalequation>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="eq-wavelet-transform-continuous.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalequation>
    <para>
      where the * is the complex conjugate symbol and function &psi; is some function which can be different obeying some rules.
    </para>
    <para>
      As it is seen, the Wavelet transform is in fact an infinite set of various transforms, depending on the merit function used
      for its computation. This is the main reason, why we can hear the term "wavelet transform" in very different situations and
      applications. There are also many ways how to sort the types of the wavelet transforms. Here we show only the division based
      on the wavelet orthogonality. We can use <emphasis>orthogonal wavelets</emphasis> for discrete wavelet transform development
      and <emphasis>non-orthogonal wavelets</emphasis> for continuous wavelet transform developement. These two transforms have
      the following properties:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        The discrete wavelet transform returns a data vector of the same length as the input is. Usually, even in this vector
        many data are almost zero. This corresponds to the fact that it decomposes into a set of wavelets (functions) that are
        orthogonal to its translations and scaling. Therefore we decompose such a signal to a same or lower number of the wavelet
        coefficient spectrum as is the number of signal data points. Such a wavelet spectrum is very good for signal processing
        and compression, for example, as we get no redundant information here.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        The continuous wavelet transform in contrary returns an array one dimension larger thatn the input data.
        For a 1D data we obtain an image of the time-frequecy plane. We can easily see the signal frequencies evolution
        during the duration of the signal and compare the spectrum with other signals spertra. As here is used the non-orthogonal
        set of wavelets, data are correlated highly, so big redundancy is seen here. This helps to see the results in a more humane form.
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      For more details on wavelet transorm see any of the thousands of wavelet resources on the Web, or for example Ref. 1.
    </para>
    <para>
      Within Gwyddion data processing library, both these transforms are implemented and the modules using wavelet transforms can be
      accessed within
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Integral Transforms</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      menu.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Discrete wavelet transform</title>
      <para>
        The discrete wavelet transform (DWT) is an implementation of the wavelet transform using a discrete set of the wavelet scales
        and translations obeying some defined rules. In other words, this transform decomposes the signal into mutually orthogonal set
        of wavelets, which is the main difference from the continuous wavelet transform (CWT), or its implementation for the discrete
        time series sometimes called discrete-time continuous wavelet transform (DT-CWT).
      </para>
      <para>
        The wavelet can be constructed from a scaling function which describes its scaling properties. The restriction that the scaling
        functions must be orthogonal to its discrete translations implies some mathematical conditions on them which are mentioned everywhere
        e. g. the dilation equation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-wavelet-dilation-equation.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where S is a scaling factor (usually chosen as 2). Moreover, the area between the function must be normalized and
        scaling function must be ortogonal to its integer translates e. g.
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-wavelet-orthogonality.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        After introducing some more conditions (as the restrictions above does not produce unique solution) we can obtain results of all
        this equations, e. g. finite set of coefficients a_k which define the scaling function and also the wavelet. The wavelet is obtained
        from the scaling function as
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-wavelet-expression-scaling-func.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where N is an even integer. The set of wavelets than forms an orthonormal basis which we use to decompose signal. Note
        that usually only few of the coefficients a_k are nonzero which simplifies the calculations.
      </para>
      <para>
        In the following figure, some wavelet scaling functions and wavelets are plotted. The most known family of orthonormal wavelets
        is a family of Daubechies. Her wavelets are usually denominated by the number of nonzero coefficients a_k, so we usually talk
        about Daubechies 4, Daubechies 6 etc. wavelets Roughly said, with the increasing number of wavelet coeficients the functions
        become more smooth. See the comparison of wavelets Daubechies 4 and 20 below. Another mentioned wavelet is the simplest one,
        the Haar wavelet, which uses a box function as the scaling function.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Haar scaling function (left) and wavelet (right).</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="whaar.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <title>Daubechies 4 scaling function (left) and wavelet (right).</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wdaub4.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <title>Daubechies 20 scaling function (left) and wavelet (right).</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wdaub20.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        There are several types of implementation of the DWT algorithm. The oldest and most known one is the Malaat (pyramidal) algoritm.
        In this algorithm two filters - smoothing and non-smoothing one are constructed from the wavelet coefficients and those filters
        are recurrently used to obtain data for all the scales. If the total number of data D=2<superscript>N</superscript> is
        used and signal length is L, first
        D/2 data at scale L/2<superscript>(N-1)</superscript> are computed, than (D/2)/2 data at scale
        L/2<superscript>(N-2)</superscript>, ... etc up to finally obtaining 2 data at scale
        L/2. The result of this algorithm is an array of the same length as the input one, where the data are usually sorted from the
        largest scales to the smallest ones.
      </para>
      <para>
        Within Gwyddion the pyramidal algorithm is used for computing the discrete wavelet transform. Discrete wavelet transform in 2D can be
        accessed using DWT module.
      </para>
      <para>
        Discrete wavelet transform can be used for easy and fast denoising of a noisy signal. If we take only a limited number of
        highest coefficients of the discrete wavelet transform spectrum, and we perform an inverse transform (with the same wavelet basis)
        we can obtain more or less denoised signal. There are several ways how to choose the coefficients that will be keeped.
        Within Gwyddion, the universal thresholding, scale adaptive thresholding [2] and scale and space adaptive thresholding [3] is implemented.
        For threshold determination within these methods we first determine the noise variance
        guess given by
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-wavelet-variance-guess.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where $Y_{ij}$ corresponds to all the coefficients of the highst scale subband of the decomposition
        (where most of the noise is assumend to be present). Alternatively, the noise variance can be obtained
        in an independent way, for example from the AFM signal variance while not scanning.
        For the highest frequency subband (universal thresholding) or for each subband (for scale adaptive thresholding)
        or for each pixel neighbourhood within subband
        (for scale and space adaptive thresholding) the variance is the computed as
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-wavelet-variance-sum.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        Treshold value is finally computed as
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-wavelet-threshold-value.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where
        <informalequation>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="eq-wavelet-sigma-X.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalequation>
        When threshold for given scale is known, we can remove all the coefficients smaller than threshold value
        (hard thresholding) or we can lower the absolute value of these coefficients by threshold value (soft thresholding).
      </para>
      <para>
        DWT denoising can be accessed within the DWT denoise module.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Continuous wavelet transform</title>
      <para>
        Continuous wavelet transform (CWT) is an implementaion of the wavelet transform using an arbitrary scales and almost arbitrary
        wavelets. The wavelets used are not orthogonal and the data obtained by this transform are highly correlated. For the disctete
        time series we can uset this transform as well, with the limitation that the smallest wavelet translations must be equal to the
        data sampling. This is sometimes called Discrete Time Continuous Wavelet Transform (DT-CWT) and it is the mostly used way of
        computing CWT in real applications.
      </para>
      <para>
        In principle the continuous wavelet transform works by using directly the definition of the wavelet transform -
        e. g. we are computing a convolution of the signal with the scaled wavelet. For each scale we obtain by this way an array of the
        same length N as the signal has. By using M arbitrarily chosen scales we obtain a field NxM which represents the time-frequency
        plane directly. The algoritm used for this computaion can be based on a direct convolution or on a convolution by means of
        multiplication in Fourier space (this is sometimes called Fast wavelet transform).
      </para>
      <para>
        The choice of the wavelet that is used for time-frequency decomposition is the most important thing. By this choice we can inlfuence
        the time and frequency resolution of the result. We cannot change the main features of WT by this way
        (low frequencies have good frequecny and bad time resolution; high frequencies have good time and bad frequency resolution),
        but we can somehow increase the total frequency of total time resolution. This is directly proportional to the width of the
        used wavelet in real and Fourier space. If we use the Morlet wavelet for example (real part - damped cosine function) we can expect high
        frequency resolution as such a wavelet is very well localized in frequencies. In contrary, using Derivative of Gaussian (DOG) wavelet
        will result in good time localization, but poor one in frequencies.
      </para>
      <para>
        Within Gwyddion, several 2D wavelets are implemented within CWT module.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>References</title>
    <para>
      [1] A. Bultheel: Bull. Belg. Math. Soc.: (1995)  2
    </para>
    <para>
      [2] S. G. Chang, B. Yu, M. Vetterli: IEEE Trans. Image Processing, (2000) 9 p. 1532
    </para>
    <para>
      [3] S. G. Chang, B. Yu, M. Vetterli: IEEE Trans. Image Processing, (2000) 9 p. 1522
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

