<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-leveling">
  <title>Data Leveling and Background Subtraction</title>
  <section>
    <title>Leveling</title>
    <para>
      Data obtained from SPM microscope are very often not leveled at all -
      microscope outputs directly raw data values computed from piezoscanner voltage,
      strain gauge, interferometer or other detection system values. This way of exporting
      data enables user to choose his/her own way of leveling data.
    </para>
    <para>
      Choosing the leveling mode should be done depending on your SPM system configuration.
      Basically, for systems with independent scanner(s) for each axis plane leveling should
      be sufficient and for systems with scanner(s) moving in all three axes (tube scanners)
      2nd order polynomial leveling should be used.
    </para>
    <para>
      Of course, you can use higher order leveling for any data, however, this can
      supress real features on the surface (namely waviness of the surface) and therefore
      alter the statistical functions and quantities evaluated from the surface.
    </para>
    <para>
      The simplest modules that ace connected with data leveling are Fix Zero and
      Zero Mean Value that simply set the average height of the data to put minimum
      to zero (Fix Zero) or mean value to zero (Zero Mean Value). These modules can be
      accessed through the following menu choices:
    </para>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Level</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fix Zero</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Level</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Level</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <section>
      <title id="process-level-plane">Plane Level</title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Level</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Pleane Level</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Plane leveling is usually one of the firsts function applied to raw SPM data. The plane is
        computed from all the image points and is subtracted from the data.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title id="process-level-three">Three point leveling</title>
      <para>
        Three point leveling tool can be used for leveling very complicated surface structures.
        User can simply mark three points in the image that should be at the same level.
        Plane is computed from these three points and is subtracted from data.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title id="module-facet-level">Facet Level</title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Level</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Facet Level</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Levels data by subtracting a plane like the standard Level function does.
        However, the plane is determined differently: it makes facets of the surface as
        horizontal as possible.  Thus for surfaces with flat horizontal areas it leads to much
        better results than the standard Level.  On the other hand, for random surfaces it can
        behave much worse compared to Level.
      </para>
      <figure float="0">
        <title>
          Facet Level example. The first image shows uncorrected, sloping data;
          the second image shows data leveled by standard plane fitting (Level);
          the last one shows data level by Facet Level.
        </title>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="module-facet-level-uncorrected.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="module-facet-level-leveled.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="module-facet-level-fleveled.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Level Rotate</title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Level</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Level Rotate</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Does similar things as plane leveling, however does not simply subtract the fitted plane
        from the data. Instead of it, this module takes the plane parameters and rotates image
        data by given amount to make it lying in plane. In comparison to plane level, this
        modules should therefore preserve angles in the data.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Background subtraction</title>
    <para>
      Basically, background can be extracted using many modules generating some filtered data,
      using the Data Arithmetics module. However, there are special modules for backgrund
      subtraction too implemented in Gwyddion.  All allow to extract subtracted background
      to a separate data window.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Polynomial Background</title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Level</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Polynomial Background</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Fits data by polynom of given order (generally the order can be different for X and
        Y axis) and subtracts this polynom.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Revolve Arc</title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Level</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Revolve Arc</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Revolves virtual `arc' of given radius horizontally of vertically over (or under) data.
        Envelope of this arcs is treated as a background, resulting in removal of features
        larger than arc radius (approximately).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Median Level</title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Level</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Median Level</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Filters data with a median filter with large kernel and treats the result as
        background, keeping only features smaller than approximately kernel size.  This method
        is very slow.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>

