<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="main-window">
  <title>Main window</title>
  <para>
    The main window is the only Gwyddion part that appears after start with no parameters. It consist of set of
    Gwyddion menus: <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu></menuchoice>, <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu></menuchoice>,
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Data Process</guimenu></menuchoice>, <menuchoice><guimenu>Graph</guimenu></menuchoice>
    and <menuchoice><guimenu>Meta</guimenu></menuchoice>, and from several rows of buttons connected with tools
    and modules (accessible also by menus).
  </para>
  <para>
    <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu></menuchoice> menu associates commands that are used for file input and output.
    Global commands (e. g. Exit) are located here too. Submenu command names are self-explanatory (Load, Save, etc.).
  </para>
  <para>
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu></menuchoice> menu constist of commands that are applicable on more data windows
    (e. g. Data arithmetic) and commands that change status of data window presentation or selection. Masks and presentations
    options can be also set here.
  </para>
  <para>
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Data process</guimenu></menuchoice> menu is build automatically from all the modules available
    at the Gwyddion modules directory (depending on operating system). Modules are responsible for all the data processing,
    so this menu item associates most of the commands you will need at analyzing your SPM data.
  </para>
  <para>
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Graph</guimenu></menuchoice> menu consist of commands that are applicable on graphs. Graph processing
    includes reading values of graphs, measuring profile distances etc.
  </para>
  <para>
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Meta</guimenu></menuchoice> are commands that provide information about height field metadata
    (e. g. scanning speed, tip voltage, etc.) and information about the Gwyddion (About).
  </para>
  <para>
    Finally, you can find some rows of buttons in the main window. These buttons represent tools and some of the modules.
  </para>
  <figure float="0">
    <title>
      Main window with data view showing microchip surface (Gwyddion sample file).
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="564" fileref="main_window.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</section>
