<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="modules-tools">
  <title>Modules and tools</title>
  <para>
    Modules are responsible for most of the Gwyddion features. They mostly include data processing fucntions
    as leveling, rotations, integral transforms, etc. See Data process menu for list of available modules.
  </para>
  <para>
    Tools are a special kind of modules that can work with selections. Tools are used for interactive selecting areas
    or lines of the data and processing them. Tools can be lounched only from tools button rows located in the main window.
    Currently, Gwyddion includes at least these tools:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem id="tool-read-value">
      <para>
        Read value under cursor – reads x,y,z values at the position of mouse click. You can average more points around the point
        where you clicked.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-crop">
      <para>
        Crop – cuts part of the data and puts it to new window.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-level3">
      <para>
        Three-point leveling – levels data by plane obtained by clicking on three points wihin data window.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-stats">
      <para>
        Statistical quantities – computes basic statistical quantities (RMS, Ra, etc.) from selection of full data
        field.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-sfunctions">
      <para>
        Statistical functions – computes basic statistical functions (distribution of heights, autocorrelation
        function, etc.) from selection of full data field.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-profile">
      <para>
        Profile extraction – extracts profiles of the data field and puts them to separate graphs. These graphs can
        be further processed with commands from the Graph menu.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-distance">
      <para>
        Measure distances – similarly to Read value tool enables user to read distance and angle between points in
        the data field.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-polynom">
      <para>
        Fit X/Y profiles by polynom – very frequently used tool for basic processing of raw SPM data. Profiles
        taken in the fast scanning axis (usually X-axis) can be mutually shifted by some amount or having slightly
        different slope. Fit X/Y profiles tool can fix this discrepancy.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-filters">
      <para>
        Basic filters – mean, median, conservative denoise and similar simple filters to reduce noise in the data.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-remove-grains">
      <para>
        Manually remove grains – remove continuous parts of the mask by clicking on mask point.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-remove-spots">
      <para>
        Manually remove spots – draw rectangle around defect in AFM data image and remove the defect using chosen
        interpolation method.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem id="tool-color-range">
      <para>
        Stretch color range – enables user to change the false color representation range (by default from data
        minimum to data maximum).
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
