<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="opengl-3d-view">
  <title>OpenGL 3D data display</title>
  <para>
    Three-dimensional OpenGL display of current data window can be invoked
    with the button with symbol of cube in <guilabel>View</guilabel> button
    row of main window.
  </para>
  <para>
    The 3D window has two possible forms: with basic and expanded controls.
    It starts with basic constrols only, this form is displayed on
    <link linkend="opengl-3d-view-screenshot">following figure</link>.
    It can be switched to the expanded form (and back) with an expander button
    it the upper right corner.
  </para>
  <figure id="opengl-3d-view-screenshot" float="0">
    <title>
      Three-dimensional OpenGL data display window with basic controls.
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="399" fileref="opengl-3d-view.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <section>
    <title>Basic controls</title>
    <para>
      Basic 3D window contains interaction mode controls at the right side of
      the view.  By default, dragging the view with mouse rotates it
      horizontally and vertically.  All possible modes are listed below:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          Rotation – this is the default.  Dragging the view horizontally
          rotates it around <phrase role="math">z</phrase>-axis, vertical drag
          rotates it around horizontal axis parallel with the plane of view.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Scale – dragging the view right and down enlarges it, drag in the
          opposite direction makes it smaller.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Z-scale – dragging the view up (down) increases (decreases) the
          <phrase role="math">z</phrase>-scale, making the hills and valleys
          more or less pronounced.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Light rotation – this possibility is available only in lighting
          visualization mode.  Dragging the view changes position of light
          source similarly to rotation of data in normal rotation mode.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      The basic controls also include an image export button.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Full controls</title>
    <para>
      In expanded controls the mode buttons are located in top row, however
      their function does not change.  In addition, there are several tabs
      with options below them:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> – controls to set rotations and scales
          numerically and to switch on an off axes, axis labels, and
          perspective projection.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <guilabel>Light &amp; Material</guilabel> – visualization settings.
          Gwyddion 3D view has two basic visualization modes: gradient, in
          which the data are simply colored with a false color scale exactly
          like in normal 2D view; and material, in which the data are
          presented as an OpenGL material rendered accoring to light
          position.  This tab also contains controls to set light position
          numerically.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <guilabel>Labels</guilabel> – fine tuning of sizes, positions,
          and other properties of axis labels.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
