<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id="presentations-masks">
  <title>Presentations and Masks</title>
  <para>
    Presentations can be used to show the height field in another way than as
    a false color map of the heights. Several presentation methods are
    implemented, including shading, gradient filters and edge detectors.  It
    is also possible to superimpose an arbitrary data field over another one
    as the presentation.
  </para>
  <para>
    When you use data with a superimposed presentation in data processing
    functions or tools the results are always computed from the original
    data – presentations are only a visualization mode.  As presentations can
    be computationaly intensive to calculate, they are not automatically
    updated when the underlying data change.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig-mask-presentation-scheme">
    <title>
      Visualization of masks and presentations.  If the user looks from above
      they can be imagined as stacked as in the picture.
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="data-show-mask.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    Masks are used for special areal selections (e.g. grains, defects or
    factes with certain orientation). Masks can have any shape and within the
    data window they can be visualized by a color overlayed over the data.
    The mask color and opacity can be changed in the right-click context
    menu of the data window.  Mask are created by various modules and it is
    also possible to manually modify them with
    <link linkend="tool-mask-editor">Mask Editor tool</link>
    which can invert, grow, and shrink masks and draw or undraw various shapes
    on the mask.  A few basic mask operations are also available in
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Mask</guisubmenu>
    </menuchoice>
    menu.
  </para>
  <para>
    Several functions require a mask and they then operate on the mask and/or
    the data it marks, e.g. interpolation of data under mask or grain
    statistics.  Some statistical functions for masked areas can be found
    under <quote>grain</quote> functions as these functions are typically
    used for grains, however, you can use them for masks of any origin.
    Other functions allow to limit the area they operate on with masks, e.g.
    the statistical quantities tool or plane leveling.
  </para>
  <para>
    Both masks and presentations can be removed from the data by functions
    in the right-click menu of the data window, or with
    <link linkend="keyboard-shortcuts">keyboard shortcuts</link>.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig-mask-presentation">
    <title>
      Data in default false color representation (left), with superimposed
      mask (centre) and with shading presentation (right).
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="mask.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</sect1>
