<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id="remote-control">
  <title>Remote Control</title>
  <para>
    <application>Gwyddion</application> provides means to open files in an
    already running instance of the application and to test whether any
    instance is running on a given display.  These operations are performed
    by so called remote control command line options.  When they are given
    to the program, it does not start the user interface as usual, instead
    it attempts to communicate with an already running Gwyddion.  All the
    remote control options take the form <option>--remote-*</option>:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--remote-new</option></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Proably the most useful option.  It opens the files given on the
          command line in an already running instance of Gwyddion.  If none
          is running, it starts new Gwyddion as if
          <option>--remote-new</option> was not given – in this case, and
          only in this case, start-up options such as
          <option>--no-splash</option> have the intended effect (and make
          sense).
        </para>
        <para>
          File type associations are created to run Gwyddion with this option
          by default.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--remote-existing</option></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This options opens the files given on the command line in an
          already running instance of Gwyddion, in this case the command
          succeeds. However, if none is running it silently fails instead of
          starting a new one.  This can be useful when you want to handle
          failure differently than by starting a new Gwyddion.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--remote-query</option></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If an instance is already running, this option prints its toolbox
          window id (<type>Window</type> on X11, <type>HWND</type> on Win32)
          and succeeds.  If none is running, it silently fails.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    If more than one instance of Gwyddion is running on the display, the
    remote control will choose an arbitrary one
  </para>
</sect1>
