<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: environment.xml 9457 2009-07-15 22:02:37Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='resources' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title>Resources</title>
  <para>
    Various bits of data, e.g. <link linkend='color-map'>false color maps</link>
    or <link linkend='raw-file-import-presets'>raw file import presets</link>,
    are stored in standalone files that are collectivelly called resource
    files. Gwyddion looks for resources in two different locations: system
    and user-specific.
  </para>
  <para>
    System resources are installed along with the program and they are not
    modifiable. Typically, they are located under a directory such as
    <filename>/usr/share/gwyddion</filename> (Unix), <filename>Program
      Files\Gwyddion</filename> (MS Windows) or other directory determined by
    <link linkend='GWYDDION_DATADIR'><envar>GWYDDION_DATADIR</envar></link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    User resources are located in a user's directory, this usually means under
    <filename>~/.gwyddion</filename> (Unix) or <filename>Documents and
      Settings\gwyddion</filename> (MS Windows).
  </para>
  <para>
    All resource files are simple text files that can be easily examined and
    modified by text editors or sent to other users (if they are copied or
    created manually Gwyddion needs to be restarted to notice them).  In most
    cases only characters of the ASCII can appear in the files.  If
    international text can appear there it must be in the UTF-8 encoding.
  </para>
  <para>
    Resources are organized in subdirectories according to their kind, e.g.
    color gradients reside in the subdirectory <filename>gradients</filename>.
    The name of the file determines the resource name – gradient Gray is found
    in file <filename>gradients/Gray</filename>.
  </para>
  <para>
    Every resource file has the same structure.  It starts with a line
    identifying the resource type:
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>Gwyddion resource GwyGradient</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    where <type>GwyGradient</type> is the type name in the type system,
    followed by named parameters in the form
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting><replaceable>name</replaceable> <replaceable>value</replaceable></programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    and resource data.  Some resource types may contain only named parameters,
    other may contain only data.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='resource-gradients'>
    <title>Gradients</title>
    <para>
      Gradients, i.e. false color maps, reside in directory
      <filename>gradients</filename>, they are identified by
      <type>GwyGradient</type> and contain only data.  They can be edited in
      the application using the
      <link linkend='color-gradient-editor'>gradient editor</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The gradient data consists of rows corresponding to individual points in
      the gradient:
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting><replaceable>position</replaceable> <replaceable>red</replaceable> <replaceable>green</replaceable> <replaceable>blue</replaceable> <replaceable>alpha</replaceable></programlisting>
      </informalexample>
      The position determines where the color defined by
      <replaceable>red</replaceable>, <replaceable>green</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>blue</replaceable> and <replaceable>alpha</replaceable>
      components is placed in the interval
      <inlineequation>
        <mathphrase>[0, 1]</mathphrase>
        <alt>[0,1]</alt>
      </inlineequation>
      where 0 corresponds to the gradient start, 1 corresponds to the end.
      The color is interpolated linearly between the specified points.
    </para>
    <para>
      The positions must form an increasing sequence from 0 to 1 (i.e.
      the minimum number of color points is two). The range of the color
      components is also
      <inlineequation>
        <mathphrase>[0, 1]</mathphrase>
        <alt>[0,1]</alt>
      </inlineequation>.
      Note the alpha value, corresponding to opacity, is unused and must be
      given as 1 (fully opaque).
    </para>
    <para>
      For instance, the standard gradient Red going from black (0 0 0) to red
      (1 0 0) to white (1 1 1) is defined as follows:
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
Gwyddion resource GwyGradient
0.0 0 0 0 1
0.5 1 0 0 1
1.0 1 1 1 1
]]></programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='resource-opengl-materials'>
    <title>OpenGL Materials</title>
    <para>
      OpenGL materials reside in directory <filename>glmaterials</filename>,
      they are identified by <type>GwyGLMaterial</type> and contain
      only data.  They can be edited in the application using the
      <link linkend='opengl-material-editor'>OpenGL material editor</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The material data consists of four RGBA lines, similar to
      <link linkend='resource-gradients'>gradients</link> that correspond in
      to the four OpenGL material components in the following order:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>ambient,</listitem>
        <listitem>diffuse,</listitem>
        <listitem>specular,</listitem>
        <listitem>emission.</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      See section <link linkend='opengl-material-editor'>OpenGL Material
        Editor</link> for explanation of the components.  They are followed by
      a line containing the shininess, again as a number from the interval
      <inlineequation>
        <mathphrase>[0, 1]</mathphrase>
        <alt>[0,1]</alt>
      </inlineequation>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note the emission component, while read and written by Gwyddion, is
      presently unused by the 3D view.  It is recommended to set it to
      0 0 0 1, i.e. black.
    </para>
    <para>
      For instance, the standard material Red-Rubber with very dark red
      ambient color, grayish diffuse reflection, red specular reflection and
      low shininess is defined as follows:
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
Gwyddion resource GwyGLMaterial
0.05 0.0  0.0  1.0
0.5  0.4  0.4  1.0
0.7  0.04 0.04 1.0
0.0  0.0  0.0  1.0
.078125
]]></programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='resource-grain-values'>
    <title>Grain Values</title>
    <para>
      Grain values reside in directory <filename>grainvalues</filename>,
      they are identified by <type>GwyGrainValue</type> and contain
      only named parameters.  They can be used to define additional grain
      quantities, derived from the built-in quantities, that appear under
      <guilabel>User</guilabel> group in
      <link linkend='grain-analysis-statistics'>grain analysis functions</link>.
      At the time of writing this, there is no editor in the application, new
      quantities must be created manually.
    </para>
    <para>
      The named parameters are summarized in the following table:
    </para>
    <para>
      <informaltable frame='none' id='table-resource-grain-value'>
        <tgroup cols='3'>
          <?dblatex llX?>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Parameter</entry>
              <entry>Required</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>symbol</varname></entry>
              <entry>required</entry>
              <entry>
                Identifier to use in other expressions (but see below).
                It must be a valid identifier of ASCII letters, numbers and
                underscores, starting with a letter.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>expression</varname></entry>
              <entry>required</entry>
              <entry>
                Formula for calculation of this quantity from other
                grain quantities.  The general expression syntax is described
                in section <link linkend='expression-syntax'>Expressions</link>.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>symbol_markup</varname></entry>
              <entry>optional</entry>
              <entry>
                Fancy symbol that can include Greek letters or subscripts
                and superscripts expressed with the
                <ulink url='http://library.gnome.org/devel/pango/stable/PangoMarkupFormat.html'>Pango markup language</ulink>.
                It is used for presentation in the application so, while it
                is optional, it is recommended to at least define it
                identically to <varname>symbol</varname>.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>power_xy</varname></entry>
              <entry>optional</entry>
              <entry>
                The power in which the lateral dimensions appear in the
                quantity. For instance, this is 1 for grain dimensions, 2 for
                areas and volumes.  The default value is 0.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>power_z</varname></entry>
              <entry>optional</entry>
              <entry>
                The power in which the <quote>height</quote> dimension appears
                in the quantity. For instance, this is 1 for values and
                volumes, 0 for dimensions and areas.  The default value is 0.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>same_units</varname></entry>
              <entry>optional</entry>
              <entry>
                Give as 1 if the quantity makes sense only for lateral and
                <quote>height</quote> dimensions being the same physical
                quantities.  For instance, this is required for the surface
                area.  The default is 0.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>is_angle</varname></entry>
              <entry>optional</entry>
              <entry>
                Give as 1 if the quantity is an angle.  The expression should
                calculate angles in radians.  However, if
                <varname>is_angle</varname> is set Gwyddion knowns the value
                can be converted to degrees for presentation.
                The default is 0.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>
    <para>
      At present, user-defined grain quantities cannot depend on other
      user-defined grain quantities to avoid circular dependences.  The
      built-in grain quantities are listed below:
    </para>
    <para>
      <xi:include href='table-grain-quantities.xml'/>
    </para>
    <para>
      For instance, a new grain value Height, measuing the grain height as the
      difference between the maximum and minimum value, can be defined as
      follows:
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
Gwyddion resource GwyGrainValue
symbol dz
symbol_markup Δz
power_xy 0
power_z 1
expression z_max - z_min
]]></programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='resource-raw-file-presets'>
    <title>Raw File Presets</title>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='settings'>
    <title>Settings</title>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
