<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="selections">
  <title>Working with selections</title>
  <para>
    All interactive <link linkend="modules-tools">tools</link> and some other processing methods allow to select
    geometrical shapes on data with mouse: points, lines, rectangles, circles/ellipses.  Existing selections can
    be similarly modified by dragging corners, endpoints, or complete selections.  When mouse cursor is moved
    near to an editable point of a selection, is changes its shape to indicate the possibility to edit this point.
  </para>
  <para>
    Each tool generally uses only one type of selection and when it is activated on a data window, it sets the
    selection mode to this type.  Selections of other types than currently displayed are remembered and they
    are recalled when a tool which uses them is activated again.  E.g., when you select several lines with Profile
    extraction tool, then switch to Statistical quantities (the lines disappear) and select a rectangular area to
    calculate statistical characteristics of, and then switch back to Profile extraction, the rectangle disappears
    and the lines appear again.
  </para>
  <para>
    Tools that use the same type of selection – e.g., both Statistical functions and Statistical quantities use
    rectangular selection – share it.  To calculate height distribution of the same rectangle you have
    selected for statistical quantities, it is sufficient to switch the tool.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you save data in Gwyddion native file format (.gwy), all selections are saved together with data and
    recalled the next time the file is opened and appropriate tool chosen.
  </para>
  <para>
    <!-- FIXME: This is actually true only in 2.0 -->
    Pressing Shift during selection restricts the degrees of freedom of the shape, making it easier to draw shapes
    form a specific subset.  E.g., pressing Shift restricts rectanglular selections to perfect squares, or it
    restricts line directions to multiples of 15 ° in line selections.
  </para>
  <figure float="0">
    <title>
      Data window with three selected lines, two horizontal and one vertical.
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="369" fileref="selections-vlsi.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</section>
