<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id="features-stats" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <!--TODO: Clean up line breaks. The equation sections are esp. messy -->

  <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
  <para>
    While analyzing randomly rough surfaces we often need a statistical approach
    to determine some set of representative quantities. Within Gwyddion, there
    are several ways of doing this. In this section we will explain the various
    statistical tools and modules offered in Gwyddion, and also present the
    basic equations which were used to develop the algorithms they utilize.
  </para>
  <para>
    Scanning probe microscopy data are usually represented as a two-dimensional
    data field of size <phrase role="math">N</phrase> × <phrase role="math">M</phrase>,
    where <phrase role="math">N</phrase> and/or <phrase role="math">M</phrase>
    represents the number of rows and/or columns within the data field. The real
    size of the field is denoted as
    <phrase role="math">L<subscript>x</subscript></phrase> × <phrase role="math">L<subscript>y</subscript></phrase>
    where <phrase role="math">L<subscript>x</subscript></phrase> and <phrase role="math">L<subscript>y</subscript></phrase>
    are the sizes of the respective axes.
    The sampling interval (distance between two adjacent points within the scan) is
    denoted Δ. We assume that the sampling interval is the same in
    both the <phrase role="math">x</phrase> and <phrase role="math">y</phrase>
    direction. We assume that the surface height at a given point
    <phrase role="math">x</phrase>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase>
    can be described by a random function
    ξ(<phrase role="math">x</phrase>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase>)
    that has given statistical properties.
  </para>
  <para>
    Note that the AFM data are usually collected as line scans along the
    <phrase role="math">x</phrase> axis that are concatenated together to form
    the two-dimensional image. Therefore, the scanning speed in the
    <phrase role="math">x</phrase> direction is considerably higher than the
    scanning speed in the <phrase role="math">y</phrase> direction.
    As a result, the statistical properties of AFM data are usually collected
    along the <phrase role="math">x</phrase> profiles as these are less affected
    by low frequency noise and thermal drift of the sample.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="stat-quantities">
    <title>
      Statistical Quantities Tool
      <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="gwy_stat_quantities-24.png"/></guiicon>
    </title>
    <para>
      Statistical quantities include basic properties of the height values
      distribution, including its variance, skewness and kurtosis. The
      quantities accessible within Gwyddion by means of the
      <guilabel>Statistical Quantities</guilabel>
      tool are as follows:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        Mean value, minimum, maximum and median.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        RMS value of the height irregularities: this quantity is computed from
        data variance.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Ra value of the height irregularities: this quantity is similar to
        RMS value with the only difference in exponent (power)
        within the data variance sum. As for the RMS this exponent is
        <phrase role="math">q</phrase> = 2,
        the Ra value is computed with exponent
        <phrase role="math">q</phrase> = 1
        and absolute values of the data (zero mean).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Height distribution skewness: computed from 3rd central moment of data
        values.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Height distribution kurtosis: computed from 4th central moment of data
        values.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Projected surface area and surface area: computed by simple
        triangulation.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Mean inclination of facets in area: computed by averaging normalized
        facet direction vectors.
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <tip>
      By default, the Statistical Quantities tool will display figures based
      on the entire image. If you would like to analyze a certain region within
      the image, simply click and drag a rectangle around it. The tool window
      will update with new numbers based on this new region. If you want you see
      the stats for the entire image again, just click once within the data
      window and the tool will reset.
    </tip>
    <para>
      More precisely, RMS (σ), skewness (γ<subscript>1</subscript>), and kurtosis (γ<subscript>2</subscript>) are computed
      from central moments of <phrase role="math">i</phrase>-th order <phrase role="math">μ<subscript>i</subscript></phrase>
      according to the following formulas:
    </para>
    <informalequation>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="eq-statistical-quantities.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalequation>
    <para id="surface-area-calculation">
      The surface area is estimated by the following method.
      Let <phrase role="math">z<subscript>i</subscript></phrase> for
      <phrase role="math">i</phrase> = 1, 2, 3, 4 be values in
      four neighbour points (pixel centers), and
      <phrase role="math">h<subscript>x</subscript></phrase> and
      <phrase role="math">h<subscript>y</subscript></phrase>
      pixel dimensions along corresponding axes.  If an additional point is
      placed in the center of the rectangle which corresponds to the common
      corner of the four pixels (using the mean value of the pixels),
      four triangles are formed and the surface area can be
      approximated by summing their areas. This leads to the following formulas
      for the area of one triangle (top) and the surface area of one
      pixel (bottom):
    </para>
    <informalequation>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="eq-area-calculation.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalequation>
    <para>
      The method is now well-defined for inner pixels of the region.  Each
      value participates on eight triangles, two with each of the four
      neighbour values.  Half of each of these triangles lies in one pixel, the
      other half in the other pixel.  By counting in the area that lies inside
      each pixel, the total area is defined also for grains and masked areas.
      It remains to define it for boundary pixels of the whole data field. We
      do this by virtually extending the data field with a copy of the border
      row of pixels on each side for the purpose of surface area calculation,
      thus making all pixels of interest inner.
    </para>
    <figure id="surface-area-vertices">
      <title>
        Surface area calculation triangulation scheme.
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="surface_area_vertices.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sfunctions">
    <title>
      Statistical Functions Tool
      <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="gwy_graph_halfgauss-24.png"/></guiicon>
    </title>
    <para>
      One-dimensional statistical functions can be accessed by using the
      <guilabel>Statistical Functions</guilabel> tool.
      Within the tool window, you can select which function to evaluate using
      the selection box on the left labeled <guilabel>Output Type</guilabel>.
      The graph preview will update automatically. You can select in which
      direction to evaluate
      (<phrase role="math">x</phrase> or <phrase role="math">y</phrase>),
      but as stated above, we recommend using the fast scanning axis direction.
      You can also select which interpolation method to use
      (see <link>Interpolation<!--TODO: Fix link--></link>).
      When you are finished, click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to close the
      tool window and output a new graph window containing the statistical data.
    </para>
    <tip>
      Similar to the
      <link linkend="stat-quantities">Statistical Quantities</link>
      tool, this tool evaluates for the entire image by default, but you can
      select a sub-region to analyze if you wish.
    </tip>
    <sect3>
      <title>Height and Angle Distribution Functions</title>
      <para>
        The simplest statistical functions are the height and slope
        distribution functions. These can be computed as non-cumulative or
        cumulative. These functions are computed as normalized histograms of
        the height or slope (obtained as dreivatives in the selected direction
         – horizontal or vertical) values.  In other words, the quantity on the
        abscissa in <quote>angle distribution</quote> is the tangent of the
        angle, not the angle itself.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>First-order vs. Second-order Quantities</title>
      <para>
        The height and slope distribution quantities belong to the first-order
        statistical quantities, describing only the statistical properties of
        the individual points. However, for the complete description of the
        surface properties it is necessary to study higher order functions.
        Usually, second-order statistical quantities observing mutual
        relationship of two points on the surface are employed. These functions
        are namely the autocorrelation function, the height-height correlation
        function, and the power spectral density function.
        A description of each of these follows:
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Autocorrelation Function</title>
      <para>
        The autocorrelation function is given by
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-autocorrelation-definition.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">z</phrase><subscript>1</subscript> and
              <phrase role="math">z</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>
        are concrete values of heights at points
        [<phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>],
        [<phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>],
        τ<subscript><phrase role="math">x</phrase></subscript> = 
        <phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>1</subscript> - 
        <phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>2</subscript> and
        τ<subscript><phrase role="math">y</phrase></subscript> = 
        <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>1</subscript> - 
        <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>.
        The function
        <phrase role="math">w</phrase>(<phrase role="math">z</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>, <phrase role="math">z</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>,
        τ<subscript><phrase role="math">x</phrase></subscript>,
        τ<subscript><phrase role="math">y</phrase></subscript>)
        denotes the two-dimensional probability density of the random function
        ξ &gt; (<phrase role="math">x</phrase>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase>)
        corresponding to points
        [<phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>],
        [<phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>]
        and the distance between these points τ.
      </para>
      <para>
        For AFM measurements, we usually evaluate the one-dimensional
        autocorrelation function based only on profiles along the fast
        scanning axis. It can therefore be evaluated from the discrete AFM data
        values as
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="eq-autocorrelation-discrete.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject role="tex">
            <phrase>$\displaystyle G_x(\tau_x) = {1\over N(M-m)}
              \sum_{l=1}^N \sum_{n=1}^{M-m} z_{n+m,l} z_{n,l}$</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">m</phrase> = τ<subscript><phrase role="math">x</phrase></subscript>/Δ. The function can thus be evaluated in a discrete set
        of values of τ separated by the sampling interval Δ.
      </para>
      <para>
        The one-dimensional autocorrelation function is often assumed to have the
        form of a Gaussian, i.e. it can be given by the following relation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-autocorrelation-gaussian.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        <!--TODO: Tried to fix this sentence, but my not be correct -->
        where σ denotes the root mean square deviation of
        the heights and
        <phrase role="math">T</phrase> represents the autocorrelation length.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the exponential autocorrelation function we have the following
        relation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-autocorrelation-exponential.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <note>
        For optical measurements (e. g. spectroscopic reflectometry, ellipsometry)
        the Gaussian autocorrelation function is usually expected to be in good
        agreement with the surface properties. However, some articles related with
        surface growth \cite{jordan} and oxidation \cite{yoshinobu}
        <!--TODO: These artical citations are not correct. -->
        usually assume that the exponential form is closer to the reality.
      </note>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Height-Height Correlation Function</title>
      <para>
        The difference between the height-height correlation function and the
        autocorrelation function is very small. As with the autocorrelation
        function, we sum the multiplication of two different values. For the
        autocorrelation function, these values represented the different
        distances between points. For the height-height correlation function,
        we instead use the power of difference between the points.
      </para>
      <para>
        For AFM measurements, we usually evaluate the one-dimensional
        height-height correlation function based only on profiles along the fast
        scanning axis. It can therefore be evaluated from the discrete AFM data
        values as
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-height-height-correlation-discrete.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">m</phrase> = τ<subscript><phrase role="math">x</phrase></subscript>/Δ.
        The function thus can be evaluated in a discrete set of values of τ
        separated by the sampling interval Δ.
      </para>
      <para>
        The one-dimensional height-height correlation function is often assumed to be
        Gaussian, i.e. given by the following relation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-height-height-correlation-gaussian.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        <!--TODO: Tried to fix this sentence, but my not be correct -->
        where σ denotes the root mean square deviation of the heights and
        <phrase role="math">T</phrase> denotes the autocorrelation length.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the exponential height-height correlation function we have the following relation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-height-height-correlation-exponential.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        <!--TODO: Fix this paragraph, as well as the accompanying figure -->
        In Fig. 1 the height-height correlation function and autocorrelation function obtained for
        simulated surface having Gaussian autocorrelation function are plotted. These functions
        are fitted by means of least-squares method using the formulae shown above. The resulting
        values of σ and <phrase role="math">T</phrase> were practically same for both the approaches.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          Height-height correlation function and autocorrelation function obtained for
          simulated surface having Gaussian autocorrelation function.
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="fig_cf.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Power Spectral Density Function</title>
      <para>
        The two-dimensional power spectral density function can be written in
        terms of the Fourier transform of the autocorrelation function
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-fft.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        Similarly to the autocorrelation function, we also usually evaluate
        the one-dimensional power spectral density function which is given by
        the equation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-1d.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        This function can be evaluated by means of the Fast Fourier Transform as follows:
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-1d-fft.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">P<subscript>j</subscript></phrase>(<phrase role="math">K<subscript>x</subscript></phrase>) is the Fourier coefficient
        of the <phrase role="math">j</phrase>-th row, i.e.
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-Pj.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        If we have chosen the Gaussian ACF, the corresponding Gaussian relation for the PSDF is
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-1d-gaussian.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        For the surface with exponential ACF we have
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-1d-exponential.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        <!--TODO: Fix this paragraph, and figure -->
        In Figure 2 the resulting PSDF and its fit for the same surface as used in Fig. 1 are plotted.
        We can see that the function can be again fitted by Gaussian PSDF. The resulting values of σ
        and <phrase role="math">T</phrase> were practically same as those from the HHCF and ACF fit.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          PSDF obtained for data simulated with Gaussian autocorrelation function. Points represent
          computed data, line represents its fit.
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="fig_psdf.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <tip>
        Within Gwyddion you can fit all statistical functions presented here
        by their Gaussian and exponential forms. To do this, fist click
        <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> within the
        <link linkend="sfunctions">Statistical Functions</link> tool window.
        This will create a new graph window. With this new window selected, click
        on
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Graph</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><link linkend=""><!--TODO: Fix Link-->Fit Graph</link></guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </tip>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Minkowski Functionals</title>
      <para>
        The Minkowski functionals are used to describe global geometric characteristics
        of structures.  Two-dimensional discrete variants of
        volume <phrase role="math">V</phrase>,
        surface <phrase role="math">S</phrase>,
        and connectivity (Euler-Poincaré Characteristic) <phrase role="math">χ</phrase>
        are calculated according to following formulas:
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-minkowski-functionals.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        Here <phrase role="math">N</phrase> denotes the total number of pixels,
        <phrase role="math">N<subscript>white</subscript></phrase> denotes
        the number of “white” pixels, that is pixels above threshold (pixels below
        threshold are referred to as “black”).
        The symbol <phrase role="math">N<subscript>bound</subscript></phrase> denotes
        the number of white-black pixel boundaries.
        Finally <phrase role="math">C<subscript>white</subscript></phrase> and
        <phrase role="math">C<subscript>black</subscript></phrase> denote the number of
        continuous sets of white and black pixels respectively.
      </para>
      <para>
        For an image with continuous set of values the functionals are parametrized by
        the height threshold value <phrase role="math">ϑ</phrase> that divides white pixels
        from black, that is they can be viewed as functions of this parameter.
        And these functions
        <phrase role="math">V</phrase>(<phrase role="math">ϑ</phrase>),
        <phrase role="math">S</phrase>(<phrase role="math">ϑ</phrase>), and
        <phrase role="math">χ</phrase>(<phrase role="math">ϑ</phrase>)
        are what is actually plotted.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="line-stats">
    <title>
      Row/Column Statistics Tool
      <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="gwy_graph_vertical-24.png"/></guiicon>
    </title>
    <para>
      This tool calculates numeric characteristics of each row or column
      and plots them as a function of its position.  This makes it kind of
      complementary to
      <link linkend="sfunctions">Statistical Functions</link> tool.
      Available quantities include:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        Mean value, minimum, maximum and median.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        RMS value of the height irregularities computed from data variance.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Surface line length.  It is estimated as the total length of the
        straight segments joining data values in the row (column).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Overall slope, i.e. the tangent of the mean line fitted through the
        row (column).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Tangent of β<subscript>0</subscript>.  This is a characteristics of
        the steepnes of local slopes, closely related to the behaviour of
        autocorrelation and height-height correlation functions at zero.  For
        discrete values it is calculated as follows:
        <informalequation>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="eq-tan-beta0.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalequation>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Two-Dimensional Slope Statistics</title>
    <para>
      Several functions in
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Statistics</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      operate on two-dimensional slope (derviative) statistics.
    </para>
    <para>
      <guimenuitem>Slope Distribution</guimenuitem> calculates a plain
      two-dimensional distribution of derivatives, that is the horizontal and
      vertical coordinate on the resulting data field is the horizontal and
      vertical derivative, respectively.  The slopes can be calculated
      as central derivatives (one-side on the borders of the image) or,
      if <guilabel>Use local plane fitting</guilabel> is enabled, by fitting
      a local plane through the neighbourhood of each point and using its
      gradient.  <guimenuitem>Slope Distribution</guimenuitem> has also
      another mode operation called <guilabel>Per-angle graph</guilabel>.
      in which it plots the distribution of
      <phrase role="math">r</phrase><superscript>2</superscript> over φ
      where we introduced polar coordinates
      (<phrase role="math">r</phrase>, φ) in the plane of derivatives.
      The relation between the derivative Cartesian coordinates of the
      two-dimensional slope distribution and the
      <link linkend="inclinations-coordinates">facet inclination
        angles</link>
      are given by the following formula:
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-facet-theta-phi.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
    </para>
    <para>
      <guimenuitem>Angle Distribution</guimenuitem> function is
      a visualization tool that does not calculate a distribution in the
      strict sense.  For each derivative <phrase role="math">v</phrase>
      the circle of points satisfying
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-angle-distribution.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      is drawn.  The number of points on the circle is given by
      <guilabel>Number of steps</guilabel>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <xi:include href="facet-analysis.xml"/>
</sect1>
