<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-stats">
  <title>Statistical analysis</title>
  <para>
    While analyzing randomly rough surfaces we often need a statistical approach to determine
    some set of representative quantities. Within Gwyddion, there are several ways of doing this
    (e. g. "statistical quantities" and "statistical functions" tools and 2D slope and angle statistics)
    Here, the basic equations which were used to develop algorithms present in Gwyddion are presented.
  </para>
  <para>
    Atomic force microscopy data are usually represented as a two-dimensional
    data field of size <phrase role="math">N</phrase> × <phrase role="math">M</phrase>,
    where <phrase role="math">N</phrase> and/or <phrase role="math">M</phrase> represents the number of rows and/or
    columns within the data field. The real size of the field is denoted as
    <phrase role="math">L<subscript>x</subscript></phrase> × <phrase role="math">L<subscript>y</subscript></phrase>
    where <phrase role="math">L<subscript>x</subscript></phrase> and <phrase role="math">L<subscript>y</subscript></phrase> are the sizes of the respective axes.
    Sampling interval (distance between two adjacent points within the scan) is
    denoted &Delta;. We assume that the sampling interval is the same in
    both the <phrase role="math">x</phrase> and <phrase role="math">y</phrase> direction. We assume
    that the surface height in a given point <phrase role="math">x</phrase>,<phrase role="math">y</phrase> can be described by a random function
    <phrase role="math">&xi;</phrase>(<phrase role="math">x</phrase>,<phrase role="math">y</phrase>) that has given statistical properties.
  </para>
  <para>
    Note that the AFM data are usually collected as a line scans in the <phrase role="math">x</phrase> axis that are
    forming the two-dimensional image. Therefore, the scanning speed in the <phrase role="math">x</phrase> direction
    is considerably higher than the scanning speed in the <phrase role="math">y</phrase> direction.
    Therefore, the statistical properties of AFM data are usually collected
    along the <phrase role="math">x</phrase> profiles as these are less affected by low frequency noise and thermal drift
    of the sample.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Statistical quantities</title>
    <para>
      Statistical quantities include basic properties of the height values distribution, including
      its variance, skewness and kurtosis. The quantities accesible within Gwyddion by means of
      the "statistical quantities" tool are as follows:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        RMS value of the height irregularities: this quantity is computed from data variance.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Ra value of the height irregularities: this quantity is similar to RMS value with the only difference in exponent (power)
        within the data variance sum. As for the RMS this exponent is <phrase role="math">q</phrase> = 2,
        the Ra value is computed with exponent <phrase role="math">q</phrase> = 1
        and absolute values of the data (zero mean),
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Height distribution skewness: again this is computed as 3rd power of the data values (zero mean)
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Height distribution kurtosis: computed as 4th power of the data values (zero mean)
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Statistical functions</title>
    <para>
      One-dimensional statistical functions can be accesed by using "statistical functions" tool.
      The functions can be computed using both the <phrase role="math">x</phrase> and <phrase role="math">y</phrase> direction. As stated above,
      we recommend using the fast scanning axis direction for statistical functions evaluation.
    </para>
    <para>
      The simplest statistical functions are the height and slope distribution functions.
      These can be computed as non-cumulative or cumulative. These functions are computed as normalized histograms
      of the height or slope (obtained by <phrase role="math">x</phrase> or <phrase role="math">y</phrase> derivation) values.
    </para>
    <para>
      The height and slope quantities belong to the first-order statistical quantities,
      describing only the statistical properties of the individual points.
      However, for the complete description of the surface properties it
      is necessary to study higher order functions. Usually, second-order statistical
      quantities observing mutual relationship of two points on the surface
      are employed. These functions are namely autocorrelation function,
      power spectral density function and height-height correlation function.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Autocorrelation function</title>
      <para>
        Autocorrelation function is given by
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-autocorrelation-definition.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">z</phrase><subscript>1</subscript> and <phrase role="math">z</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>
        are concrete values of heights at points [<phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>],
        [<phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>],
        <phrase role="math">&tau;<subscript>x</subscript></phrase> = <phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>1</subscript> - <phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>
        and <phrase role="math">&tau;<subscript>y</subscript></phrase> = <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>1</subscript> - <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>.
        Function <phrase role="math">w</phrase>(<phrase role="math">z</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>, <phrase role="math">z</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>,
        <phrase role="math">&tau;<subscript>x</subscript></phrase>, <phrase role="math">&tau;<subscript>y</subscript></phrase>)
        denotes two-dimensional probability density of random function <phrase role="math">&xi;</phrase> &gt; (<phrase role="math">x</phrase>,<phrase role="math">y</phrase>)
        corresponding to points [<phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>1</subscript>],
        [<phrase role="math">x</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>, <phrase role="math">y</phrase><subscript>2</subscript>]
        and the distance between
        these points <phrase role="math">&tau;</phrase>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Within the AFM measurements we usually evaluate the one-dimensional
        autocorrelation function determined only from profiles in the fast
        scanning axis which can be evaluated from the discrete AFM data values as
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="eq-autocorrelation-discrete.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject role="tex">
            <phrase>$\displaystyle G_x(\tau_x) = {1\over N(M-m)}
              \sum_{l=1}^N \sum_{n=1}^{M-m} z_{n+m,l} z_{n,l}$</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">m</phrase> = <phrase role="math">&tau;<subscript>x</subscript></phrase>/<phrase role="math">&Delta;</phrase>. Function thus can be evaluated in a discrete set
        of values of <phrase role="math">&tau;</phrase> separated by the sampling interval <phrase role="math">&Delta;</phrase>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The one-dimensional autocorrelation function is often supposed as being
        Gaussian, i. e. given by the following relation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-autocorrelation-gaussian.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">&sigma;</phrase> and/or <phrase role="math">T</phrase> denotes the root mean square deviation of
        the heights and/or the autocorrelation length.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the exponential autocorrelation function we have the following relation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-autocorrelation-exponential.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        Note that in optical measurements (e. g. spectroscopic reflectometry, ellipsometry)
        Gaussian autocorrelation function is usually expected to be in good
        agreement with the surface properties. However, some articles related with
        surface growth \cite{jordan} and oxidation \cite{yoshinobu} usually assume that the exponential form is
        closer to the reality.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Height-height correlation function</title>
      <para>
        The difference between height-height correlation function and autocorrelation
        function is only very small. As within autocorrelation function we sum multiples
        of two different values (for different distances between points representing these values),
        for height-height correlation function evaluation we use power of difference between
        these two values.
      </para>
      <para>
        Within the AFM measurements we usually evaluate the one-dimensional
        height-height correlation function determined only from profiles in the fast
        scanning axis which can be evaluated from the discrete AFM data values as
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-height-height-correlation-discrete.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">m</phrase> = <phrase role="math">&tau;<subscript>x</subscript></phrase>/<phrase role="math">&Delta;</phrase>. Function thus can be evaluated in a discrete set
        of values of $\tau$ separated by the sampling interval <phrase role="math">&Delta;</phrase>.
      </para>
      <para>
        As stated above, the one-dimensional autocorrelation function is often supposed as being
        Gaussian, i. e. given by the following relation for the height-height correlation function
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-height-height-correlation-gaussian.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">&sigma;</phrase> and/or <phrase role="math">T</phrase> denotes the root mean square deviation of
        the heights and/or the autocorrelation length.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the exponential autocorrelation function we have the following relation for the
        height-height correlation function
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-height-height-correlation-exponential.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        In Fig. 1 the height-height correlation function and autocorrelation function obtained for
        simulated surface having Gaussian autocorrelation function are plotted. These functions
        are fitted by means of least-squares method using the formulae shown above. The resulting
        values of <phrase role="math">&sigma;</phrase> and <phrase role="math">T</phrase> were practically same for both the approaches.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          Height-height correlation function and autocorrelation function obtained for
          simulated surface having Gaussian autocorrelation function.
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="fig_cf.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
      <para>
        Two-dimensional power spectral density function can be written in terms of Fourier transform of the
        autocorrelation function
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-fft.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        Similarly to autocorrelation function, also here we
        usually evaluate the one-dimensional
        power spectral density function which is given by equation
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-1d.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        This function can be evaluated by means of the Fast Fourier transform as follows:
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-1d-fft.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        where <phrase role="math">P<subscript>j</subscript></phrase>(<phrase role="math">K<subscript>x</subscript></phrase>) is the Fourier coefficient
        of the <phrase role="math">j</phrase>-th row, i. e.
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-Pj.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        If we have chosen the Gaussian ACF, the corresponding Gaussian relation for the PSDF is
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-1d-gaussian.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        For the surface with exponential ACF we have
      </para>
      <informalequation>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="eq-power-spectral-density-1d-exponential.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalequation>
      <para>
        In Figure 2 the resulting PSDF and its fit for the same surface as used in Fig. 1 are plotted.
        We can see that the function can be again fitted by Gaussian PSDF. The resulting values of
        <phrase role="math">&sigma;</phrase> and <phrase role="math">T</phrase> were practically same as those from the HHCF and ACF fit.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          PSDF obtained for data simulated with gaussian autocorrelation function. Points represent
          computed data, line represents its fit.
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="fig_psdf.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Note that within Gwyddion you can fit all statistical function presented here
        by their gaussian and exponential forms. For this, evaluate the statistical function
        (and put it into graph) and fit this by choosing "graph fit" module.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
