<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-edit">
  <title>Data edit</title>
  <para>
  There are several modules that enable direct or indirect editing of the
  SPM data. In principal, most of the data processing modules do some "data edit"
  as they change the data.
  However, in this chapter we would like to describe the modules and tools
  that can be used for removing locally all the information from the data field
  and substituting it by some other information.  This includes functions for
  removing spots, scars and general data under mask.
  </para>
  <section>
     <title>Remove spots</title>
     <para>
     Remove spots tool can be used for removing very small parts of the image that
     are considered as scanning error, dust particle or anything else that should not
     be present in the data. Note that doing so can dramatically alter the resulting
     statistical parameters of the surface, so be sure not to remove things that
     are really present on the surface.
     </para>
     <para>
     Within the tool you can select rectangle around the area that should be removed.
     You can use then several methods for creating data in place of former spot:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
	Hyperbolic flatten - uses information from selected area boundaries to interpolate
	the information inside area.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	Pseudo-laplace and Laplace solver - solves Laplace equation to find out data inside
	area; the boundary is treated as virtual source.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	Fractal correction - uses whole image to determine fractal dimension. Then tries
	to create randomly rough data that have the same fractal dimension and put them into the area.
	</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Remove scars</title>
     <para>
     Scars (or stripes) are parts of the image that are corrupted by very common scanning error - local
     fault of the closed loop. As the scanning highly probably does not happen in the previous and following
     scan line we obtain a line defect paralell to the fast scanning axis in the image. This line defect
     can be found and removed using the neighbourhood lines within this module.
     </para>
     <para>
     Similarly, the Mark scars module can create mask of the points treated as scars.
     </para>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Remove data under mask</title>
     <para>
     This module tries to substitute data under mask by solving Laplacian equation. Unmasked data are used
     as virtual source and information in the masked regions is iterativelyh computed.
     </para>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Fractal correction</title>
     <para>
     Fractal correction module has the same output as "Remove data under mask" module, however using
     a different approach. Fractal dimension of the whole image is first computed and the areas under
     mask are substituted by randomly rough surface having the same fractal dimension as the surface.
     Moreover, also root mean square value of the height irregularities (roughness) is not changed
     by apllying this module.
     </para>
     <para>
     Note that running this module on data that do not have fractal properties itself causes really crazy
     results.
     </para>
  </section>
</section>

