<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-fractal">
  <title>Fractal analysis</title>
  <para>
  In practice objects exhibiting random properties are encountered.
  It is often assumed that these objects exhibit the self-affine
  properties in a certain range of scales. Self-affinity is a generalization
  of self-similarity which is the basic property of most of the deterministic
  fractals. A part of self-affine object is similar to whole object after
  anisotropic scaling. Many randomly rough surfaces are assumed to belong
  to the random objects that exhibit the self-affine properties and they are
  treated self-affine statistical fractals. Of course, these surfaces can be
  studied using atomic force microscopy (AFM). The results of the fractal
  analysis of the self-affine random surfaces using AFM are often used to
  classify these surfaces prepared by various technological procedures [1-4].
  </para>
  <para>
  Within Gwyddion, there are different methods of fractal analysis implemented
  within
  <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Statistics</guisubmenu>
    <guimenuitem>Fractal analysis</guimenuitem>
  </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
    Cube counting method [1,2] is derived directly from a definition of box-counting fractal dimension.
    The algorithm is based on the following steps: a cubic lattice with lattice constant l is superimposed
    on the <phrase role="math">z</phrase>-expanded surface. Initially <phrase role="math">l</phrase> is set
    at <phrase role="math">X/2</phrase> (where <phrase role="math">X</phrase> is length of
    edge of the surface), resulting in a lattice of 2x2x2=8 cubes. <phrase role="math">N(l)</phrase> is then number of all cubes that
    contain at least one pixel of the image. Lattice constant <phrase role="math">l</phrase> is then reduced stepwise by factor of
    2 and the process repeated until <phrase role="math">l</phrase> is equal to distance between two adjacent pixels. The slope
    of a plot of <phrase role="math">log (N(l))</phrase> versus <phrase role="math">log(1/l)</phrase>
    gives fractal dimension <phrase role="math">D<subscript>f</subscript></phrase> directly.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    Triangulation method [1] is very similar to cube counting method and is also based
    directly on the box-counting fractal dimension definition. The method works as follows:
    A grid of unit dimension <phrase role="math">l</phrase> is placed on the surface. This defines the location of the
    vertices of a number of triangles. When <phrase role="math">l=X/4</phrase>, for example, the surface is covered by
    32 triangles of different areas inclined at various angles with respect to the <phrase role="math">x-y</phrase> plane.
    The areas of all triangles are calculated and summed to obtain an approximation of the surface area
    <phrase role="math">S(l)</phrase> corresponding to <phrase role="math">l</phrase>. The grid size is then decreased by successive factor of 2,
    as before, and the process continued until <phrase role="math">l</phrase> corresponds to distance between two adjacent
    pixel points. The slope of a plot of <phrase role="math">log (S(l))</phrase> versus <phrase role="math">log(1/l)</phrase> is then corresponding to
    <phrase role="math">D<subscript>f</subscript>-2</phrase>.
    </listitem>
     <listitem>
     The variance method [3,4] is based on the scale dependence of the variance of fractional Brownian motion.
     In practice, in the variance method one divides the full surface into equal-sized squared boxes, and the
     variance (power of RMS value of heights), is calculated for particular box size. Fractal dimension is
     evaluated from the slope <phrase role="math">beta</phrase>  of a least-square regression line fit to the data points in log-log
     plot of variance  as <phrase role="math">D<subscript>f</subscript> = 3-&beta;/2</phrase>.
    </listitem>
     <listitem>
     Power spectrum method [3, 4, 5] is based on the power spectrum dependence of fractional Brownian motion.
     In the power spectrum method, every line height profiles that forms the image is Fourier transformed and
     the power spectrum evaluated and then all these power spectra are averaged. Fractal dimension is evaluated
     from the slope In the power spectrum method, every line height profiles that forms the image is Fourier
     transformed and the power spectrum evaluated and then all these power spectra are averaged. Fractal
     dimension is evaluated from the slope <phrase role="math">beta</phrase> of a least-square regression line fit to the data
     points in log-log plot of power spectrum as <phrase role="math">D<subscript>f</subscript>=7/2-&beta;/2</phrase>.
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
  Note, that results of different methods differ. This fact is caused by systematic error of different
  fractal analysis approaches.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Fractal analysis dialog.</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="fractal.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
  Moreover, the results of the fractal analysis can be influenced strongly by the tip convolution.
  We recommned therefore to check the certainty map before fractal analysis. In cases when the surface is
  influenced a lot by tip imaging, the results of the fractal analysis can be misrepresented strongly.
  </para>
  <para>
  Note, that algorithms that can be used within the fractal analysis module are also used in "Fractal correction" module
  ad "Fractal correction" option of "Remove spots" tool.
  </para>
  <section>
  <title>References</title>
  <para>
  [1] C. Douketis, Z. Wang, T. L. Haslett, M. Moskovits: Fractal character of cold-deposited
  silver films determined by low-temperature scanning tunneling microscopy. Physical
  Review B, Volume 51, Number 16, 15 april 1995, 51
  </para><para>
  [2] W. Zahn, A. Z\uffffsch: The dependance of fractal dimension on measuring conditions of
  scanning probe microscopy. Fresenius J Analen Chem (1999) 365: 168-172
  </para><para>
  [3] A. Van Put, A. Vertes, D. Wegrzynek, B. Treiger, R. Van Grieken: Quantitative
  characerization of individual particle sutfaces by fractal analysis of scanning electron
  microscope images. Fresenius J Analen Chem (1994) 350: 440-447
  </para><para>
  [4] A. Mannelquist, N. Almquist, S. Fredriksson: Influence of tip geometry on fractal analysis
  of atomic force microscopy images. Appl. Phys. A 66,1998, 891-895
  </para><para>
  [5] W. Zahn, A. Z\uffffsch: Characterization of thin film surfaces by fractal geometry. Fresenius J
  Anal Chem (1997) 358: 119-121
  </para>
  </section>
</section>

