<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-grains">
  <title>Grain analysis</title>
  <para>
  There are several grain-related algorithms implemented in Gwyddion.
  First of all, simple thresholding algorithms can be used (height, slope or curvature
  thresholding). These procedures can be very efficient namely within particle
  analysis (to mark particles located on flat surface).
  </para>
  <para>
  Thresholding methods can be accessed within Gwyddion as
  <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Grains</guisubmenu>
    <guimenuitem>Mark by Threshold</guimenuitem>
  </menuchoice>.
  Height, slope and curvature thresholding is implemented within this module. The results
  of each individual thresholding methods can be merged together using several operators.
  </para>
  <para>
  Similarily, the grains can be removed from the mask using
  <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Grains</guisubmenu>
    <guimenuitem>Remove Grains</guimenuitem>
  </menuchoice> menu choice.
  Maximum height and/or size thresholding methods can be used to eliminate false grains
  occured by noise or some dust particles, for example. You can use also interactive grain
  removal tool for doing this manually.
  </para>
  <para>
  For more complicated data structures the effectiveness of thresholding
  algorithms can be very poor. For these data a <emphasis>watershed algorithm</emphasis> can be used more
  effectively for grain or particle marking.
  </para>
  <para>
  The watershed algorithm is usually employed for local minima
  determination and image segmentation in image processing. As the problem
  of determining the grain positions can be understood as the problem of finding local extremes on the surface
  this algorithm can be used also for purposes of grain segmentation or marking.
  For convenience in the following we will
  treat the data inverted in the <emphasis>z</emphasis> direction while describing the algorithm
  (i.e. the grain tops are forming local minima in the following text).
  We applied two stages of the grain analysis (see Ref. [1]):
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
    At each point of the inverted surface the virtual water drop was placed. In the case that
    the drop was not allready in a local minimum it followed the steepest descent path to
    minimize its potential energy. As soon as the drop reached any local minimum it stopped here
    and rested on the surface. In this way it filled the local minimum partially by its volume (see Fig 2 and the figure caption).
    This process was repeated several times. As the result a system of lakes of different sizes
    filling the inverted surface depressions was obtained.
    Then the area of each of the lakes was evaluated and the smallest lakes were removed under
    assumption that they were formed in the local minima originated by noise. The larger lakes
    were used to identify the positions of the grains.
    In this way the noise in the AFM data was eliminated.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    The grains found in the step 1 were marked (each one by a different number).
    The water drops continued in falling to the surface and filling the local minima. As the grains
    were already identified and marked after the first step, the next five situations could happen as soon as the
    drop reached a local minimum.
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
      the drop reached the place previously marked as a concrete grain. In this case the drop was
      merged with the grain, i. e. it was marked as a part of the same grain.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      the drop reached the place where no grain was found but a concrete grain was found in the closest neighbourhood
      of the drop. In this case the drop was merged with the grain again.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      the drop reached the place where no grain was found and no grain was found even in the closest neighbourhood
      of the drop. In that case the drop was not marked at all.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      the drop reached the place where no grain was found but more than one concrete grain was found in the closest neighbourhood
      (e. g. two different grains were found in the neighbourhood). In this case the drop was marked as the grain boundary.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      the drop reached the place marked as grain boundary. In this case the drop was marked as the grain boundary too.
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
  In this way we can identify the grain positions and then determine the volume occupied
  by each grain separately.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Image of grain-like surface structure (a) and corresponding results of height thresholding (b), curvature thresholding (c),
                  and watershed (d) algorithm. Within watershed algorithm it is possible to segment image even further.
		  </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="allgrains.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <section>
     <title>References</title>
     <para>
     [1] <ulink url="http://klapetek.cz/download.html">
     Petr Klapetek, Ivan Ohlídal, Daniel Franta, Alberto Montaigne-Ramil, Alberta Bonanni, David Stifter, Helmut Sitter:
     Acta Physica Slovaca, 3 (223-230), 2003
     </ulink>
     </para>
  </section>
  <!--  Doesn't work well, needs serious formatting improvements.
  <bibliography>
    <biblioentry>
      <biblioset relation='article'>
        <authorgroup>
          <author><firstname>Petr</firstname><surname>Klapetek</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Ivan</firstname><surname>Ohlídal</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Daniel</firstname><surname>Franta</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Alberto</firstname><surname>Montaigne-Ramil</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Alberta</firstname><surname>Bonanni</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>David</firstname><surname>Stifter</surname></author>
          <author><firstname>Helmut</firstname><surname>Stifter</surname></author>
        </authorgroup>
        <title>Atomic force microscopy characterization of ZnTe epitaxial films</title>
      </biblioset>
      <biblioset relation='journal'>
        <title>Acta Physica Slovaca</title>
        <volumenum>3</volumenum>
        <pagenums>223-230</pagenums>
        <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
      </biblioset>
    </biblioentry>
  </bibliography>
  -->
</section>

