<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <section id="motivation">
    <title>Motivation</title>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://gwyddion.net/"><application>Gwyddion</application></ulink>
      is a modular program for SPM data analysis. Primarily it is
      supposed to be used for analysis of height fields obtained by means
      of scanning probe microscopy techniques (AFM, MFM, STM, NSOM), but
      generally it can be used for any other height field analysis or image analysis.
      Gwyddion is a free software, covered by
      <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html">GNU General Public License</ulink> (GNU GPL).
    </para>
    <para>
      The main idea behind Gwyddion developement is to provide modular program
      for 2D data analysis that could be easily extended by modules and plugins
      with no need of core recompilation. Moreover, the status of free software
      enables to provide source codes to developers and users, which makes the further
      program improvement easier.
    </para>
    <para>
      Gwyddion can be currently used with Linux/Unix and Windows(TM) operating systems. Both
      families of systems can be used also for developement. For graphical interface,
      <ulink url="http://www.gtk.org/">Gtk+</ulink> and
      <ulink url="http://gtkglext.sourceforge.net/">GtkGLExt</ulink> and
      libraries are used, therefore it can be basically ported on any system
      that is supported by Gtk+ and GtkGLExt.
    </para>
    <para>
      Gwyddion core developement is currently funded by Czech Metrology Institute (<ulink url="http://www.cmi.cz/">www.cmi.cz</ulink>).
      The project started as a part of the Nanomet initiative (covered by Euromet) in August, 2004.
      It is supposed that more persons and institutions will participate on developement.
      Project is open for anyone. Welcome...
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="licensing">
    <title>Licensing</title>
    <para>
      Gwyddion is covered by <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html">GNU General Public License</ulink> (GNU GPL). See file
      <filename>COPYING</filename> in distribution for full License
      text. In particular, this means that:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            you can freely make copies and modify them. You can download the program and its source
            code from the Gwyddion pages and modify it as you want - however, the modified code
            will be still covered by the same license.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            if you add any part to the program (e. g. if you write a module), your code must be also
            covered by GNU GPL. The only exception are plugins that are run as a separate programs
            communicating with Gwyddion. Plugins therefore can have any license.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      The main reasons, why the program is covered by this kind of license are here: first of all, this
      licensing policy enables us to make modular program that can be easily developed my many persons
      from different institutions. Second, this license protects the rights of developers that their code,
      here given to public, cannot be copied and used for commercial purposes.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
