<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='color-map'>
  <title>False Color Mapping</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>color</primary>
    <secondary>mapping</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    False color mapping is the basic two-dimensional data visualization
    method.  The color gradient (also called palette) to use can be selected
    after clicking on the false color map part of a data window with right
    mouse button.
  </para>
  <para>
    This quick selection pop-up menu offers the list of preferred color
    gradients.  In addition it allows to invoke the full color gradient list
    by selecting <menuchoice><guimenuitem>More</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
    Preferred gradients can be chosen by checking the corresponding check
    buttons in the full list or in the
    <link linkend='color-gradient-editor'>gradient editor</link> list.
    Selecting a row in the full list changes the gradient to the selected
    one, double-clicking (or pressing <keycap>Enter</keycap>) also finishes
    selection and closes the list window.  Gradients of known names can be
    quickly accessed by starting to type their name. The default color
    gradient to use (when none is specified in the file) can be also set in
    the <link linkend='color-gradient-editor'>gradient editor</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    More control over the way values are mapped to colors is possible with
    <link linkend='color-range'>Color range</link> tool.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-gradient-selectors'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='gradient-selectors.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>
          Comparison of step and edge detection methods on several images
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        A data window with the right-click color gradient pop up menu and the
        full color gradient list.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <sect2 id='color-range'>
    <title>
      Color Range Tool
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_color_range-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <para>
      Color range tool is a special <link linkend='tools'>tool</link> whose
      purpose is not to analyse or modify data, but to control the way values
      are mapped to colors.  It offers four basic color mapping types:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Full
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_color_range_full-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Data values are mapped to colors linearly, the full data range
            corresponds to the full color range.  This is the default type
            (unless you have changed the default).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Fixed
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_color_range_fixed-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Data values are mapped to colors linearly, a user-specified data
            range (which can be smaller or greater than the full range) maps
            onto the full color range.  Values outside this range are
            displayed with the edge colors.  The range can be set by several
            means:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              by entering desired values numerically in the tool window,
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              by selecting a range on the height distribution graph in the
              tool window or
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              by selecting an area on the data window, the range is then
              set from the minimum to maximum of the data in this area only.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            If no range is manually set, fixed range type behaves identically
            to full range.
          </para>
          <para>
            Note data processing operations often modify the value range –
            and as the fixed range remains fixed as you set it, it can result
            for instance in completely black data display.  You may wish or
            have to update the range manually then, or to switch to another
            mapping type.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Automatic
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_color_range_auto-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Data values are mapped to colors linearly, a heuristically
            determined subinterval of the full value range maps onto the full
            color range.  Values outside this subrange are again displayed
            with the edge colors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Adaptive
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_color_range_adaptive-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The full data range corresponds to the full color range, however
            data values are mapped to colors non-linearly.  The mapping
            function is based on inverse cumulative height distribution,
            therefore flat areas generally get bigger slice of the color
            gradient and smaller value variations can be seen on them than
            normally.
          </para>
          <para>
            The false color map ruler on the right side of
            <link linkend='data-windows'>data windows</link> does not display
            any ticks in this mode, only the minimum and maximum value.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      A mapping type can be set to be default by checking the
      <guilabel>Default</guilabel> check button when it is active.  Newly
      displayed data windows then use this type, unless a channel explicitly
      specifies other type to use.
    </para>
    <para>
      Saving data to <filename>.gwy</filename> file also saves all color
      mapping settings: mapping type, range and gradient.  Gradient is
      however not physically stored in the file, only referenced by name.  In
      other words, color gradients of the same name are shared among files.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='color-gradient-editor'>
    <title>Color Gradient Editor</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>color map</primary>
      <secondary>editting</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>color map</primary>
      <secondary>choosing default</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Color gradient editor can be invoked with
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Color Gradients</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      It consists of a gradient list similar to the full gradient selector,
      with an additional button panel, and the actual editor that can be
      invoked by double-clicking on a gradient you wish to edit or by
      activating the <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> button.  Renaming is p
      Only user-created
      color gradients can be edited or deleted, system gradients installed
      with Gwyddion are immutable.
    </para>
    <para>
      The last button in the gradient list control panel makes the currently
      selected gradient the default.  It will be used for all newly displayed
      data that do not specify any particular color gradient.
    </para>
    <para>
      Two editing modes are available:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Points</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The color gradient is defined by a set of points and their
              associated colors.  The points are represented by triangular
              markers on the gradient displayed in the lower part of the
              editor window.  Moving these markers moves the points, new
              points can be added by clicking into an empty space, existing
              points can be removed by dragging them away from the gradient.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Curve</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The color gradient is defined by red, green and blue curves.
              The curves are again segmented, but the segments of individual
              curves do not need to coincide.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
