<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="features-tip">
  <title>Tip convolution artefacts</title>
  <para>
  Tip convolution artefact is one of the most important error sources in SPM.
  As the SPM tip is never ideal (like delta function) we often observe a certain
  degree of image distortion due to this effect. We can even see some SPM tips imaged on the
  surface scan while sharp features are present on the surface.
  </para>
  <para>
    <figure>
    <title>Images of ZnSe surface measured with four different SPM tips (more or less broken ones).</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="500" fileref="alltips.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <para>
  We can fortunately simulate and/or correct the tip efects using algorithms of dilation
  and/or erosion, respectively. These algorithms were published by Villarubia (see Ref. [1]).
  </para>
  <section>
    <title id="fetures-tip-get">Obtaining the tip geometry</title>
    <para>
    For studying the tip influence on the data we need to know tip geometry firts. In general,
    the geometry of the SPM tip can be determined in these ways:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
      use manufacturer's specifications (tip geometry, apex radiius and angle)
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      use scanning electron microscope of other independent technique to determine
      tip properties.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      use known tip characterizer sample (with steep edges)
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      use blind tip estimation algorithm together with tip characterizers or other
      suitable samples
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
    Within Gwyddion, we can use the firts and the last approach of the mentioned ones.
    Using tip modelling (
	<menuchoice>
	   <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Model Tip</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice>
    ) most of the tips with simple geometries can be simulated. This way
    of tip geometry specification can be very efficient namely when we need to check only
    certainty map of perform tip convolution simulation. To obtain more detailed (and more realistic)
    tip structure blind tip estimation algorithm can be used (
	<menuchoice>
	   <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Blind Estimation</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice>
      ).
    </para>
    <para>
    Blind tip estimation algorithm is an extension of the well-known fact that on some surface data we can see images of
    certain parts of tip directly. The algortihm iterates over all the surface data and at each point
    tries to refine each tip point according to steepest slope in the direction between
    concrete tip point and tip apex.
    </para>
    <para>
    We can use two modification of this algorithm within Gwyddion: <emphasis>partial</emphasis> tip estimation that uses
    only limited number of highest points on the image and <emphasis>full</emphasis> tip estimation taht uses full image
    (and is much slower therefore). Within Gwyddion tip estimation module we can use also partial
    tip estimation results as starting point for full estimation. This shlould improve the full
    tip estimation algorithm speed.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>SPM tips obtained from data of Figure 1 using blind estimation algorithm.</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="1000" fileref="alltips2.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title id="fetures-tip-use">Tip convolution and surface reconstruction</title>
    <para>
    When we know tip geometry, we can use tip convolution (dilation) algorithm to simulate data acquisition
    process. For doing this use Dilation module
    (
	<menuchoice>
	   <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Dilation</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice>

     ). This can be in particular useful when working with data being result of some numerical modelling
    (see e. g. Ref. 2).
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Simulated fractal surface before (left) and after (right) tip convolution.</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="600" fileref="fractaltips.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
    The opposite of the tip convolution is surface reconstruction (erosion) that can be used to correct partially the tip influence
    on image data. For doing this, use Surface Reconstruction module
       (
	<menuchoice>
	   <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Surface Reconstruction</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice>
     ).
    Of course, the data corresponding to point in image not touched by tip (e. g. pores) cannot be reconstructed
    as there is no information about these points.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>
      Original and reconstructed image of ZnSe imaged by broken SPM tip.
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="600" fileref="reconstruction.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
    As it can be seen, the most problematic parts of SPM image are data points, where tip did not touch the surface
    in a single point, mut in multiple points. There is a loss of information in these points. Certainty map algorithm
    can identify these data points and mark them.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>
      Certainty map obtained from columnar surface (having large pores). (A) - sample,
               (B) sample with marked certainty map.
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="400" fileref="cmap.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
    Certainty map algortihm can be therefore used to mark data in the SPM image that are corrupted by
    tip convolution in an irreversible way. For SPM data analysis on surfaces with large slopes it is important
    to check always presence of these points. Within Gwyddion you can use Ceratinty map module for creating
    these maps
    (
	<menuchoice>
	   <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu><guisubmenu>Tip</guisubmenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Certainty Map</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice>
     ).
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>References</title>
     <para>
     [1] J. S. Villarubia, J. Res. Natl. Inst. Stand. Technol. 102 (1997) 425.
     </para>
     <para>
     [2] <ulink url="http://klapetek.cz/download.html">P. Klapetek, I. Ohlídal, Ultramicroscopy, 94 (19-29), 2003</ulink>
     </para>
  </section>
</section>

