<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<section id="unrotate">
  <title>Unrotate</title>
  <para>
    Unrotate can automatically make principal directions in an image
    parallel with horizontal and/or vertical image edges.  For that to work,
    the data need to have some principal directions, therefore it is most
    useful for scans of artifical and possibly crystallic structures.
  </para>
  <para>
    The rotation necessary to straighten the image – displayed
    as <guilabel>Correction</guilabel> – is calculated from peaks
    in angular slope distribution
    <!-- TODO: link to Slope distribution -->
    assuming a prevalent type of structure, or symmetry.
    The symmetry can be estimated automatically too, but it is possible to
    select a particular symmetry type manually and let the module calculate
    only corresponding rotation correction.  Note if you assume a
    structure type that does not match the actual structure, the calculated
    rotation is rarely meaningful.
  </para>
  <para>
    It is recommended to level (or facet-level<!-- TODO: link -->) the data
    first as overall slope can skew the calculated rotations.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>
      Unrotate dialog with automatically estimated type of structure and
      rotation.
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="unrotate.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The assumed structure type can be set with <guilabel>Assume</guilabel>
    selector.  Following choices are possible:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Detected
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Automatically detected symmetry type, displayed above as
            <guilabel>Detected</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Parallel
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Parallel lines, one prevalent direction.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Triangular
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Triangular symmetry, three prevalent directions (unilateral) by
            120 degrees.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Square
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Square symmetry, two prevalent directions oriented
            approximately along image sides.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Rhombic
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Rhombic symmetry, two prevalent directions oriented approximately
            along diagonals.  The only difference from Square is the
            preferred diagonal orientation (as opposed to parallel with
            sides).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Hexagonal
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Hexagonal symmetry, three prevalent directions (bilateral) by 120
            degrees.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>
</section>

