<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='fractal-analysis'>
  <title>Fractal Analysis</title>
  <para>
    In practice objects exhibiting random properties are encountered. It is
    often assumed that these objects exhibit the self-affine properties in
    a certain range of scales. Self-affinity is a generalization of
    self-similarity which is the basic property of most of the deterministic
    fractals. A part of self-affine object is similar to whole object after
    anisotropic scaling. Many randomly rough surfaces are assumed to belong
    to the random objects that exhibit the self-affine properties and they
    are treated self-affine statistical fractals. Of course, these surfaces
    can be studied using atomic force microscopy (AFM). The results of the
    fractal analysis of the self-affine random surfaces using AFM are often
    used to classify these surfaces prepared by various technological
    procedures
    [<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-1'>1</link>,<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-2'>2</link>,<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-3'>3</link>,<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-4'>4</link>].
  </para>
  <para id='fractal-dimension'>
    <indexterm><primary>fractal dimension</primary></indexterm>
    Within Gwyddion, there are different methods of fractal analysis
    implemented within
  <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
    <guisubmenu>Statistics</guisubmenu>
    <guimenuitem>Fractal analysis</guimenuitem>
  </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Cube counting method
        [<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-1'>1</link>,<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-2'>2</link>]
      </term>
      <listitem>
        is derived directly from a definition of box-counting fractal
        dimension. The algorithm is based on the following steps: a cubic
        lattice with lattice constant l is superimposed on the
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>z</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>z</alt>
        </inlineequation>-expanded surface.
        Initially
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>l</alt>
        </inlineequation>is set
        at
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>X</phrase>/2</mathphrase>
          <alt>X/2</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        (where
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>X</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>X</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        is length of edge of the surface), resulting in a lattice of
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase>2×2×2 = 8</mathphrase>
          <alt>2\times2\times2=8</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        cubes.  Then
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>N</phrase>(<phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase>)</mathphrase>
          <alt>N(l)</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        is the number of all cubes that contain at least one pixel of the
        image.  The lattice constant
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>l</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        is then reduced stepwise by factor of 2 and the process repeated
        until
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>l</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        is equal to the distance between two adjacent pixels. The slope of
        a plot of
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase>log(<phrase role='mathvar'>N</phrase>(<phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase>))</mathphrase>
          <alt>\log N(l)</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        versus
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase>log(1/<phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase>)</mathphrase>
          <alt>\log 1/l</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        gives the fractal dimension
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>D</phrase><subscript>f</subscript></mathphrase>
          <alt>D_{\rm f}</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        directly.
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Triangulation method
        [<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-1'>1</link>]
      </term>
      <listitem>
        is very similar to cube counting method and is also based directly on
        the box-counting fractal dimension definition. The method works as
        follows: A grid of unit dimension
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>l</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        is placed on the surface. This defines the location of the vertices of
        a number of triangles.  When, for example,
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase> = <phrase role='mathvar'>X</phrase>/4</mathphrase>
          <alt>l=X/4</alt>
        </inlineequation>,
        the surface is covered by 32 triangles of different areas inclined at
        various angles with respect to the
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>xy</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>xy</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        plane.  The areas of all triangles are calculated and summed to obtain
        an approximation of the surface area
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>S</phrase>(<phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase>)</mathphrase>
          <alt>S(l)</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        corresponding to
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>l</alt>
        </inlineequation>.
        The grid size is then decreased by successive factor of 2, as before,
        and the process continues until
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>l</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        corresponds to distance between two adjacent pixel points.
        The slope of a plot of
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase>log(<phrase role='mathvar'>S</phrase>(<phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase>))</mathphrase>
          <alt>S(l)</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        versus
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase>log(1/<phrase role='mathvar'>l</phrase>)</mathphrase>
          <alt>\log 1/l</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        then corresponds to
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>D<subscript>f</subscript></phrase> − 2</mathphrase>
          <alt>D_{\rm f}-2</alt>
        </inlineequation>.
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Variance method
        [<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-3'>3</link>,<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-4'>4</link>]
      </term>
      <listitem>
        is based on the scale dependence of the
        variance of fractional Brownian motion. In practice, in the variance
        method one divides the full surface into equal-sized squared boxes, and
        the variance (power of RMS value of heights), is calculated for
        particular box size. Fractal dimension is
        evaluated from the slope
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>β</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>\beta</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        of a least-square regression line fit to the data points in log-log
        plot of variance as
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>D</phrase><subscript>f</subscript> = 3 − <phrase role='mathvar'>β</phrase>/2</mathphrase>
          <alt>D_{\rm f} = 3-\beta/2</alt>
        </inlineequation>.
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Power spectrum method
        [<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-3'>3</link>,<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-4'>4</link>,<link linkend='fractal-analysis-ref-5'>5</link>]
      </term>
      <listitem>
        is based on the power spectrum dependence of fractional Brownian
        motion. In the power spectrum method, every line height profiles that
        forms the image is Fourier transformed and the power spectrum evaluated
        and then all these power spectra are averaged. Fractal dimension is
        evaluated from the slope In the power spectrum method, every line
        height profiles that forms the image is Fourier transformed and the
        power spectrum evaluated and then all these power spectra are averaged.
        Fractal dimension is evaluated from the slope
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>β</phrase></mathphrase>
          <alt>\beta</alt>
        </inlineequation>
        of a least-square regression line fit to the data points in log-log
        plot of power spectrum as
        <inlineequation>
          <mathphrase><phrase role='mathvar'>D</phrase><subscript>f</subscript> = 7/2 − <phrase role='mathvar'>β</phrase>/2</mathphrase>
          <alt>D_{\rm f}=7/2-\beta/2</alt>
        </inlineequation>.
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    The axes in Fractal Dimension graphs always show already logarithmed
    quantities, therefore the linear dependences mentioned above corresponds
    to straight lines there.  The measure of the axes should be treated as
    arbitrary.
  </para>
  <para>
    Note, that results of different methods differ. This fact is caused by
    systematic error of different fractal analysis approaches.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-fractal-dimension-screenshot'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='fractal.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Fractal Dimension dialog.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    Moreover, the results of the fractal analysis can be influenced strongly by
    the tip convolution. We recommned therefore to check the certainty map
    before fractal analysis. In cases when the surface is influenced a lot by
    tip imaging, the results of the fractal analysis can be misrepresented
    strongly.
  </para>
  <para>
    Note, that algorithms that can be used within the fractal analysis module
    are also used in Fractal Correction module and Fractal Correction option
    of Remove Spots tool.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='fractal-analysis-ref'>
    <title>References</title>
    <para id='fractal-analysis-ref-1'>
      [1] C. Douketis, Z. Wang, T. L. Haslett, M. Moskovits: Fractal
      character of cold-deposited silver films determined by low-temperature
      scanning tunneling microscopy. Physical Review B, Volume 51, Number 16,
      15 April 1995, 51
    </para>
    <para id='fractal-analysis-ref-2'>
      [2] W. Zahn, A. Zösch: The dependance of fractal dimension on measuring
      conditions of scanning probe microscopy. Fresenius J Analen Chem (1999)
      365: 168-172
    </para>
    <para id='fractal-analysis-ref-3'>
      [3] A. Van Put, A. Vertes, D. Wegrzynek, B. Treiger, R. Van Grieken:
      Quantitative characerization of individual particle sutfaces by fractal
      analysis of scanning electron microscope images. Fresenius J Analen
      Chem (1994) 350: 440-447
    </para>
    <para id='fractal-analysis-ref-4'>
      [4] A. Mannelquist, N. Almquist, S. Fredriksson: Influence of tip
      geometry on fractal analysis of atomic force microscopy images. Appl.
      Phys. A 66,1998, 891-895
    </para>
    <para id='fractal-analysis-ref-5'>
      [5] W. Zahn, A. Zösch: Characterization of thin film surfaces by
      fractal geometry. Fresenius J Anal Chem (1997) 358: 119-121
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
