<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='presentations-masks'>
  <title>Presentations and Masks</title>
  <sect2 id='presentations-introduction'>
    <indexterm><primary>presentation</primary></indexterm>
    <title>Presentations</title>
    <para>
      Presentations can be used to show the height field in another way than as
      a false color map of the heights, for instance with shading or with
      highlighted edges.  It is also possible to superimpose an arbitrary data
      field over another one as the presentation.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note the superimposed presentation is really only a presentation, it is
      never used for calculations.  In all data processing functions or tools
      the results are always computed from the original underlying data.  Since
      presentations can be computationaly intensive to calculate, they are not
      automatically updated when the underlying data change.  The various
      presentations available are described in section
      <link linkend='presentations'>Presentations</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The presence of presentation over the data is indicated by flag
      <guilabel>P</guilabel> in the
      <link linkend='data-browser-channels'>data browser</link> and also by the
      empty false color map ruler on the right side of the
      <link linkend='data-windows'>data window</link> that does not display
      any ticks nor the minimum and maximum value.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='masks-introduction'>
    <indexterm><primary>mask</primary></indexterm>
    <title>Masks</title>
    <para>
      Masks are used for special areal selections, e.g. grains, defects or
      factes with certain orientation.  Masks can have any shape and within the
      data window and they are visualized by a color overlayed over the data.
      The mask color and opacity can be changed in the right-click context
      menu of the data window.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since grain marking is the most common use of masks, several functions
      that operate on marked areas are called <quote>grain</quote> functions,
      e.g.  Grain Statistics.  Also, a contignuous part of mask is sometimes
      called grain in this guide.  However, since a mask does not bear any
      information how it was created all mask functions can be used with masks of
      any origin.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <informalfigure id='fig-mask-presentation-scheme'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='data-show-mask.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>
          Mask (top), presentation (middle), original data (bottom)
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        Visualization of masks and presentations.  If you look from above they
        can be imagined to be stacked as in the picture.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    Both masks and presentations can be removed from the data by functions
    in the right-click menu of the
    <link linkend='data-windows'>data window</link>, or with
    <link linkend='keyboard-shortcuts'>keyboard shortcuts</link>.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-mask-presentation'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='mask.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>A data field shown with a mask and a presentation</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        Data in default false color representation (left), with superimposed
        mask visualized with a red color (centre) and with shading presentation
        (right).
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <sect2 id='masks'>
    <title>Working with Masks</title>
    <para>
      The mask-related functions can be divided into three main groups:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Creation
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Masks are created by various types of marking functions, namely
            grain marking functions
            (<link linkend='grain-threshold'>Mark by Threshold</link>,
            <link linkend='grain-watershed'>Mark by Watershed</link>),
            defect marking functions
            (<link linkend='mask-of-outliers'>Mask of Outliers</link>,
            <link linkend='mark-scars'>Mark Scars</link>)
            and feature marking functions
            (<link linkend='mask-by-correlation'>Mask by Correlation</link>,
            <link linkend='facet-analysis'>Facet Analysis</link>,
            <link linkend='tip-certainty-map'>Certainty Map</link>).
            In addition, some general mask editting functions provide means to
            create masks from scratch.
          </para>
          <para>
            Masks are also used to mark invalid pixels in files imported from
            formats that distinguish between valid and invalid pixels since
            Gwyddion does not have a concept of invalid pixels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Application
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In general, the mask-covered area is considered to be the area of
            interest, i.e. the area to operate on.  This applies namely to
            statistical functions such as the
            <link linkend='stat-quantities'>Statstical Quantities tool</link>.
            Function
            <link linkend='remove-data-under-mask'>Remove Data Under Mask</link>
            replaces the data under mask, while the
            <link linkend='remove-grains'>Remove Grains tool</link> can perform
            such replacement for individual grains.  There are several functions
            for the examination of grain properties, see section
            <link linkend='grain-analysis-statistics'>Grain Statstics</link>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Some functions ask whether to consider the area under mask included
            or excluded (or ignore the mask), namely
            <link linkend='leveling'>leveling functions</link>.  Such choice is
            offered only if a mask is present on the data.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Editting
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A few basic mask operations, such as inversion or complete removal,
            are available in
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Mask</guisubmenu>
            </menuchoice>
            menu.  More advanced functions include the grain-oriented
            <link linkend='remove-grains'>Remove Grains tool</link> and
            <link linkend='grain-remove-thresholding'>Remove by Threshold</link>
            that provide different means to remove parts of the mask, as well
            as
            <link linkend='mask-editor'>Mask Editor tool</link> and
            <link linkend='mark-with'>Mark With</link>
            focused on general mask editting.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='mask-editor'>
    <title>
      Mask Editor Tool
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='gwy_mask_editor-24.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </title>
    <para>
      The Mask Editor is the basic mask modification tool.  It provides two
      groups of functions: editing of the mask by drawing shapes directly in
      the data window and global operations with the mask such as inversion
      or growing and shrinking.  The drawing operations are controlled by the
      buttons in the <guilabel>Editor</guilabel> group.
    </para>
    <para>
      Buttons in the <guilabel>Mode</guilabel> row select how the shape drawn
      in the data window will modify the mask:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Set
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_mask-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The mask is set to the drawn shape, discarding any mask already
            present.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Add
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_mask_add-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The mask is extended by the drawn shape (if there is no mask yet
            a mask is created).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Subtract
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_mask_subtract-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The drawn shape is cut out from the mask
            This function has no effect if there is no mask.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Intersect
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_mask_intersect-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The mask is set to the intersection of the drawn shape and the
            already present mask.
            This function has no effect if there is no mask.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Buttons in the <guilabel>Shape</guilabel> row control which shape is
      drawn on the mask.  The choices include rectangles, ellipses and thin
      lines.
    </para>
    <para>
      The basic global operation with masks, i.e. inversion, removal and
      filling the entire data field area with a mask are available in the
      <guilabel>Actions</guilabel> row.  Additional operations include:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guibutton>Grow</guibutton>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_mask_grow-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Extends the mask by <guilabel>Amount</guilabel> pixels on each
            side.  More precisely, the mask is extended by one pixel on each
            side and this is repeated <guilabel>Amount</guilabel> times.
          </para>
          <para>
            Normally, growing does not distinguish between individual parts of
            the mask.   Parts that grow so much that they touch therefore
            merge.  This can be prevented by <guilabel>Prevent grain merging
              by growing</guilabel> which makes individual parts of the mask
            stop growing once there is only one-pixel space between them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guibutton>Shrink</guibutton>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='gwy_mask_shrink-24.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Reduces the mask by <guilabel>Amount</guilabel> pixels from each
            side.  More precisely, the mask is reduced by one pixel from each
            side and this is repeated <guilabel>Amount</guilabel> times.
          </para>
          <para>
            The reduction may or may not occur from the data field borders.
            This is controlled by the <guilabel>Shrink from border</guilabel>
            check box.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='mark-with'>
    <title>Mark With</title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Mask</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Mark With</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Mark With can create or modify masks using another mask or data of the
      same dimensions.  The operations that can be applied to the current mask
      are the same as in the
      <link linkend='mask-editor'>Mask Editor tool</link>: creation,
      union, subtraction and intersection.  The source of the other mask can
      be one of the following:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Mask
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the simplest case, a mask can be combined with another mask
            using the specified logical operations.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Data
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the Data mode, another height field is used as the other mask
            source.  The mask consists of pixels within a range of heights,
            specified as relative values within the total range.  To use pixels
            outside a certain range for the masking, set the upper bound to a
            smaller value than the lower bound.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Presentation
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Presentation mode differs from Data mode only in that a
            presentation is used instead of the data.
          </para>
          <para>
            This is an exception to the rule stating that presentations are
            never used for further processing.  Sometimes it can be useful to
            mark, for instance, edges found on the data even though the
            corresponding presentation visualizes a quantity weird from the
            physical point of view.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
